HERE. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
WELCOME TO THE JULY 21ST REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS .
>> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
YES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN
PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
PRESENT SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN PRESIDENT MANDOLIN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SARDAR
SARDAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERYL PRESENT
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT SUPERVISOR WANG WANG
PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE RAMAKRISHNA LONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE
INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH
THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAMAKRISHNA LONI HAVE NEVER
CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE
RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR
TRADITIONAL HOMELANDS. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAW
MATERIAL OWNING COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE AS INDIGENOUS UNITED STATES?
>> ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I WOULD LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE
STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV AND TODAY THAT IS KALEENA MENDOZA
AND JEANETTE EGAN LAUGH. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? >> YES.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
WELCOMES YOUR ATTENDANCE HERE IN PERSON HERE IN THE BOARD'S
LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER ROOM 250 ON THE SECOND FLOOR OF CITY HALL.
WHEN YOU CAN'T BE HERE, THE PROCEEDINGS ARE AIRING LIVE ON
S.F. GOV TV'S LOCAL CABLE CHANNEL OR LIVE STREAMING AT
SFO VTV YORK. AS OF JULY 1ST A FULL BOARD IS
REQUIRED TO TAKE REMOTE PUBLIC COMMENT PURSUANT TO SB 707
DURING THE PUBLIC COMMENT PERIODS WE WILL PRIORITIZE
THOSE WHO HAVE JOINED US IN PERSON AND THEN HEAR FROM
OUR REMOTE CALLERS. AS A REMINDER THE BOARD
COMMITTEE MEETINGS ARE NOT REQUIRED TO TAKE PUBLIC REMOTE
PUBLIC COMMENT. THE BOARD HAS ALSO APPROVED A
RULE TO ADDRESS DISORDERLY PUBLIC COMMENT.
MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC MAY KEEP THEIR COMMENTS GERMANE TO
MATTERS WITHIN THE JURISDICTION OF THE BOARD OR THE SUBJECT
MATTER AND ANY COMMENTS THAT CONTAIN PERSONAL ATTACKS
HARASSMENT OR DISCRIMINATORY REMARKS SHALL BE REDIRECTED.
IN A FAILURE TO IMMEDIATELY REDIRECT THOSE COMMENTS WILL
RESULT IN THAT INDIVIDUAL'S FORFEITURE OF REMAINING TIME.
WE WILL TRANSITION TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
PLEASE REMEMBER TO ADDRESS YOUR COMMENTS TO THE BOARD AS A
WHOLE AND NOT TO INDIVIDUAL MEMBERS.
TO SUBMIT PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING SEND AN EMAIL TO
POST AT SFO GEO REORG OR VIA U.S. POSTAL SERVICE TO THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS NUMBER ONE.
DR. CARLTON BEGINS AT PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN
FRANCISCO CALIFORNIA NINE FOR 1 OR 2 TO MAKE A REASONABLE
ACCOMMODATION FOR A FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS
WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE.
PLEASE CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS
DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING (415) 554-5184 MEMBERS.
THAT CONCLUDES MY COMMUNICATION.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR MEETING MINUTES.
TODAY'S MEETING MINUTES FOR UP FOR APPROVAL ARE THE JUNE 16TH
BOARD MEETING. REGULAR MINUTES.
>> COULD I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED MOVED BY CHEN AND SECONDED BY CHERYL.
MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WANG WANG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR I THERE ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION
THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT AS
PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT AGENDA PLEASE
CALL ITEMS ONE THROUGH THREE ITEMS ONE THROUGH THREE ARE ON
CONSENT. THESE ARE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED
ROUTINE. IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY
BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ON THE CONSENT AGENDA
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WANG WANG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANAGEMENT HI MANAGEMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISE OR SADR SADR EITHER LEBANESE WITHOUT
OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK
LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL THE BUDGET ITEMS
FOUR THROUGH 19 TOGETHER ITEMS FOUR THROUGH 19 COMPRISE THE
ANNUAL BUDGET ITEM FOUR IS THE BUDGET AND APPROPRIATION
ORDINANCE APPROPRIATING ALL ESTIMATED RECEIPTS AND ALL
ESTIMATED EXPENDITURES FOR DEPARTMENTS OF THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AS OF JUNE 1ST, 2026 FOR THE
FISCAL YEAR ENDING JUNE 30TH 2027 AND JUNE 30TH 2028.
ITEM FIVE IS THE ANNUAL SALARY ORDINANCE ENUMERATING POSITIONS
IN THE ANNUAL BUDGET AND APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE FOR
THE FISCAL YEAR ENDING JUNE 30TH, 2027 AND JUNE 30TH 2028.
ITEM SIX IS ORDINANCE TO AMENDING ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO
AUTHORIZE THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR TO PAUSE, REDUCE
OR RETURN THE ANNUAL CONTRIBUTIONS BY THE
DEPARTMENTS AT CONTRACT FOR PUBLIC WORKS TO THE SAN
FRANCISCO SELF-INSURANCE 30 BOND FUND.
ITEM SEVEN IS AN ORDINANCE TO MODIFY THE BASELINE FUNDING
REQUIREMENTS FOR EARLY CARE AND EDUCATION PROGRAMS
IN FISCAL YEAR 2627 AND 2728 TO ENABLE THE CITY TO USE INTEREST
EARNED FROM THE EARLY CARE AND EDUCATION COMMERCIAL RENTS
TAX FOR THOSE BASELINE PROGRAMS ITEM EIGHT IS AN ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE HEALTH CODE TO SET PATIENT RATES FOR SERVICES
PROVIDED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH FOR FISCAL YEARS
2627 AND 2728. ITEM NINE IS ORDINANCE AMENDING
THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO INCREASE CERTAIN UTILITY METER
FEES AND AUTHORIZE THE COMPTROLLER TO ANNUALLY ADJUST
DEVICE FEES FOR WEIGHTS AND MEASURES AND UTILITY METERS
UP TO THE MAXIMUM ALLOWABLE UNDER STATE LAW.
ITEM TEN IS AN ORDINANCE TEMPORARILY SUSPENDING THE CAP
ON THE USE OF HOMELESSNESS GROSS RECEIPTS TAX REVENUES TO
FUND SHORT TERM RENTAL SUBSIDIES AND FINDING THAT THE
TEMP THAT TEMPORARILY ALLOWING FOR INCREASED EXPENDITURES ON
SHORT TERM RENTAL SUBSIDIES WILL FURTHER THE PURPOSES OF
OUR STATE OF THE ART CITY OUR HOME FUND ITEM 11 IS AN
ORDINANCE TO ADOPT THE NEIGHBORHOOD BEAUTIFICATION
AND GRAFFITI CLEANUP FUND TAX DESIGNATION SELENE TAX FOR TAX
YEAR 2026. >> ITEM 12 IS THE RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE THE FISCAL YEAR 2627 BUDGET OF THE OFFICE OF
COMMUNITY INVESTMENT IN INFRASTRUCTURE FOR OPERATING
AS A SUCCESSOR AGENCY TO THE REDEVELOPMENT AGENCY OF THE
CITY. AND APPROVING THE ISSUANCE OF
BONDS AND THE AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL PRINCIPAL AMOUNT OF
275 MILLION FOR THE PURPOSE OF FINANCING A PORTION OF THIS
ENFORCEABLE OBLIGATIONS. ITEM 13 IS A RESOLUTION TO
CONCUR WITH THE CONTROLLERS ESTABLISHMENT OF THE SUMER
PRICE INDEX FOR 2026 AND ADJUSTING THE ACCESS LINE
TAX FOR THE SAME RATE ITEM 14 IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE
THE PUBLIC LIBRARY TO ACCEPT AN EXPENDED 1.5 MILLION GRANT OF
IN-KIND GIFTS, SERVICES AND CASH MONEYS FROM THE
FRIENDS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC LIBRARY FOR DIRECT
SUPPORT FOR THE CHINATOWN BRANCH RENOVATION CAPITAL
PROJECT WITHIN THE PERIOD OF FISCAL YEARS 2627 THROUGH 2930.
ITEM 15 IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE ACCEPTANCE
AND EXPENDITURE OF RECURRING STATE GRANT FUNDS BY THE SAN
FRANCISCO DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH FOR FISCAL YEAR 2627.
ITEM 16 IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE FISCAL YEAR 2627
2728 EXPENDITURE PLAN FOR THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS
AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING FUND. ITEM 17 IS A RESOLUTION TO
CONCUR WITH THE COMPTROLLER CERTIFICATE IN THAT DEPARTMENT
SERVICES PREVIOUSLY APPROVED CAN BE PERFORMED BY PRIVATE
CONTRACTORS FOR A LOWER COST AND SIMILAR WORK PERFORMED BY
CITY AND COUNTY EMPLOYEES. ITEM 18 IS A RESOLUTION TO
CONCUR WITH THE COMPTROLLER CERTIFICATE IN THAT DEPARTMENT
SERVICES CAN BE PERFORMED BY PRIVATE CONTRACTORS FOR A LOWER
COST THAN SIMILAR WORK PERFORMED BY CITY EMPLOYEES FOR
PROTECTIVE PROTECTIVE SERVICES AND SECURITY SERVICES.
AND FINALLY, ITEM 19 IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE
RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT TO ISSUE AN AMENDED PERMIT
ALLOWING ANOTHER PLANET ENTERTAINMENT TO HOLD TICKETED
CONCERTS AT THE GOLDEN GATE POLO FIELDS TO TAKE PLACE ON
THE FRIDAY, SATURDAY AND SUNDAY EITHER FOLLOWING OR PROCEEDING
TO OUTSIDE LANDS FESTIVAL IN 27, 28 AND 29 IN EXCHANGE
FOR A MINIMUM PERMIT FEE OF 1.53 MILLION PER DAY FOR TWO
DAY EVENTS AND APPROXIMATELY 2.2 MILLION PER DAY FOR THREE
DAY EVENTS THROUGH 2029 AND WITH OPTIONS TO EXTEND THE
PERMIT UNTIL 2035. >> CHAIR CHAN THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AMANDO MY COLLEAGUES I PLAN TO RESERVE MY COMMENT
UNTIL NEXT WEEK ON OUR FINAL FINAL VOTE AND ALSO THE FINAL
FINAL BOARD MEETING BEFORE THE AUGUST RECESS.
I URGE YOU FOR YOUR YES VOTE ON TODAY'S FIRST VOTE ON THIS
BUDGET WHICH HAD UNANIMOUS VOTE TO RECOMMEND IT OUT OF OUR
BUDGET AND APPROPRIATIONS COMMITTEE.
I DO WANT TO TAKE A QUICK OPPORTUNITY HERE TO THANK ALL
THE MEMBERS OF THE BUDGET AND APPROPRIATIONS COMMITTEE
FOR THEIR HARD WORK. AND SO WITH THAT I WILL RESERVE
MY COMMENTS UNTIL NEXT WEEK. >> THANK YOU.
>> AND WITH THAT I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS.
>> OH, SUPERVISOR FIELDER, THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MIDDLEMEN.
COLLEAGUES, THIS BUDGET CLOSES A MASSIVE DEFICIT WITHOUT MASS
LAYOFFS. CERTAINLY NOT WITHOUT
TRADEOFFS. I'M STILL WRESTLING WITH
GROWING POLICE PAY BY 14% OVER FOUR YEARS ISN'T WHERE I WOULD
HAVE PUT OUR LIMITED DOLLARS. HOWEVER, IN A YEAR WITH LOOMING
FEDERAL CUTS AND NO EASY OPTIONS, THIS BOARD HELD THE
LINE ON CRITICAL SAFETY NET PROGRAMS THAT TENS OF THOUSANDS
OF SAN FRANCISCANS DEPEND ON. >> AND THAT IS A REAL WIN.
THIS BUDGET IS NOT EVERYTHING MANY OF US WOULD HAVE WANTED
BUT IT'S A FIGHT WORTH CONTINUING INTO NEXT YEAR'S
BUDGET. >> THIS WIN IS DUE IN LARGE
PART TO THE ADVOCACY, THE HIGH LEVEL OF ORGANIZATION AND THE
UNITY AMONG COMMUNITY GROUPS AND LABOR THE PEOPLE WHO
DELIVER OUR CITY'S SERVICES EVERY DAY THAT ALLOWED US TO
STAVE OFF THE DEEPEST CUTS AND KEEP CRITICAL SOCIAL
SERVICE PROGRAMS RUNNING FOR THE PEOPLE WHO RELY ON THEM.
>> THAT KIND OF OUTCOME ALSO DEPENDS ON PARTNERSHIP INSIDE
THIS BUILDING. I WANT TO THANK YOU COLLEAGUES
FOR CARING AND SUPPORTING DISTRICT NINE'S PRIORITIES
THROUGHOUT THIS PROCESS WHILE I WAS OUT ON LEAVE.
IN PARTICULAR, I WANT TO RECOGNIZE BUDGET CHAIR CHEN,
SUPERVISOR CHEN AND SUPERVISOR WALTON ALONG WITH THEIR STAFF
FRANCES SHEA, JACKIE PRAGER AND TRACY BROWN FOR THEIR WORK
IN PARTNERSHIP WITH MY STAFF IN MAKING SURE OUR DISTRICT'S
NEEDS WERE HEARD AND MET AT EVERY STAGE.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK MY OWN STAFF JENNIFER FERRIGNO
AND SHEILA CHUNG HAGAN WHO WORKED DILIGENTLY TO MOVE OUR
PRIORITIES FORWARD MAKING THIS OUTCOME POSSIBLE.
>> THE DILIGENCE WITH WHICH THIS BOARD WORKED THROUGH SUCH
A DIFFICULT BUDGET IS A TESTAMENT TO THE COLLABORATIVE
LEADERSHIP OF BUDGET CHAIR CHAN AND THE COMMITMENT OF THE
ENTIRE BOARD. NEXT YEAR PROMISES TO BE AN
EVEN TOUGHER BUDGET YEAR. WE WILL STILL BE FACING FEDERAL
CUTS AND CONTINUED ATTACKS FROM THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION.
MY HOPE IS THAT WE TAKE THE WORK THAT WHAT WORKED WHAT
WORKED THIS YEAR LISTENING DEEPLY TO COMMUNITY AND LABOR
PARTNERS AND HOLDING THE LINE ON THE PROGRAMS PEOPLE DEPEND
ON MOST AND CARRY THAT SAME APPROACH INTO NEXT YEAR'S
BUDGET. AND WITH THAT COLLEAGUES I'LL
BE VOTING IN SUPPORT OF THESE ITEMS AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE
THESE ITEMS. SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST
READING AND THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 20.
>> ITEM NUMBER 20 IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE ENVIRONMENT HEALTH, LABOR AND EMPLOYMENT
PART PLANNING POLICE PUBLIC WORKS SUBDIVISION
TRANSPORTATION AND BUILDING INSPECTION COMMISSION CODES TO
MODIFY NUMEROUS REPORTING REQUIREMENTS AFFIRM THE SQUAD
DETERMINATION AND MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 20.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON I'M SO
SORRY. >> WALTON NO.
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I. SUPERVISOR CHAN.
CHAN NO SUPERVISOR CHEN. CHEN I.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY. DORSEY I.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER. FIELDER.
NO. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
MAHMOOD I. SUPERVISOR BENJAMIN HI.
MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR. MELGAR NO SUPERVISOR SADR.
SADR THERE ARE SEVEN EYES AND FOUR NOS.
THE SUPERVISORS WALTON CHAN FIELDER AND MELGAR VOTED NO.
>> THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 21.
>> ITEM NUMBER 21 IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING
CODE TO REDUCE INCLUSIONARY AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROGRAM
REQUIREMENTS FOR PROJECTS OF 25 UNITS OR MORE.
DELETE AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROGRAM REQUIREMENTS FOR
PROJECTS UNDER 25 UNITS. ALLOW ALL PROJECTS TO DEDICATE
LAND TO THE CITY AS AN ALTERNATIVE TO PAYMENT OF THE
INCLUSIONARY HOUSING PROGRAM FEE.
ADOPT A PROCESS FOR PROJECTS TO REQUEST A MODIFICATION TO
CONDITIONS OF APPROVAL RELATED TO INCLUSIONARY AFFORDABLE
HOUSING PROGRAM REQUIREMENT. DELETE CERTAIN ARTICLE FOUR
IMPACT FEES AND ADOPT CONFORMING AMENDMENTS TO
VARIOUS CONDITIONS TO VARIOUS SECTIONS OF THE PLANNING CODE.
AMENDING THE BUILDING CODE TO REDUCE PLANNING CODE ARTICLE
FOUR DEVELOPMENT IMPACT FEES AND ALLOW DEFERRAL OF PAYMENTS
OF SUCH FEES. AND AMENDING THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE TO ADOPT CONFORMING AMENDMENTS TO THE REQUIREMENTS
OF THE CITY WIDE AFFORDABLE HOUSING FUND.
TO AFFIRM THE SCORE DETERMINATION AND MAKE THE
APPROPRIATE FINDINGS, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL AN ITEM 21.
>> SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I. SUPERVISOR WALTON NO WALTON NO
SUPERVISOR WANG. WANG I.
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I. SUPERVISOR CHEN.
CHEN. NO SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
DORSEY I. SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
FIELDER I. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I.
>> SUPERVISOR I MANDARIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SARDAR EITHER NINE EYES AND TWO
NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON AND CHEN VOTING NO.
>> AND THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 20 TWO.
>> ITEM NUMBER 22 IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO STATE THAT IT IS CITY POLICY TO
EXPAND THE AVAILABILITY OF SITE BASED PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING THAT PROHIBITS ONSITE ILLICIT DRUG USE AMONG
RESIDENTS TO MEET THE DEMAND OF PEOPLE EXPERIENCING
HOMELESSNESS WHO PREFER SUCH A RESIDENTIAL OPTION.
>> REQUIRE THAT CITY FUNDING FOR NEW SITE BASED PCH FOR
PEOPLE EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS BE USED FOR DRUG
FREE PASSAGE. REQUIRE THE DEPARTMENT OF
HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING TO SURVEY RESIDENTS
AND REQUIRE HSA TO ADOPT RULES AND REGULATIONS.
ESTABLISH ESTABLISH STANDARDS AND PROTOCOLS FOR EVICTIONS.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 22.
>> SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I. SUPERVISOR WALTON O.
WALTON NO SUPERVISOR WANG WANG I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN NO
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN NO SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR GENTLEMAN HI. AMENDMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SARDAR I THERE ARE SEVEN EYES
AND FOUR NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON CHEN, CHEN AND FIELD ARE
VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM 23. >> ITEM NUMBER 23 IS AN
ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE APPROXIMATELY 1.9 MILLION OF
BOARDING OF PRISONERS REVENUE AND APPROXIMATELY 14 MILLION TO
OVERTIME SALARIES AND TO APPROPRIATE APPROXIMATELY 12.1
MILLION FROM A RETIREMENT FRINGE BENEFITS VEHICLES
AND VARIOUS CAPITAL PROJECTS AND WORK ORDERS IN THE
SHERIFF'S OFFICE TO SUPPORT THE DEPARTMENT'S PROJECTED
INCREASES IN OVERTIME IN FISCAL YEAR 2526 PLEASE CALL THE ROLL
ON ITEM 23. SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON HI WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WANG I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR GENTLEMAN I.
AMENDMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR
EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 24 ITEM
24 IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE SECOND AMENDMENT BETWEEN
THE CHILDREN'S COUNCIL OF SAN FRANCISCO AND THE DEPARTMENT OF
EARLY CHILDHOOD FOR THE PROVISION OF THE EARLY CARE
WORK FIRST COMPENSATION AND ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES TO
SUPPORT THE CITY'S IMPLEMENTATION OF THE CITYWIDE
PLAN FOR EARLY CARE AND EDUCATION, WORKFORCE
DEVELOPMENT AND COMPENSATION INITIATIVES INCREASE THE
AGREEMENT FOR A TOTAL APPROXIMATE AMOUNT OF 230
MILLION FOR A TERM OF OCTOBER 1ST 2022 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2027
. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS SAME
HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER 25. >> ITEM NUMBER 25 IS THE
RESOLUTION TO APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF
PROPERTY AND ON BEHALF OF THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS
IN SUPPORT OF HOUSING TO ENTER INTO A LEASE OF REAL PROPERTY
LOCATED AT 125 BAYSHORE BOULEVARD WITH W Y EL ORIAN
PROPERTIES FOR INITIAL TERM OF TEN YEARS WITH TWO FIVE YEAR
OPTIONS TO EXTEND ANTICIPATED TO COMMENCE ON JULY FIRST 2026
FOR USE BY THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF
HOUSING FOR EMERGENCY SHELTER PURPOSES AT INITIAL ANNUAL BASE
RENT OF APPROXIMATELY 655,000 WITH 3% ANNUAL INCREASES TO A
FIRM SEQUEL DETERMINATION AND MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS SO SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEMS
26 THROUGH 28 TOGETHER. >> ITEM 26 IS THE RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE THE SECOND AMENDMENT WITH CANON USA FOR COPIER
MACHINE LEASES, RENTALS AND PURCHASES TO INCREASE THE
CONTRACT FOR A TOTAL AMOUNT OF 15.3 MILLION WITH NO CHANGES TO
THE CONTRACT TERM OF APRIL 1ST 2024 THROUGH A DECEMBER 15TH
2030. ITEM 27 IS A RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE AN AGREEMENT AN AMENDMENT BETWEEN THE CITY
AND SIGLO SUPPLY FOR PLUMBING SUPPLIES EXTENDING THE TERM BY
TWO YEARS THROUGH NOVEMBER 30TH 2031 AND INCREASE THE CONTRACT
FOR TWO NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF 15.5 MILLION.
AND FINALLY ITEM 28 IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE
DEPARTMENT OF TECHNOLOGY TO ENTER INTO THE FIRST AMENDMENT
TO THE AGREEMENT WITH ZONES LLC FOR MICROSOFT ENTERPRISE
PRODUCTS TO INCREASE THE CONTRACT FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT
OF 115 MILLION AND TO EXTEND THE TERM FOR A TOTAL TERM OF
SEPTEMBER 1ST 2023 THROUGH AUGUST 31ST 2029 WITH THE
OPTION OF THREE ONE YEAR EXTENSIONS AND WE CAN TAKE
THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL OUT A
NUMBER 29. >> ITEM NUMBER 29 IS A
RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE
GENERAL MANAGER OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES
COMMISSION TO EXECUTE AMENDMENT NUMBER ONE TO THE JOINT
EXERCISE OF POWERS AGREEMENT FOR SEWER SERVICE WITH THE CITY
OF BRISBANE AND GUADALUPE VALLEY MUNICIPAL IMPROVEMENT
DISTRICT INCREASING THE DURATION OF THE ORIGINAL
AGREEMENT TO DECEMBER 31ST, 2027.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEMS
30 AND 31 TOGETHER. >> ITEM 31 IS A RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE PURCHASE AND SALE AGREEMENT
BETWEEN THE CITY AND PACIFIC GAS AND ELECTRIC COMPANY FOR
THE ACQUISITION OF RURAL PROPERTY LOCATED AT 5000
HUNTERS POINT BOULEVARD IN THE BAYVIEW NEIGHBORHOOD FOR THE
AMOUNT THOUSAND PLACING THE PROPERTY UNDER THE JURISDICTION
OF THE RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT AND MAKING
APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. AND ITEM 31 IS A RESOLUTION
AND APPROVING A PURCHASE AND SALE AGREEMENT WITH PACIFIC
GAS AND ELECTRIC COMPANY IN THE AMOUNT OF 950,000 GRANTING
JANIE AND EASEMENT WITH SUBSURFACE UTILITIES IN JOHN
MCLAREN PARK UNDER VISITATION AVENUE AND MANSEL STREET
AND MAKING THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> TAKE THESE SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED AND PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 32.
>> ITEM NUMBER 32 IS A RESOLUTION AUTHORIZING THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO
ACCEPT AN IN-KIND GIFT OF CONSULTING SERVICES PROVIDED BY
SEVEN FUZE FELLOWS THROUGH THE FUZE FELLOWS PROGRAM VALUED AT
2,520,000 FROM FUZE, A CORPORATE.
FOR THE TERM TO COMMENCE ON AUGUST 1ST, 2026 AND TO EXPIRE
OCTOBER 20TH 2028 TO STRENGTHEN COORDINATION, STRATEGY
AND SYSTEMS ACROSS PUBLIC HEALTH, HOUSING, HOMELESSNESS
AND HUMAN SERVICES. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER THREE.
>> ITEM NUMBER 33 IS A RESOLUTION APPROVING THE PORT
COMMISSION LEASE WITH JP F 1300 BATTERY FOR A SINGLE STORY
RESTAURANT SPACE AN OUTDOOR DINING AREA LOCATED AT 1300
BATTERY STREET FOR A TERM EXPIRING ON MAY 5TH 2046 FOR A
MONTHLY BASE RENT OF 5000 FOR A TOTAL BASE RENT OF
APPROXIMATELY 1.5 MILLION. >> SAME HOUSE.
SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 40.
>> ITEM 34. ITEM 34 IS A RESOLUTION
AUTHORIZING THE PORT TO EXECUTE THE FIRST AMENDMENT TO THE
MANAGEMENT AGREEMENT WITH PASHA AUTOMOTIVE SERVICES TO
DISCONTINUE A 50,000 MONTHLY MANAGEMENT FEE PAID BY THE
PORT. ADOPT REVISED REVENUE SHARING
AND SPECIAL EVENT PROVISIONS AND RESTRUCTURE THE EXCLUSIVE
USE OF THE PORT'S PIER EIGHT TERMINAL SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED
AND PLEASE CALL ITEMS 35 AND 36 TOGETHER.
>> ITEM 35 IS A RESOLUTION APPROVING AND AUTHORIZING THE
FIRST AMENDMENT TO THE LOAN AGREEMENT BETWEEN MAUI CD
AND 1234 GREAT HIGHWAY LLC TO FINANCE PRE-DEVELOPMENT COSTS
ASSOCIATED WITH THE DEVELOPMENT OF MULTIFAMILY RESIDENTIAL
PROJECT AFFORDABLE TO LOW INCOME AND FORMERLY HOME
HOMELESS SENIORS ON THE PROPERTY LOCATED AT 1234 1270
AND 1280 GREAT HIGHWAY IN THE TOTAL AMOUNT NOT TO EXCEED
APPROXIMATELY 27,000,036 IS A RESOLUTION APPROVING
AND AUTHORIZING MAUI CD TO ENTER INTO A GROUND LEASE FOR
1939 MARKET STREET WITH MERCY HOUSING CALIFORNIA 109 FOR A
LEASE TERM OF 75 YEARS AND 124 YEAR FOUR YEAR OPTION TO EXTEND
AND AN ANNUAL BASE RENT OF 15,000 TO CONSTRUCT A 187 UNIT
MULTIFAMILY RENTAL HOUSING DEVELOPMENT AFFORDABLE TO LOW
INCOME HOUSING HOUSEHOLDS. >> SAME HOUSE SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
PLEASE CALL ITEM 37. >> ITEM NUMBER 37 IS AN
ORDINANCE AMENDING THE PLANNING CODE TO INCREASE THE NUMBER OF
GUEST ROOMS FOR HOTEL USES PERMITTED AS A CONDITIONAL USE
AND RH TWO RH THREE ROOM ONE R AND RM3RM FOR ARTICLE ONE
AND ARTIOLE. DISTRICTS FROM FIVE TO FEWER
ROOMS TO TEN OR FEWER ROOMS AND MAKING THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 38.
>> ITEM NUMBER 38 IS AN ORDINANCE AMENDING THE PUBLIC
WORKS CODE TO WAIVE BANNER AND INSPECTION FEES FOR CERTAIN
NONPROFIT ORGANIZATIONS IN ALL NCDS AND TDS R T AND R T O C
DISTRICTS AND AFFIRMING THE SCORE DETERMINATION.
>> SAME HOUSE AND CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING PLEASE CALL ITEM 39 ITEM NUMBER 39 IS
AN ORDINANCE AMENDING THE FIRE AND PUBLIC WORKS CODES TO WAIVE
APPLICATION REVIEW AND PROCESSING FEES FOR PERMITS
TO ABATE VIOLATIONS RELATED TO THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING
INSPECTIONS, INTERNAL QUALITY CONTROL AUDIT AMNESTY PROGRAM
AND AFFIRMING THE SECRET DETERMINATION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER
40. >> ITEM NUMBER 40 IS AN
ORDINANCE AMENDING THE POLICE CODE TO PROVIDE PENALTIES FOR
THE PROHIBITED DISCHARGE OF FIREWORKS INCLUDING THAT A
FIRST OFFENSE IS PUNISHABLE AS AN INFRACTION WITH A FINE NOT
LESS THAN $125 OR MORE OR MORE THAN $250.
ANY SECOND AND ANY SUBSEQUENT OFFENSES WITHIN FIVE YEARS OF A
PRIOR OFFENSE ARE PUNISHABLE AS MISDEMEANORS WITH A FINE NOT
LESS THAN 250 OR MORE THAN 750 OR IMPRISONMENT IN THE COUNTY
JAIL OF NOT MORE THAN SIX MONTHS OR BY BOTH SUCH FINE
AND IMPRISONMENT. >> SUPERVISOR WONG COLLEAGUES
THIS ORDINANCE COMES BEFORE THE FULL BOARD WITH THE
RECOMMENDATION OF THE PUBLIC SAFETY AND NEIGHBORHOOD
SERVICES COMMITTEE WHICH APPROVED IT ON JULY 9TH.
THE TERM SAFE AND SANE CAN CREATE A DANGEROUSLY MISLEADING
IMPRESSION THESE FIREWORKS MAY BE LOWER POWERED AND APPROVED
BY THE STATE FIRE MARSHAL BUT THEY ARE NOT HARMLESS
ESPECIALLY IN A DENSE CITY LIKE SAN FRANCISCO.
SPARKLERS, FOUNTAINS AND OTHER CONSUMER FIREWORKS CAN CAUSE
SERIOUS BURNS, IGNITE CLOTHING, INJURE EYES AND START
VEGETATION OR STRUCTURE FIRES. FIREWORKS MARKETED AS IF INSANE
HAVE CAUSED SEVERE INJURIES AND EVEN DEATHS.
>> CHILDREN ARE ESPECIALLY VULNERABLE AND ADULT
SUPERVISION CANNOT ELIMINATE THE RISKS CREATED BY EXTREME
HEAT SPARKS DRY CONDITIONS MISUSE OR DEFECTIVE PRODUCTS.
SAN FRANCISCO ALREADY PROHIBITS THE DISCHARGE OF FIREWORKS
INCLUDING THOSE MARKETED UNDER THIS CATEGORY.
>> BUT OUR LOCAL LAWS DOES NOT CURRENTLY GIVE OFFICERS A CLEAR
AND PRACTICAL WAY TO ENFORCE THAT PROHIBITION.
THIS ORDINANCE WOULD MAKE A FIRST OFFENSE INFRACTION WITH A
FINE BETWEEN $125 AND $250 LESS THAN A STOP SIGN IN OR SPEEDING
TICKET. STRONGER PENALTIES WOULD APPLY
ONLY TO REPEAT OFFENDERS WITHIN FIVE YEARS.
THIS IS NOT AN ARREST FIRST APPROACH OR AN EFFORT TO
CRIMINALIZE CELEBRATION. IT IS ABOUT ENSURING THAT THE
LAW HAS A REAL AND PROPORTIONATE CONSEQUENCE
DETERRENCE WORKS ONLY WHEN PEOPLE BELIEVE THERE IS A
REASONABLE CHANCE THEY'LL BE CITED.
RIGHT NOW OFFICERS MAY STOP THE ACTIVITY BUT OFTEN HAVE NO
CLEAR LOCAL CITATION THEY CAN ISSUE THAT MAKES THE LAW EASIER
TO IGNORE AND REINFORCES THE IMPRESSION THAT FIREWORKS ARE
ACCEPTABLE IN SAN FRANCISCO. THESE FIREWORKS ALSO AFFECT
MORE THAN THE PERSON LIGHTING THEM THEY CAN FRIGHTEN PETS,
DISRUPT FAMILIES AND BE ESPECIALLY HARMFUL TO VETERANS
PEOPLE, PTSD AND PEOPLE WITH SENSORY SENSITIVITIES.
A SINGLE SPARK CAN ALSO THREATEN NEARBY HOMES
AND RESIDENTS. THE 4TH OF JULY WEEKEND ALSO
SHOWED THE BROADER STRAIN CAUSED BY FIREWORKS ACTIVITY
MEDICAL INCIDENTS ON JULY 4TH AND FIFTH WERE ABOUT DOUBLE THE
NUMBER SEEN DURING THE SAME PERIOD OF LAST YEAR WHILE THE
FIRE DEPARTMENT RECEIVED ROUGHLY 576 CALLS IN 24 HOURS
AND RESPONDED TO TWO HOUSE FIRES CAUSED BY FIREWORKS.
WE DO NOT NEED TO WAIT FOR ANOTHER SERIOUS INJURY OR FIRE
TO ACT. EVEN LOWER POWERED CONSUMER
FIREWORKS CAN CAUSE PERMANENT HARM.
THIS ORDINANCE GIVES THE CITY A PRACTICAL TOOL TO CHANGE
BEHAVIOR BEFORE SOMEBODY IS BURNED.
A HOME CATCHES FIRE OR A NEIGHBORHOOD IS PUT AT RISK.
IT SHOULD BE PAIRED WITH EDUCATION, AN OUTREACH FOR
ENFORCEMENT AND TRANSPARENCY. >> BUT LEAVING THE LAW WITH A
WORK WITHOUT A WORKABLE CONSEQUENCE DOES NOT PROTECT
OUR COMMUNITIES. I'D LIKE TO THANK THE CERTAIN
GOOD POLICE DEPARTMENT FOR WORKING WITH US ON THIS
LEGISLATION AND BRINGING UP THIS POTENTIAL LEGISLATION AS
WELL AS THE FIRE DEPARTMENT FOR SHARING DATA ON IT, THE SPCA
FOR COMING OUT TO SPEAK ON FIREWORKS IMPACTS ON PETS
AND THE VETERANS COMMUNITY FOR COMING OUT.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK SUPERVISORS CHERYL MELGAR CIDER
DORSEY MANAGEMENT FOR CO-SPONSORING THIS LEGISLATION
AND I RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU
PRESIDENT VANDEMAN FIRST OFF THE FINDINGS IN THIS ORDINANCE
READ QUOTE THE PENALTY STRUCTURE ESTABLISHED BY THIS
ORDINANCE IS CONSISTENT WITH THE RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE
CIVIL GRAND JURY. UNQUOTE.
THAT IS FALSE. A CIVIL GRAND JURY DID NOT
RECOMMEND ANY PENALTY STRUCTURE FOR FIREWORKS THAT ARE ALREADY
PROHIBITED LOCALLY. >> THEY ACTUALLY RECOMMEND DATA
COLLECTION A TASK FORCE AND PUBLIC EDUCATION.
ADDITIONALLY, CALIFORNIA HEALTH AND SAFETY CODE ALREADY
PROHIBITS DANGEROUS FIREWORKS AS IF PD DOES HAVE THE ABILITY
TO ENFORCE STATE LAW AS OF PD COMMUNICATIONS AROUND THIS PAST
4TH OF JULY NOTED THAT FIREWORKS THAT EXPLODE GO INTO
THE AIR OR UNCONTROLLABLY MOVE ON THE GROUND CAN LEAD TO A
CITATION OR AN ARREST. THE CURRENT LOCAL FIREWORKS
ORDINANCE PROHIBITS SMALLER FIREWORKS.
THIS ORDINANCE IMPOSES A NEW FLAT FINE OF $125 TO $250 FOR A
FIRST OFFENSE RISING TO $750 AND A MISDEMEANOR UP TO SIX
MONTHS IN JAIL FOR A SECOND OFFENSE WITHIN FIVE YEARS.
>> STATE LAW ALREADY HAS AN ENFORCEMENT MECHANISM FOR
ILLEGAL AND DANGEROUS FIREWORKS SO THIS ORDINANCE COULD ALLOW
JAIL TIME FOR USE OF SMALL AND INSUBSTANTIAL FIREWORKS
EVEN SPARKLERS. >> SIX MONTHS IN JAIL IS A LONG
TIME FOR A SPARKLER IF AN ENFORCEMENT MECHANISM IS WHAT
THIS ORDINANCE SEEKS, IT WOULD MAKE BETTER SENSE TO FOLLOW THE
PENALTY STRUCTURE ALREADY IMPOSED FOR FAR RELATED
OFFENSES $100 FOR THE FIRST VIOLATION UP TO $200 FOR A
SECOND OFFENSE WITHIN A YEAR AND UP TO $500 FOR ADDITIONAL
VIOLATIONS WITHIN ONE YEAR OF THE SUBSEQUENT VIOLATION.
SO I'M CONCERNED THAT THIS LAW WILL RUIN LIVES OF PRIMARILY
YOUNG PEOPLE FROM LOW INCOME HOUSEHOLDS AND COMMUNITIES OF
COLOR AND ACTUALLY MAKE OUR COMMUNITIES LESS SAFE IN DOING
SO. AND SO I WILL BE VOTING NO ON
THIS ITEM. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON ITEM 40 SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR
WALTON NO WALTON NO SUPERVISOR WANG WANG I SUPERVISOR CHEN
CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FILTER FILTER NO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN RIGHT MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO
NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON INFIELDER VOTING NO THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO
OUR 2:30 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER. >> ALL RIGHT ARE 230 SPECIAL
ORDER EACH IS A RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS
SERVICE WITHIN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO
AND TODAY WE WILL START WITH DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR CHERYL
THANK YOU. >> PRESIDENT MENDELSOHN WOOD
MARY LINDA, PLEASE. WELL, WHY DON'T YOU REMAIN
SEATED FOR A MOMENT AND I'M GOING TO TALK ABOUT YOU FOR A
SECOND. >> COLLEAGUES, TODAY I'M
HONORED TO COMMEND MARY LINDY FOR HER DEDICATED SERVICE TO
SAN FRANCISCO'S SENIOR COMMUNITY CULMINATING WITH HER
RETIREMENT AS THE CEO OF HERITAGE ON THE MARINA.
HERITAGE HAS SERVED SAN FRANCISCO'S SENIORS SINCE 1853,
STANDING AS ONE OF THE CITY'S OLDEST AND MOST STORIED
NONPROFIT ORGANIZATIONS AND A VITAL HOME FOR OLDER ADULTS
IN OUR COMMUNITY. >> MARY GREW UP IN A LARGE
FAMILY IN EASTERN PENNSYLVANIA AND PURSUED A CAREER
IN NURSING, EARNING HER BACHELOR'S DEGREE FROM EASTERN
MENNONITE UNIVERSITY AND HER MASTER'S DEGREE IN NURSING FROM
DREXEL WITH A CONCENTRATION IN EXECUTIVE LEADERSHIP
IN ORGANIZATIONAL DESIGN. >> NOW SHE BEGAN HER CAREER AS
A NEURO CRITICAL CARE NURSE AT TWO OF THE COUNTRY'S MOST
RESPECTED INSTITUTIONS JOHN HOPKINS HOSPITAL
AND MASSACHUSETTS GENERAL HOSPITAL BEFORE FINDING HER
TRUE CALLING IN SENIOR CARE. SINCE 1990 EIGHT, MARY HAS
DEVOTED HER CAREER TO SERVING OLDER ADULTS, ADVANCING THROUGH
ROLES AS AN EDUCATOR, DIRECTOR OF NURSING NURSING HOME
ADMINISTRATOR AND CONTINUING CARE RETIREMENT COMMUNITY
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR WHO ACROSS PENNSYLVANIA AND CALIFORNIA.
BEFORE ARRIVING IN SAN FRANCISCO, MARY SERVED AS
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF ST PAUL'S TOWERS IN OAKLAND WHERE SHE
GUIDED THE COMMUNITY SAFELY THROUGH THE FIRST YEAR OF COVID
19 WITH ZERO OUTBREAK EARNED RECOGNITION AS A QUOTE GREAT
PLACE TO WORK IN AGING SERVICES AND PROTECTED RESIDENTS
AND STAFF DURING ONE OF THE MOST CHALLENGING PERIODS
IN SENIOR CARE HISTORY. NOW HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, MARY
JOINED HERITAGE ON THE MARINA AS CEO IN MARCH 2021 BRINGING
VISION AND ENERGY TO AN ORGANIZATION SERVING SOME OF
SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST CHERISHED RESIDENTS.
DURING HER TENURE SHE LED HERITAGE THROUGH SIGNIFICANT
TRANSFORMATION REDUCING OPERATING EXPENSES BY $1.7
MILLION IN HER FIRST YEAR. >> SHE ALSO PARTNERED WITH THE
BOARD TO DOUBLE THE ORGANIZATION'S REVENUE
GENERATING SQUARE FOOTAGE FUNDAMENTALLY RESHAPING THE
IMPACT OF HERITAGE INTO ITS CONTEMPORARY SUCCESS.
SHE'S ALSO A PUBLISHED AUTHOR AND SCHOLAR CONTRIBUTING TO
NURSING AND SENIOR CARE LITERATURE WHICH REFLECTS HER
LIFELONG COMMITMENT TO ADVANCING THE FIELD BEYOND JUST
HER OWN ORGANIZATION. SHE'S ALSO SERVED THE BROADER
SENIOR CARE FIELD THROUGH MULTIPLE LEADING CALIFORNIA
COMMITTEES AND AS A LEADERSHIP COACH.
THROUGH THE ASSOCIATION'S EMERGE PROGRAM.
NOW IT MUST ALSO BE MENTIONED THAT MARY IS A VERY PROUD
MOTHER TO HER TWO SONS THEODORE AND QUINN AND TO AUGGIE, HER
PUPPY ALL OF WHOM WE SUSPECT ARE VERY MUCH LOOKING FORWARD
TO HAVING HER CLOSER TO HOME BACK IN MARYLAND.
>> BUT WE ARE NOT SO HAPPY AS THEY ARE BECAUSE WE HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO WHETHER IT IS ME YOU HAD THE PLEASURE TO WORK WITH
YOU OR THE RESIDENTS OF HERITAGE, MANY OF WHOM I SEE
HERE IN THE AUDIENCE TODAY HAVE THE PLEASURE OF BENEFITING FROM
YOUR TIRELESS ENERGY, YOUR COMPASSION, YOUR KINDNESS
AND YOUR WARMTH. SAN FRANCISCO IS FOR SURE
LOSING A LIGHT IN YOU BUT BALTIMORE IS GAINING ONE.
AND TO ME THE GREATEST GIFT YOU HAVE GIVEN US IS THE ENDURING
LEGACY THAT HERITAGE WILL HAVE AS IT CONTINUES ON INTO THE
FUTURE. SO THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMPASSION. MOST IMPORTANTLY, THANK YOU FOR
YOUR COMMITMENT TO ENSURING THAT SAN FRANCISCO'S SENIORS
CAN LIVE WITH DIGNITY AND LIVE WITH JOY.
>> WE WISH YOU ALL THE BEST AS WE BEGIN THIS NEXT CHAPTER WITH
YOUR RETIREMENT. >> MARY, CONGRATULATIONS
AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL I WOULD BE REMISS IF I DID NOT ALSO
CONGRATULATE MARY AND THANK HER FOR HER KINDNESS TO BERNADETTE
ELEANOR BURKE WHO WERE MY GODPARENTS AND WHO FINISHED
THEIR LIVES AT THE HERITAGE AND HAD A WONDERFUL TIME WITH
HER AND LOVED HER VERY MUCH. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SO MUCH, SUPERVISOR CHERYL.
I'M TRULY HONORED AND I'M A LITTLE OVERWHELMED BY ALL OF
THAT. AND I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU FOR
YOUR ONGOING SUPPORT IN DISTRICT TWO.
WE HAVE REALLY BEEN BENEFICIARIES OF THAT.
FOR ME IT'S THE END OF A LONG CAREER AND I'M INCREDIBLY
GRATEFUL GRATEFUL THAT I WAS CALLED TO THIS WORK.
>> WHEN I FIRST GOT INTO THIS FIELD MY HEART WAS SIMPLY DRAWN
TO SUPPORTING AND SERVING SENIORS AS THEY ENTERED THE
LAST DECADES OF THEIR LIVES. >> BUT I QUICKLY REALIZED THAT
I WAS GETTING THE BETTER END OF THE DEAL.
I HAVE LEARNED AND GROWN SO MUCH FROM THE PEOPLE I SERVED.
I'M GRATEFUL TO KNOW THE RESIDENTS I SERVE LEARNING FROM
THEIR STORIES AND RICH HISTORIES AND GRATEFUL TO
WITNESS THE DAILY DEDICATION AND COMPASSION OF OUR STAFF.
>> I'M TRULY GRATEFUL FOR THOSE RELATIONSHIPS.
THE PEOPLE IN OUR COMMUNITY ARE THE ONES WHO INSPIRED ME
AND THEY ARE TRULY THE ONES BEHIND EVERY DECISION THAT WE
MADE AND EVERY GOOD THING THAT WE ACHIEVED.
IN RECOGNIZING ME TODAY YOU'RE RECOGNIZING THOSE RELATIONSHIPS
AND THE QUIET DEDICATION AND BEHIND THE SCENES WORK THAT
I'VE BEEN SO PRIVILEGED TO LEAD .
IT WAS A COLLECTIVE EFFORT TO REACH THE MILESTONE THAT
MATTERS THE MOST AND YOU MENTIONED IT WORKING TO PROTECT
OUR COMMUNITY AND SECURE HOUSING FOR OUR SAN FRANCISCO
SENIORS IN PERPETUITY. >> HERITAGE ON THE MARINA
REFLECTS THE HEART AND SOUL OF SAN FRANCISCO.
AND THIS COMMENDATION IS A DIRECT REFLECTION OF THE STAFF
AND RESIDENTS WHO MAKE HERITAGE SO SPECIAL.
>> IT HAS BEEN MY ABSOLUTE PRIVILEGE TO SERVE THEM.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
AND YOU CAN USE UP NEXT DISTRICT FOR SUPERVISOR WONG.
>> CAN WE HAVE ART WITH ELDERS COME UP GO GOOD AFTERNOON
AND PRESENT AND COLLEAGUES. >> TODAY WE HONOR A PROGRAM
THAT ENRICHES THE JOURNEY OF AGING AND A LEADER WHOSE WORK
REFLECTS THE VERY BEST OF DISTRICT FOUR IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AS WE CELEBRATE DISABILITY PRIDE MONTH, I'M HONORED TO
RECOGNIZE OUR ELDERS AND EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR MARK
CAMPBELL FOR THEIR EXTRAORDINARY WORK SUPPORTING
OLDER ADULTS AND PEOPLE LIVING WITH DISABILITIES.
ART WITH ELDERS EMBODIES THE SPIRIT OF DISABILITY PRIDE BY
CREATING SPACES WHERE CREATIVITY, CONNECTION AND A
SELF-EXPRESSION ALLOW EVERY PARTICIPANT TO BE SEEN, HEARD
AND VALUED. I ALSO WANT TO HIGHLIGHT MARK'S
DEEP ROOTS IN OUR COMMUNITY. FOR MORE THAN 35 YEARS MARK
AND HIS WIFE DEE, A NURSE AT UCSF NURSES HAVE MADE THEIR
HOME IN THE OUTER SUNSET RAISING THEIR TWO CHILDREN
AND CONTRIBUTING TO THE DISTRICT'S STRONG SENSE OF
COMMUNITY. THE SUNSETS PEACEFUL FOG
SHROUDED CHARACTER HAS LONG SUPPORTED MARK'S ARTISTIC
PRACTICE. HIS DEDICATION TO LAGUNA HONDA
HOSPITAL AND HIS LEADERSHIP OF ARTS WITH OTHERS.
AND FINALLY I WANT TO ENCOURAGE EVERYONE TO JOIN WITH ART WITH
ELDERS AS THEY CELEBRATE THEIR 33RD ANNUAL EXHIBIT AT THE
VETERANS BUILDING FROM AUGUST 16TH THROUGH SEPTEMBER 9TH.
IT'S A WONDERFUL OPPORTUNITY TO EXPERIENCE THE POWER OF
CREATIVITY AND THE VOICES OF ELDER ARTISTS FROM ACROSS OUR
CITY. THANK YOU.
AND WITH THAT I'D LIKE TO TURN IT OVER TO MARK CAMPBELL,
DISTRICT FOUR RESIDENT ARTIST AND EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF ART
WITH ELDERS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. TRUE STORY.
COUPLE OF MONTHS AGO I WAS IN MY STUDIO IN THE AVENUES
PAINTING AND THE DOORBELL RANG AND THE DOGS WENT CRAZY AND MY
SON THE 23 YEAR OLD WENT TO THE DOOR AND HAD A CONVERSATION
WITH SOMEONE. >> AND I WAS YOU KNOW, IT TOOK
A LONG TIME. I'M LIKE WHAT THE HECK WAS THAT
ABOUT? HE FINALLY COMES BACK IN AND HE
SAYS OH I MET A REPRESENTED OF MR. WONG, THE SUPERVISOR WHO'S
RUNNING FOR ELECTION. >> AND I SAID OH WOW.
SO DID THEY REPRESENTED WELL AND HE SAID ACTUALLY WAS IT WAS
ALAN HIMSELF AND AND YOU KNOW I SAID DID YOU DID YOU HAPPEN TO
CHANGE OF ALL VOTE OR LEARN ANYTHING ABOUT IT AND HE SAID
HE WAS VERY IMPRESSED AND WE ARE SO THRILLED THAT THE
RESULTS CAME OUT THE WAY HE DID.
>> BUT WHAT I WANTED TO TALK ABOUT IS THE THE GIFT OF
CREATIVITY AND THE FACT THAT CREATIVITY OPENS DOORS
AND BUILDS BRIDGES AND FOR THOSE WHO ARE MOST
DISENFRANCHIZED I FEEL A SPECIAL FORCE AND WE WE'VE DONE
THE MATH. WE'VE BEEN AROUND FOR ABOUT 30
YEARS AND WE ACTUALLY HAVE IN THAT TIME WORKED WITH OVER
12,000 SENIORS IN THE BAY AREA. WE HAVE ABOUT 50 CLASSES
RUNNING PER WEEK. WE HAVE MANY EXHIBITIONS THAT
HAPPEN THROUGHOUT THE YEAR AND WE HAVE THESE GREAT
OPENINGS AT LAGUNA HONDA HOSPITAL IN THE SUMMERTIME
AND WE INVITE EVERYONE TO VISIT OUR WEBSITE ART WITH ELDERS
YOUR G TO LEARN MORE ABOUT OUR PROGRAMING.
BUT REALLY THRILLED FOR THIS HONOR AND THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
RECOGNIZING ME AND MY WORK AND WE HAVE DARCY O'BRIAN HERE
AND IRIS WHO AND CRYSTAL BOOTH WHO IS OUR PROGRAM MANAGER IS
UNABLE TO MAKE IT TODAY BUT IT TAKES AN ARMY AND THE REAL
HEROES ARE OUR STUDENTS THOSE WITH DISABILITIES THOSE ELDERS
WHO PUT THEMSELVES OUT THERE AND LEARN THROUGH CREATIVITY
HOW TO MANAGE THE GREAT STRESSES THAT COME WITH GETTING
OLDER. WE REALLY FIND VALUE IN OUR
PROGRAM AND WE UNDERSTAND THAT IT WORKS.
IT TRULY DOES TRANSFORM LIVES. SO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THIS
HONOR AND OH REALLY APPRECIATE THAT.
>> THANK YOU. YES, PLEASE I'M GOING TO GET
EVERYBODY IN DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR DORSI THANK YOU
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN COLLEAGUES IN RECOGNITION OF PROBATION
SERVICES WEEK IT IS MY PRIVILEGE TO HONOR THE
DEDICATED PROFESSIONALS OF SAN FRANCISCO'S PROBATION
DEPARTMENTS. AND I'D FIRST LIKE TO WELCOME
CHIEF ADULT PROBATION OFFICER KRYSTAL TULLOCH TO THE LECTERN.
CHIEF TULLOCH IS HERE TO ACCEPT THIS COMMENDATION ON BEHALF OF
THE ADULT PROBATION DEPARTMENT PROBATION PROFESSIONALS CHIEF
TAUGHT PROBATION PROFESSIONALS PLAY A UNIQUE AND ESSENTIAL
ROLE IN OUR JUSTICE SYSTEM EVERY DAY THEY WORK TO
STRENGTHEN PUBLIC SAFETY, SUPPORT VICTIMS, PROMOTE
ACCOUNTABILITY AND HELP JUSTICE INVOLVED INDIVIDUALS
SUCCESSFULLY RETURN TO THEIR COMMUNITIES THROUGH EVIDENCE
BASED AND COURT ORDERED PROGRAMING.
PROBATION OFFICERS HOLD INDIVIDUALS ACCOUNTABLE WHILE
CONNECTING THEM WITH THE SERVICES AND SUPPORT THEY NEED
TO BUILD HEALTHIER AND MORE PRODUCTIVE LIVES.
THEY ALSO SERVE AS IMPORTANT CONNECTORS BETWEEN THE COURT
LAW ENFORCEMENT, CITY DEPARTMENTS, BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
PROVIDERS, SCHOOLS, COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS AND SERVICE
PROVIDERS. I'D ALSO LIKE TO RECOGNIZE THE
JUVENILE PROBATION DEPARTMENT FOR ITS WORK SUPPORTING YOUNG
PEOPLE AND THEIR FAMILIES. JUVENILE PROBATION
PROFESSIONALS CONNECT YOUTH WITH EDUCATION SKILLS TRAINING,
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH SERVICES AND OTHER KINDS OF COMMUNITY
BASED SUPPORT. PROBATION OFFICERS BALANCE
OPPORTUNITIES FOR TREATMENT AND REHABILITATION WITH THE
RESPONSIBILITY TO PROTECT THE LARGER COMMUNITY TO SUPERVISE
INDIVIDUAL EYES AND TO ENSURE COMPLIANCE WITH COURT ORDERED
CONDITIONS. HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO,
PROBATION PROVIDES AN EFFECTIVE ALTERNATIVE TO INCARCERATION
WHEN APPROPRIATE. IT ALLOWS INDIVIDUALS TO REMAIN
IN THEIR COMMUNITIES WHILE RECEIVING STRUCTURED
SUPERVISION AND SUPPORT RELATED TO SUBSTANCE USE MENTAL HEALTH
EDUCATION, EMPLOYMENT, HOUSING AND OTHER NEEDS.
BY COMBINING ACCOUNTABILITY AND SUPERVISION WITH ACCESS TO
TREATMENT EDUCATION, WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AND REHABILITATIVE
SERVICES, PROBATION HELPS ADDRESS THE ROOT CAUSES OF
CRIME, REDUCE RECIDIVISM AND IMPROVE COMMUNITY
WELL-BEING. TODAY WE RECOGNIZE THE
PROFESSIONALISM, COMPASSION, COMPASSION AND DEDICATION OF
ALL OF SAN FRANCISCO'S PROBATION PROFESSIONALS.
THEIR WORK CHANGES LIVES SUPPORTS FAMILIES AND HELPS
MAKE OUR COMMUNITY SAFER. ON BEHALF OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS, IT IS MY HONOR TO COMMEND ALL THE
PROFESSIONALS OF THE ADULT PROBATION AND JUVENILE
PROBATION DEPARTMENTS ON THE OCCASION OF PROBATION SERVICES
WEEK AND IN PARTICULAR CHIEF TULLOCH, CONGRATULATIONS
AND THANKS TO YOU AND YOUR ENTIRE DEPARTMENT FOR YOUR
SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR YOUR
FIERCELY LEADERSHIP. IT'S AN HONOR TO WORK IN YOUR
LIGHT. AND THANK YOU TO THE OTHER
BOARD MEMBERS WHO HAVE DEFINITELY BEEN SUPPORTIVE OF
AND OR ENGAGED WITH PROBATION OVER THE YEARS.
>> PROBATION CHIEFS ACROSS CALIFORNIA DURING THIS WEEK AS
PRESENTING IN FRONT OF THEIR BOARDS IS TAKING THIS
OPPORTUNITY TO RECOGNIZE THAT CHIEF MERLYN WASHINGTON CHIEF
OF MARIN COUNTY PROBATION DIED SUDDENLY LAST FRIDAY AT THE END
OF OUR ASSOCIATION MEETING. AND SO WE'RE ALL RECOGNIZING
HIM THIS THIS WEEK. >> I WOULD LIKE TO CALL CHIEF
KATIE MILLER UP AS PROBATION AS YOU RECOGNIZE.
THANK YOU. YOU HEAR US AND YOU SEE US JUST
BASED ON YOUR WORDS. SUPERVISOR THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
AND I LIKE SUPER CHIEF MILLER TO SPEAK.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR AS I THINK YOU ALL HEARD US SAY MANY TIMES, WE'RE
THE ONLY COUNTY IN THE STATE WITH TWO CHIEFS SO YOU GET LIKE
TWICE THE PACK OF PUNCH FROM US AND JUST REALLY WANT TO THANK
YOU THANKS TO YOU FOR YOUR RECOGNITION AND REALLY REALLY
ACKNOWLEDGING TODAY THE HARD WORK AND DEDICATION OF THE
FOLKS WHO WORK IN BOTH OF OUR DEPARTMENTS WHO CARE ABOUT OUR
CLIENTS ON OUR END, WHO CARE ABOUT YOUNG PEOPLE AND THEIR
FAMILIES AND THE COMMUNITY AS A WHOLE.
>> THIS IS A REALLY IMPORTANT TIME FOR US EVERY YEAR TO
REFLECT ON WHAT IS SIGNIFICANT AND URGENT AND ESSENTIAL ABOUT
OUR WORK AND SO WE'RE GLAD TO CELEBRATE THAT WITH YOU.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
TOGETHER WE'RE GOING TO THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR
ACKNOWLEDGING OUR PROBATION DEPARTMENTS THIS WEEK.
YOU ALREADY HAD A AS AN OFFICER A SPECIAL ACCOMMODATION IN THE
WORKS WHEN YOU TOOK THAT ON SO LET'S DO YOUR SECOND ONE.
>> THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR INDULGING ME FOR A LITTLE
MANDATORY DOUBLE DIPPING BUT IT IS REALLY MY HONOR TO RECOGNIZE
A DISTRICT SIX INSTITUTION AND THE ABERDEEN FIGHT CLUB
AND TWO OF ITS CHAMPION FIGHTERS SAN FRANCISCANS WHOSE
ACHIEVEMENTS IN THE RING AND IN OUR COMMUNITY ARE AN
INESTIMABLE CREDIT TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
I WANT TO START WITH JASON JP PETERSON, OWNER AND HEAD COACH
OF ABERDEEN. >> JP WOULD YOU COME ON UP TO
THE LECTERN? >> JP IS A FORMER PROFESSIONAL
BOXER AND SAN FRANCISCO NATIVE WHO BUILT ABERDEEN AS AN OLD
SCHOOL STRICTLY BOXING GYM IN THE HEART OF OUR CITY RIGHT
ON MARKET STREET. IT'S A PLACE FOCUSED ON
TEACHING REAL FUNDAMENTALS AND TECHNIQUE TO YOUTH
AND ADULTS ALIKE THE KIND OF COACHING THAT CAN GET LOST
IN BIGGER, MORE CROWDED SETTINGS.
IT'S A GYM BY DESIGN WITH CLASSES CAPPED AT JUST TEN
PEOPLE. BUILT AROUND A FIGHTER
AND FIGHT TEAM MENTALITY WHERE EVERY MEMBER TRAINS
AND COMPETES AS IF THEY'RE ONE OF THE CLUB'S CHAMPIONS.
AND THE GYM'S MISSION GOES BEYOND ITS WALLS.
JP IS ALSO FOUNDED A NONPROFIT CONNECTED TO ABERDEEN, THE
ABERDEEN FIGHT CLUB BOXING PROGRAM WHICH USES EVERY DOLLAR
DONATED TO FUND EQUIPMENT AND COMPETITION EXPENSES FOR
THE YOUTH BOXING PROGRAM GIVING SAN FRANCISCO KIDS THE CHANCE
TO COMPETE AT LEVELS THEY MIGHT NOT OTHERWISE HAVE ACCESS TO.
IT'S WITH THIS KIND OF SPIRIT THAT HE BUILT A PLACE THAT
ISN'T JUST A CLUB BUT A COMMUNITY.
IT'S OUT OF THAT GYM AND UNDER JP'S COACHING THAT TODAY'S
OTHER TWO HONOREES HAVE RISEN TO BECOME CHAMPIONS.
CECELIA DOMINIC KAISER CECILIA IS A TWO TIME IS A TWO TIME
NORTHERN CALIFORNIA GOLDEN GLOVES CHAMPION A TWO TIME
SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA STATE CHAMPIONSHIP WINNER AND A STATE
CALIFORNIA STATE GOLDEN GLOVES CHAMPION.
THE GOLDEN GLOVES IS ONE OF THE OLDEST AND MOST STORIED AMATEUR
BOXING COMPETITION IN THE COUNTRY AND WINNING IT AT THE
STATE LEVEL LET ALONE DOING IT MULTIPLE TIMES IN BOTH NORTHERN
AND SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA PUTS DOMINIQUE AMONG THE MOST
ACCOMPLISHED AMATEUR BOXERS THAT OUR STATE HAS EVER
PRODUCED. BUT HER TALENTS DON'T STOP AT
BOXING. SHE'S ALSO AN EMERGENCY ROOM
REGISTERED NURSE AT UCSF AND THE OWNER OF LASER CLEAR
SKIN MED SPA, A LOCAL SMALL BUSINESS.
DOMINIQUE REPRESENTS THE VERY BEST OF WHAT IT MEANS TO BE A
CHAMPION BOTH IN AND OUT OF THE RING AND ALSO SUGAR SARA
MAHMOOD OF. >> DID I PRONOUNCE IT SORRY?
>> DID I PRONOUNCE THAT RIGHT? YEAH.
OKAY. >> I'M SORRY IS A NINE TIME
NATIONAL CHAMPION A DISTINCTION THAT REFLECTS YEARS OF GOING
TOE TO TOE AGAINST THE VERY BEST AMATEUR BOXERS IN THE
NATION AND COMING OUT ON TOP AGAIN AND AGAIN.
THAT RECORD MADE HIM ONE OF THE TOP PROSPECTS IN THE SPORT
AND IT'S WHAT PUT HIM ON THE RADAR TO BECOME THE FIRST SAN
FRANCISCO NATIVE PROFESSIONAL BOXER SIGNED TO ZUFFA BOXING A
NEW PROMOTION THAT LAUNCHED IN JANUARY AND THEN QUICKLY
LANDED MAJOR MEDIA RIGHTS DEALS WITH PARAMOUNT PLUS AND CBS
SARA JUST WON HIS ZUFFA DEBUT ON PARAMOUNT AGAINST AS UNTIL
THEN UNDEFEATED FRENCH CHAMPION IN SAN FRANCISCO WILL BE
WATCHING CLOSELY ON HIS NEXT FIGHT WHICH WAS JUST ANNOUNCED.
HE IS PROOF THAT WORLD CLASS TALENT IS BORN AND MADE RIGHT
HERE IN OUR CITY. ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS I WANT TO THANK JP DOMINICK AND SARRAY FOR
REPRESENTING SAN FRANCISCO WITH EXCELLENCE AND FOR THE EXAMPLE
YOU SET FOR ALL THE ATHLETES IN OUR CITY.
>> THANKS SO MUCH. I WROTE THIS LAST NIGHT SO I
DON'T MESS IT UP SO FIRST OFF I'D LIKE TO THANK SUPERVISOR
MATT DORSEY AND HIS OFFICE FOR THEIR SUPPORT AS WELL AS EVERY
BUDDY ON THE BOARD TODAY. THANK YOU GUYS VERY MUCH.
YOU HUMBLE ME WITH THIS ACKNOWLEDGMENT BEYOND WORDS BUT
I'M GOING TO STILL TRY MY BEST TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE HERE.
I'M BORN AND RAISED IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I GUESS YOU COULD SAY I ALWAYS DIDN'T MAKE THE RIGHT CHOICES
IN MY LIFE AND THAT LANDED ME WITH A LENGTHY PRISON TERM AT
ONE POINT IN TIME. DURING THAT TIME I DID A LOT OF
REFLECTING ON MY LIFE AND THE MISTAKES I MADE AND I WAS
DETERMINED NOT TO WASTE WHAT I HAD LEARNED THE HARD WAY
BECAUSE IF I DID IT WOULD HAVE BEEN A WASTE OF LIFE BEFORE I
WENT AWAY. BOXING BECAME MY PASSION AND I
HAD HAD I GOTTEN INTO IT AT A YOUNGER AGE THINGS MAY HAVE
BEEN DIFFERENT BUT I DO BELIEVE EVERYTHING HAPPENS FOR A REASON
TO HELP YOU GRASP THE STORY. IN SHORT, ONE MONTH BEFORE I
HAD TO TURN MYSELF IN FOR A TEN YEAR SENTENCE I FOUGHT AT THE
PLAYBOY MANSION AND ON ESPN 30 DAYS LATER I SAT ON A PRISON
YARD THINKING WHAT I COULD HAVE DONE DIFFERENTLY.
THE NEXT TEN YEARS I DAYDREAMED ABOUT BUILDING A GYM AND USING
BOXING AS A PLATFORM TO HELP THE YOUTH OF SAN FRANCISCO STAY
OUT OF TROUBLE AND ATHLETES IN THE SPORT ACHIEVE THEIR
MAXIMUM POTENTIAL. FAST FORWARD AND HERE I AM
OWNER OF A STRICTLY OLD SCHOOL BOXING GYM THE ONLY ONE OF ITS
KIND IN THE HEART OF SAN FRANCISCO BEING ACKNOWLEDGED BY
THE CITY WHICH I AM VERY GRATEFUL.
FLANKED BY MY TWO TIME NORCAL AND STATE CHAMPION AND THE
FIRST PRO BOXER OUT OF SAN FRANCISCO SIGNED BY ZUFFA THE
NEWEST AND FASTEST GROWING BOXING PROMOTION VIEWED AROUND
THE WORLD AND THIS IS IN UNDER THREE YEARS WE ARE DOING IT FOR
REAL AND WE APPRECIATE YOU SAN FRANCISCO FOR ACKNOWLEDGING US.
>> AND LAST BUT NOT LEAST BEFORE I GET TOO LONG AND GET
YELLED AT BY TONY, I JUST WANT TO THANK TONY DELORENZO FOR
ALWAYS BEING THERE AND SUPPORTING US THE BEST HE
CAN AS WELL. >> THANK YOU TONY.
YOU SORRY
? >> DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR
WALTON THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT OF MANAGEMENT
COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE THE PRIVILEGE OF RECOGNIZING
SOMEONE WHOSE STORY IS A POWERFUL TESTAMENT TO
TRANSFORMATION REDEMPTION AND SERVICE TO OUR COMMUNITY.
DAMIAN POSEY DAMIEN'S JOURNEY IS ONE OF RESILIENCE
AND PURPOSE. AFTER RETURNING HOME FROM
PRISON, HE MADE A LIFE CHANGING DECISION TO TRANSFORM HIS
EXPERIENCES INTO A MISSION OF GIVING BACK RATHER THAN
ALLOWING HIS PAST TO DEFINE HIM.
DAMIEN CHOSE TO DEDICATE HIS LIFE TO HELPING OTHERS CREATE
BRIGHTER FUTURES. TODAY HE IS A RESPECTED
COMMUNITY LEADER AND MENTOR WHOSE WORK HAS TOUCHED THE
LIVES OF YOUTH, SENIORS AND FAMILIES THROUGHOUT SAN
FRANCISCO. >> DRIVEN BY THE BELIEF THAT
EVERYONE DESERVES A SECOND CHANCE AND THE OPPORTUNITY TO
SUCCEED, DAMIEN HAS EARNED THE TRUST OF OUR COMMUNITY BY
LEADING WITH COMPASSION, AUTHENTICITY AND ACCOUNTABILITY
. HIS ABILITY TO CONNECT WITH
YOUNG PEOPLE HAS INSPIRED MANY TO PURSUE EDUCATION, EMPLOYMENT
AND PERSONAL GROWTH WHILE BECOMING POSITIVE ROLE MODELS
IN THEIR OWN NEIGHBORHOODS. >> ONE OF DAMIEN'S MOST
IMPACTFUL ACCOMPLISHED MOMENTS IS THE CREATION AND GROWTH OF
THE US FOR US ORGANIZATION. MORE THAN JUST A JOBS PROGRAM
IT EQUIPS YOUNG PEOPLE WITH LEADERSHIP PROFESSIONALISM,
TEAMWORK, COMMUNICATION AND LIFE SKILLS THAT PREPARE
THEM FOR LONG TERM SUCCESS. UNDER DAMIEN'S LEADERSHIP AS
FOR US HAS SUPPORTED COMMUNITY EVENTS, NEIGHBORHOOD CLEANUPS,
FOOD AND RESOURCE DISTRIBUTIONS ,MENTORSHIP INITIATIVES
AND MANY MEANINGFUL ASSISTANCE FOR SENIOR CITIZENS BY BRINGING
GENERATIONS TOGETHER. DAMIEN HAS HELPED FOSTER A
CULTURE OF RESPECT WHERE YOUNG PEOPLE LEARN THE IMPORTANCE OF
SERVING THEIR ELDERS AND SENIORS RECEIVE THE CARE
COMPANIONSHIP AND SUPPORT THEY DESERVE.
KNOWN TO SO MANY AS UNCLE DAMIEN, HE PUTS HIS HEART INTO
EVERY YOUNG PERSON HE MENTORS, ENCOURAGING THEM TO SEE BEYOND
THEIR CIRCUMSTANCES AND RECOGNIZE THEIR OWN
POTENTIAL. HIS LEADERSHIP DEMONSTRATES
THAT LASTING CHANGE IS BUILT THROUGH CONSISTENT GUIDANCE
MEANINGFUL OPPORTUNITIES AND A COMMITMENT TO SERVING OTHERS.
DAMIEN ALSO PLAYS A MAJOR ROLE IN PREVENTING VIOLENCE IN OUR
COMMUNITIES. HE WORKS WITH YOUNG PEOPLE TO
PREVENT RETALIATIONS AND ESCALATE FURTHER INCIDENTS
WHEN ISSUES OCCUR IN NEIGHBORHOODS.
DAMIEN'S JOURNEY FROM REDEMPTION TO LEADERSHIP HAS
BECOME A SOURCE OF HOPE AND INSPIRATION FOR COUNTLESS
INDIVIDUALS. HIS UNWAVERING DEDICATION
CONTINUES TO EMPOWER YOUNG PEOPLE, UPLIFT SENIORS,
STRENGTHEN FAMILIES AND BUILD A MORE CONNECTED
AND COMPASSIONATE COMMUNITY. THANK YOU DAMIEN, FOR YOUR
OUTSTANDING LEADERSHIP AND LASTING CONTRIBUTIONS TO
OUR COMMUNITY AND BEYOND. >> THANK YOU.
I'M NOTHING WITHOUT MY VILLAGE SO I NEED MY VILLAGE TO GO.
COME ON UP HERE, MAN. IF YOU CAME UP FOR UNCLE DAMIEN
IN I NEED YOU TO COME OVER HERE REAL QUICK.
I'M GOING TO DO MY BEST NOT TO BE LONG WINDED BECAUSE I KNOW I
COULD SPEAK. I'LL COME ON UP HERE.
FIRST OF ALL, GIVE AN HONEST TO GOD YOU KNOW, WITHOUT WHOM I
WOULDN'T BE HERE AT ALL AND ESPECIALLY GRATEFUL TO MY
MOTHER. MS..
>> RENE POSEY OVER HERE WHO GAVE BIRTH TO ME 47 YEARS AGO.
WELL, AND STAND UP, MOM. STAND UP.
DON'T MAKE SOME NOISE FOR THIS BEAUTIFUL QUEEN FOR ME, PLEASE.
Y'ALL CLAP IT UP FOR THIS BEAUTIFUL QUEEN FOR ME, PLEASE.
>> THANK YOU. I WANT TO THANK EVERYBODY THAT
CAME OUT HERE TODAY AND KNOW THAT LIKE I ALWAYS SAY, THEY
MADE A CALL MY NAME BUT THIS RECOGNITION AND WHATEVER IT IS
BELONGS TO ALL OF US. EVERYBODY IN THIS ROOM THAT'S
PUTTING UP THIS FIGHT IN THE COMMUNITY, I STAND ON THE
SHOULDERS OF MY ELDERS. I STAND ALONGSIDE THE MANY,
MANY SOLDIERS WHO COULD BE STAND IN HIS PLACE GETTING
RECOGNIZED. YOU KNOW WHOM I WOULD NOT BE
HERE WITHOUT BECAUSE IT DEFINITELY TAKES ALL OF US YOU
KNOW WHAT I'M SAYING TO KEEP UP THIS FIGHT IN THE COMMUNITY,
YOU KNOW, ALL THE WAY FROM PROJECT LEVEL 100% COLLEGE PREP
TAILOR MADE UNITED PLAYERS WAS RUDY'S NOT HERE BUT I GOT TO
PAY HOMAGE TO RUDY BECAUSE Y'ALL KNOW I CAME TO THAT U.P.
LINEAGE, YOU KNOW SHINE RICHARD'S CREEK AS VIP ALL THE
THE RTP ALL THE Y C D, YOU KNOW WHAT I MEAN?
AND I CAN GO ON AND ON THE AMAZING PEOPLE IN THIS ROOM MY
SPIRITUAL ADVISOR WHO WAS THERE FOR ME PASSED IT MARQUESE WENT
BACK HE'LL MAKE SOME NOTES TO PASTOR KEYS FOR ME PLEASE DON'T
PLEASE DO A LOT OF WORK IN THE COMMUNITY CHIK CHICO EVERYBODY
UP HERE AND TO MY BROTHER GOOD BROTHER MY ASSISTANT DANA ALL
OF THE AMAZING YOUNG PEOPLE YOU KNOW THAT WHO ARE HERE AND TO
ALL OF YOU SUPERVISORS WHO I KNOW THIS IS NOT AN EASY JOB
THAT YOU HAVE. YOU KNOW THIS IS NOT AN EASY
JOB THAT YOU HAVE REPRESENTING EACH DISTRICT OF THIS BEAUTIFUL
CITY THAT WE HAVE. YOU KNOW, PEOPLE TALK ABOUT ME
A LOT AND THAT'S BECAUSE I'M YOU KNOW, I DO HAVE A BIG HEART
AND I TELL YOU HOW BIG MY HEART IS IS SEVEN BY SEVEN SQUARE
MILES. YOU KNOW WHAT I'M SAYING?
IN HIS BEAUTIFUL STOLEN LAND THAT WE LIVE ON, YOU KNOW,
WHICH I'VE DEDICATED THE SECOND PART OF MY LIFE BECAUSE WHEN I
WAS COMING UP I WASN'T THE BEST SON.
THAT'S WHY I ALWAYS ACKNOWLEDGE MY MOTHER, YOU KNOW, LIKE THE
BROTHER WHO JUST CAME BEFORE ME ALSO WAS UNFORTUNATELY
IN PRISON FOR 120 MONTHS. THIS TEN YEARS.
BUT DURING THAT TIME I RECEIVED A ELEVATION AND ENLIGHTENMENT
IN MY LIFE AND UNDERSTOOD THE IMPORTANCE OF REPRESENTING FOR
THOSE THAT COME AFTER YOU THE YOUNG PEOPLE NOT FORGETTING
ABOUT THE SENIORS IN OUR COMMUNITY BECAUSE MY MOTHER WAS
A BEAUTIFUL YOUNG MOTHER OF 60 YEARS OLD WHEN SHE HAD ME SO I
HAD AN AMAZING GRANDPARENTS WHO TAUGHT ME A LOT OF THINGS YOU
KNOW, AND JUST LOVING ALL OF THE PEOPLE THE HOUSELESS YOU
KNOW, I'VE HAD THE PLEASURE OF WORKING WITH MATT DORSEY
IN DISTRICT SIX DOWNTOWN. WE KNOW THE STRUGGLES THAT HIS
DISTRICT FACED THAT ALL OF OUR DISTRICTS FACE.
YOU KNOW, I'VE HAD THE PLEASURE WE'RE WORKING WITH A LOT OF YOU
GUYS, YOU KNOW, AND IF I HAVEN'T WORK WITH YOU, I'M OPEN
TO WORKING WITH YOU IN YOUR DISTRICT BECAUSE I AM PRIMARILY
TEN YOU KNOW, GREW UP BUT LIKE I SAID SEVEN BY SEVEN MAN I
LOVE EVERY INCH OF SAN FRANCISCO.
THESE YOUNG PEOPLE COME FROM EVERY DISTRICT IN OUR CITY, YOU
KNOW? AND AS I LEAVE I WANT TO
ENCOURAGE YOU TO NOT FORGET ABOUT THEM.
AND LIKE I SAID, I KNOW THIS JOB IS HARD BUT WE MUST HOLD
THE INDIVIDUALS ACCOUNTABLE THE TECH COMPANIES, THE PROPERTY
MANAGERS AND ALL THAT. I BECAUSE I'M IN A WHO'S IN THE
COMMUNITIES EVERY DAY WE STILL HAVE BRAND NEW APARTMENT
BUILDINGS THAT ARE BREAKING DOWN SENIORS THAT CAN'T GET TO
THEIR APARTMENTS BECAUSE THE ELEVATORS ARE DOWN.
YOU KNOW VIOLENCE IS GOING DOWN BUT WE STILL NEED HELP.
WE HAVE TO ENCOURAGE, ENLIGHTEN AND EMPOWER OUR YOUNG PEOPLE,
THE COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS THAT ARE OUT THERE ON THE FIELD
EVERY DAY GIVING BACK LIKE US FOR US.
SO I APPRECIATE YOU GUYS. I LOVE YOU GUYS.
YOU KNOW WHAT I'M SAYING? MY YOUNG PEOPLE I JUST WANT YOU
TO KNOW THIS COULD BE ANY ONE OF Y'ALL UP HERE.
YOU FEEL ME? >> THIS COULD BE ANY ONE OF
Y'ALL UP HERE THAT YOU KNOW AND THEY LEFT.
BUT I WANT TO SHOUT OUT GABE AND THEM THEY JUST LEFT
JUVENILE PROBATION BECAUSE THEY GIVEN ME AN OPPORTUNITY TO WORK
WITH THE YOUNG PEOPLE. I'M IN THE JUVENILE HALLS ALL
THE TIME IN COMMUNITIES ALL THE TIME, YOU KNOW, BUT ON PAPER I
WILL LOOK LIKE AN INDIVIDUAL THAT SHOULDN'T BE DOING THAT,
YOU KNOW. BUT MY KIDS HAVE FAITH IN ME
AND I PROMISE TO CONTINUE TO KEEP WORKING AND NOT LET YOUR
DOWN. I APPRECIATE YOU SO MUCH
AND SERMON ON YOUR WAY OUT MAN. I JUST HOPE AND PRAY THAT WE
GET ANOTHER STRONG LEADER LIKE YOU IN OUR COMMUNITY.
MAN THAT REALLY WORKS WITH THE PEOPLE, TALKS WITH THE PEOPLE,
COMES OUT AND GIVES BACK AND THEN CONGRATULATIONS ON
EVERYTHING THAT YOU'VE DONE. YOU KNOW I'M SAYING THE
PHARMACY I KNOW THEY LIKE TO TALK DOWN TO YOU BUT US IN THE
STREET IN A COMMUNITY WE KNOW HOW HARD YOU WORK AND WE SEE
YOU ALL THE TIME AND WE APPRECIATE YOU AND WE THANK
YOU, MAN AND I THANK EVERYBODY THAT CAME OUT HERE BIG RICH, MY
BROTHER BIG RICH YOU MY BROTHER BIG RICH SUMMER FROM THE HYPE
CENTER PERCY PRESS INTERVIEW EVERYBODY ALL THESE GUYS ARE AC
DC TOO BECAUSE THEY KNOW I'M HALF CATHY VALENCIA.
I LOVE EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU.
I APPRECIATE YOUR TAILOR MADE BACK THERE MAN MY GUYS YOU'VE
GOT SAY SAYING I'VE BEEN HOME 15 YEARS YOU'VE BEEN I'M SAYING
GIVE IT BACK SO THEY LET YOU KNOW THEY GOT KIDS AND WAS
WORKING WITH THOSE 15 AND NOW 30 DOING AMAZING THINGS IN THE
COMMUNITY. I APPRECIATE I LOVE ALL YOUR
MAN THANK YOU AND YOU KNOW I COULD TALK FOR TOMORROW FOR FOR
THREE WE'RE GOING TO DO A BIG ONE ON THEIR SECOND DISTRICT
ONE SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT MAN DOMAIN COLLEAGUES
IT IS MY HONOR. YOU KNOW OUR FORMER KALI
SUPERVISOR DEAN PRESTON HAS DONE THIS BUT I FEEL LIKE IT IS
MY HONOR AND MY PRIVILEGE TO DO THIS EVEN THOUGH WITH SADNESS
THAT PART OF IT WAS A BITTERSWEET TO RECOGNIZE PAUL
OSAKI ON THE OCCASION OF HIS RETIREMENT TO THANK HIM FOR HIS
TIRELESS SERVICE AND LEADERSHIP TO THE JAPANESE CULTURAL
AND COMMUNITY CENTER OF NORTHERN CALIFORNIA LOVELY
LOVINGLY KNOWN AS JAYCEE'S AND SEE ALSO FOR THE COMMUNITY
TO BE KNOW THE CENTER WHILE PAUL WILL BE RECOGNIZED AT A
FORMAL COMMUNITY CELEBRATION THAT WILL BE DURING OUR AUGUST
RECESS. >> IT IS TRULY A PRIVILEGE FOR
ME TO BE ABLE TO RECOGNIZE HIM TODAY IN OUR BOARD CHAMBER.
>> WE HAVE DONE SO BEFORE FOR HIS ACCOMPLISHMENT BUT TODAY WE
GET TO CELEBRATE HIM FOR ALL THAT HE HAS ACCOMPLISHED BEYOND
THE 38 YEARS OF HIS SERVICE SERVING THE CENTER.
IT IS TRULY A LABOR OF LOVE WHAT HE HAS DONE NOT JUST FOR
THE CENTER BUT FOR THE ENTIRE COMMUNITY NOT JUST THE
JAPANESE-AMERICAN COMMUNITY BUT TRULY THE AAPI COMMUNITY.
WE'RE REALLY FOR THE GREATER COMMUNITY THROUGHOUT THE CITY.
BUT HIS MENTORING AND INSPIRING THE GENERATION TO GIVE BACK TO
OUR COMMUNITY SO THAT WE COULD KNOW LOVE AND OUR COMMUNITY
AND TO SERVE OUR COMMUNITY IT IS BECAUSE OF PAUL HAS ALWAYS
BEEN LEADING BY EXAMPLE. PAUL'S LIFELONG CONTRIBUTION
REFLECTS THE VALUES OF DEDICATION THAT IS A TRADEMARK
OF THE ESSAY AND NISEI GENERATION IS WHOSE SACRIFICES,
RESILIENCE AND COMMITMENT TO BUILD COMMUNITY CREATE
OPPORTUNITIES FOR CURRENT AND FUTURE GENERATIONS.
>> PAUL STEADY AND VISIONARY LEADERSHIP HAS HELPED EXPAND
THE IMPACT OF NOT ONLY NANCY THE CENTER BUT ALSO STRENGTHENS
THE CULTURAL, SOCIAL AND COMMUNITY FABRIC OF
JAPANTOWN. PAUL'S WORK HAS A LOCAL,
REGIONAL AND GLOBAL IMPACT BY UPLIFTING THE ESSENTIAL WORK OF
PRESERVING SAN FRANCISCO'S JAPANTOWN ONE OF ONLY THREE
REMAINING JAPAN TOWNS IN OUR COUNTRY, HE HAS BEEN DEEPLY
COMMITTED TO HONORING THE PAST WHILE INVESTING IN THE FUTURE,
ESTABLISHING THE POCHA AS TAKAHASHI E SAY HERITAGE CENTER
ONE OF HIS LASTING GIFTS TO THE COMMUNITY WHICH WILL HELP
PRESERVE THE STORIES, VALUES AND CONTRIBUTIONS OF THE EAST,
SAY PIONEERS FOR FUTURE GENERATIONS.
THANK YOU PAUL, FOR YOUR UNWAVERING COMMITMENT TO
PRESERVING JAPANESE AMERICAN HERITAGE, HERITAGE, CULTURE
AND TRADITIONS ESPECIALLY DURING A TIME WHERE IMMIGRANT
STORIES AND EXPERIENCES ARE BEING ATTACKED AND WIPE AWAY.
SO AT THIS BORDER WE WILL HAVE A RESOLUTION HONORING PAUL
AND THAT WE TO CELEBRATE AUGUST 29TH AS PART OZAKI DAY.
THANK YOU. WE HAVE OTHER SUPERVISORS WHO
WANT TO SAY NICE THINGS ABOUT PAULA SAKI.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD THANK YOU COLLEAGUES.
I WANT TO ADD MY APPRECIATION FOR PAULA SAKI AS WELL
AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR BRINGING FORWARD THIS
COMMENDATION AND AND THE RESOLUTION LATER TODAY THE
JAPANESE CULTURAL COMMUNITY CENTER OF NORTHERN CALIFORNIA
IS A BEDROCK SPACE IN THE JAPANTOWN COMMUNITY AND IN THE
REGION'S JAPANESE DIASPORA UNDER PAUL'S LEADERSHIP THE
CENTER TRANSFORM FROM AN IDEA TO A KEY PART OF THE
UNBREAKABLE STRONG CIVIC AND COMMUNITY FABRIC THAT MAKES
JAPANTOWN SO SPECIAL. >> THE CENTER FOSTERS AND HELPS
GROW TRADITIONS LIKE THE ICHIBAN FLOWER ARRANGEMENT
KENDO MARTIAL ARTS AND THE ANNUAL JAPANESE CEMETERY
CLEANUP TRADITIONS THAT CONNECT US TO THE PAST BUT ALSO BUILD
RELATIONSHIPS AND KINSHIP IN THE PRESENT.
IT SPEAKS TO PAUL'S SELFLESS SPIRIT AND BELIEF IN THE
JAPANTOWN COMMUNITY THAT WHAT WAS INITIALLY GOING TO BE AS I
UNDERSTAND IT FROM COMMUNITY MEMBER IS JUST A YEARLONG GIG
TRANSLATED ACTUALLY INTO 38 YEARS OF SERVICE AT THE HOME OF
THE CENTER. >> PERSONALLY I'VE BEEN
INSPIRED PAUL, BY SEEING YOU BY WATCHING YOU WITH YOUR
PASSIONATE ADVOCACY FOR THE COMMUNITY.
>> RON KEEPING HOTELS OPEN DURING COVID BUT ALSO MAKING
SURE THAT JAYDEN'S VOICE IS HEARD DURING THE REDEVELOPMENT
PLANS FOR THE FILLMORE SAFEWAY AS WELL.
>> HE'S ALSO BEEN AN INSPIRATION AND AN INCREDIBLE,
INCREDIBLE NEW GENERATIONAL LEADERS WHO I'M SO FORTUNATE TO
GET TO WORK WITH TODAY. THE SUPERVISOR EVERY DAY IS
POLLO SAKI DAY IN JAPANTOWN BUT I'M GLAD THAT WE AS A CITY WILL
GET A POLLO SAKI DAY ON AUGUST 29TH.
POLLY WISH YOU A RESTFUL AND JOYOUS RETIREMENT.
>> THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU.
I'M NOT GOING TO BELABOR SOME OF THE POINTS THAT MY COLLEAGUE
HAVE MADE BUT THANK YOU PAUL FOR EVERYTHING THAT YOU HAVE
DONE FOR OUR CITY. BUT MORE THAN ANYTHING THANK
YOU FOR THE DECADES OF WORK UPHOLDING JAPANESE CULTURE
AND EVERYTHING THAT YOU HAVE GIVEN US IN TERMS OF YOUR WORK
WITH YOUNG PEOPLE PAYING IT FORWARD FOR THE NEXT GENERATION
. YOU HAVE LOTS OF FANS HERE.
YOU HAVE LOTS OF HANDS ON THIS SIDE TOO.
AND GOOD LUCK ON YOUR RETIREMENT.
I KNOW YOU'LL STILL BE DOING A LOT BEHIND THE SCENES BUT AGAIN
FROM THE BOTTOM OF MY HEART THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
HONORABLE SUPERVISORS. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR
THIS HONOR YESTERDAY AT THIS TIME I WAS ACTUALLY AT 850
BRYANT IN ROOM 304 WHICH IS THE JURY ROOM AND I WAS THERE FOR
LIKE 4.5 HOURS TRYING TO THINK OF HOW AM I GOING TO GET OUT OF
THIS? NOT THAT I DON'T THINK SERVING
ON JURIES IS I'VE SERVED ON SEVERAL JURIES BUT I'M TRYING
TO FIGURE OUT HOW AM I GOING TO GET OUT OF THIS AND AT THE END
A JUDGE CAME UP AND HE SAID LET ME LISTEN TO YOUR HARDSHIP
CASES. AND SO ONE WENT UP AND SAID I
HAVE TO TAKE CARE OF MY NINE YEAR OLD MOTHER.
SHE SAID HE SAID SIT DOWN AND ANOTHER ONE WENT UP SAID
I'M THE SOLE PROPRIETOR OF A JOB AND JUST SIT BACK DOWN.
>> AND THE THIRD PERSON WENT UP AND SAID I'M ON A CRUISE
AND JUST SIT BACK DOWN. >> AND I WAS THINKING LIKE WELL
WHAT AM I GOING TO SAY? SO WHEN I WENT UP WHEN HE
CALLED MY NAME I SAID, YOU KNOW, THEY TOOK MY THREE
EXCUSES AND THEN HE SAID TELL ME WHAT YOUR HARDSHIP IS.
>> AND I SAID I GOT TO GO TO CITY HALL.
AND HE SAID THAT'S YOUR HARDSHIP.
THAT'S MY HARDSHIP. SO THAT'S WHY I'M HERE TODAY.
>> YOU KNOW, I WANT TO THANK ALL THE SUPERVISORS, YOU KNOW,
THAT I'VE WORKED WITH OVER THE YEARS SUPERVISOR CHAN MAHMOOD
MENG, OUR CHAN SUPERVISOR FIELD ALTHOUGH YOU KNOW, I REALLY
WISH YOU ARE IN SACRAMENTO WITH OUR STATE SENATOR.
I'M GLAD YOU'RE HERE. >> YOU KNOW, I HAD THE GREATEST
JOB IN THE WORLD WORKING FOR A NONPROFIT ORGANIZATION.
I FELL INTO A BY ACCIDENT WHEN I FLUNKED OUT OF HIGH SCHOOL
AND MY MOM SAID, YOU KNOW, IF YOU DON'T START DOING SOME THEY
KICK YOU OUT OF THE HOUSE. SO I ENDED UP VOLUNTEERING AT
THE ORGANIZATION CALLED THE JAPANESE COMMUNITY YOUTH
COUNCIL AND THAT KIND OF STARTED IT ALL FOR ME.
I LEARNED SELF-ESTEEM. I LEARNED WHAT SERVICE IS, I
LEARNED WHAT LEADERSHIP IS. I WENT TO WORK ON TO BUCHANAN
YMCA LATER THE KOREAN COMMUNITY CENTER, THEN THE ASIAN AMERICAN
RESIDENTIAL RECOVERY SERVICES BEFORE COMING TO THE CENTER
AND SPENDING THE LAST 38 YEARS HERE.
>> SO YOU KNOW WHEN FUNDING ISSUES COME UP FOR NONPROFITS
ESPECIALLY FOR YOUTH FOR CHILDREN I REALLY WANT TO
ENCOURAGE YOU AND I KNOW YOU HAVE TO FUND THEM.
YOU KNOW WHAT WE CAN DO FOR OUR CHILDREN AND WHAT WE DO FOR
NONPROFITS. YOU KNOW, WE WE BUILD
COMMUNITIES. WE CREATE CHANGE.
WE BUILD A BETTER SAN FRANCISCO AND UNLESS WE GET OUT
AND ENCOURAGE OUR YOUTH TO BE ABLE TO BE IN THESE POSITIONS
AND TO BE PART OF THESE COMMUNITIES AND NONPROFITS,
YOU'RE NOT GOING TO SEE THAT HAPPEN.
SO I REALLY WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR FUNDING.
YOU KNOW THOSE PROGRAMS. >> I WANT TO THANK MY STAFF
AND AND TURN TO OUR BACK HERE. I TOLD THEM I'M GOING TO PAY
THEM BUT ACTUALLY YOU'RE TAKING VACATION TIME TO BE HERE SO BUT
AGAIN, I HAD THE GREATEST JOB IN THE WORLD.
YOU KNOW THIS IS GOING TO BE THE FIRST TIME IN 38 YEARS THAT
I HAVEN'T GOT DINGED OFF OF THIS PODIUM.
>> SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH
. LEE HOUSEKEEPER YOU'RE BACK
THERE SOMEWHERE. >> COME ON UP.
YOU CAN BRING YOUR PEOPLE IF YOU WANT TO.
>> >> COLLEAGUES TODAY IT IS MY HONOR TO PRESENT A SPECIAL
COMMENDATION TO LEE HOUSE KEEPER FOR HIS 37 YEARS
ORGANIZING SAN FRANCISCO'S COMMEMORATION OF THE 1906
EARTHQUAKE AND FIRE BEFORE DAWN EVERY APRIL 18TH, SAN
FRANCISCANS GATHER AT LADIES FOUNTAIN AT MARKET GEARY
AND KEARNY STREETS AND AT 5:12 A.M. THE EXACT MINUTE THE
GROUND BEGAN TO SHAKE IN 1906 VINTAGE FIRE ENGINES SOUND A
SIREN INTO THE DARK CITY LEADERS SPEAK A WREATH IS LAID
AND THE CROWD SINGS SAN FRANCISCO THE ANTHEM FROM THE
1936 MGM FILM OF THE SAME NAME .
>> AFTERWARD, THE PROCESSION MOVES TWO MILES SOUTH TO
DISTRICT EIGHT 20TH AND CHURCH STREETS WHERE SAN FRANCISCANS
SPRAY GOLD PAINT ON A SMALL FIRE HYDRANT KNOWN AS THE
LITTLE GIANTS THE ONE HIDE THE ONE HYDRANT THAT KEPT FLOWING
WHEN THE REST FAILED IN 1906 SAVING THE MISSION DISTRICTS.
>> THE EARTHQUAKE COMMEMORATION DATES BACK TO 1919 WHEN THE
SOUTH OF MARKET BOYS, A FRATERNAL ORGANIZATION BEGAN
LAYING A WREATH EVERY APRIL 18TH AT THE FOUNTAIN WHERE
SURVIVORS GATHERED IN 1906 TO SEARCH FOR MISSING FAMILY
AND FRIENDS. THE TRADITION HAS CONTINUED FOR
DECADES AND FOR AND FOR THE LAST 37 OF THOSE YEARS LEE HAS
KEPT IT GOING. >> HE WAS BORN AND RAISED
IN CHICAGO AS A YOUNG MAN. >> HE MADE HIS WAY TO GREENWICH
VILLAGE WHERE HE LIVED ON GAY STREETS AND SPENT HIS EARLY
CAREER IN THE ORBIT OF THE ERA'S BIGGEST MUSICIANS
INCLUDING JANIS JOPLIN AND JUNE OF 1969 AS THE STONEWALL RIOTS
ERUPTED NEAR HIS APARTMENT, STRAIGHT ALLY LEE LENT HIS
GARBAGE CAN LIDS TO THE CROWD OUTSIDE SAID THEY'D HAVE
SOMETHING TO USE AS SHIELDS AGAINST THE POLICE.
>> LEE CAME TO SAN FRANCISCO IN 1980 AND BY 1982 HE'D BUILT
HIS OWN PUBLIC RELATIONS PRACTICE REPRESENTING CLIENTS
THAT HAVE INCLUDED MAYOR WILLIE BROWN AND CIVIL RIGHTS ATTORNEY
JOHN BURRIS. LEE HAS CALLED HIMSELF THE LAST
OF THE OLD TIME SAN FRANCISCO PRESS AGENTS FOR YEARS.
HE WAS ALSO THE PUBLIC VOICE BEHIND THE CHRISTMAS TOY DRIVE
AND LEFT YODELS A SANG FOR ADULTS, A SAN FRANCISCO
RESTAURANT AND SPORTS BAR NAMED FOR THE BASEBALL PLAYER
AND MANAGER WHICH IN SOME YEARS COLLECTED AS MANY AS 15,000
TOYS FOR CHILDREN THROUGH THE SAN FRANCISCO FIREFIGHTER'S TOY
PROGRAM CARRYING BOXES OF TOYS THROUGH A BAR PACK THREE DEEP
WITH CUSTOMERS. >> LEE ONCE SAID, IS SORT OF
LIKE A BALLET HE TOOK OVER THE EARTHQUAKE COMMEMORATION ALMOST
BY ACCIDENT AS IT WAS PASSED ON TO HIM THROUGH A GIRLFRIEND
WHOSE FATHER WAS THE LAST PRESIDENT OF THE SOUTH OF
MARKET BOYS IN ITS EARLY YEARS THE JOB MEANT TRACKING DOWN THE
LIVING SURVIVORS OF THE EARTHQUAKE AND DRAWING OUT
THEIR STORIES ONE BY ONE BEFORE THEY WERE LOST.
THE LAST KNOWN SURVIVOR DIED IN 2016 AT 109 YEARS OLD
AND THE CEREMONIES ORIGINAL REASON FOR BEING WENT WITH HIM.
CHRONICLE REPORTER CARL NULTY GAVE LEE A NEW REASON IT'S NOT
THE SURVIVORS SAN FRANCISCO IS THE SURVIVOR.
LEE KEPT IT KEPT THE TRADITION GOING ON THAT IDEA FOR ANOTHER
DECADE THIS YEAR WAS LEE'S LAST AS ORGANIZER OF THE EARTHQUAKE
COMMEMORATION HE'S PASSED THAT RESPONSIBILITY OFF TO THE
GUARDIANS OF THE CITY, A NONPROFIT DEDICATED TO
CELEBRATING AND PRESERVING SAN FRANCISCO'S POLICE FIRE.
SHERIFF AND EMS CONTRIBUTIONS AND HAVE SUPPORTED LEE
IN RUNNING AND RUNNING THE COMMEMORATION FOR MANY YEARS.
THANK YOU GUARDIANS LEE HAS PRESERVED AND PASSED ON A
TRADITION THAT'S BROUGHT TOGETHER GENERATIONS OF SAN
FRANCISCANS, SURVIVORS, FIRST RESPONDERS, CIVIC LEADERS
AND NEIGHBORS IN REMEMBRANCE CELEBRATING AND REAFFIRMING THE
CITY'S SPIRIT OF RESILIENCE. >> HIS LEGACY CARRIES FORWARD
NOT ONLY THROUGH THAT TRADITION AND HIS OTHER WORK BUT THROUGH
HIS FAMILY HIS SON JAMES SMITH AND HIS GRANDCHILDREN CONNOR
AND KATIE LEE. YOU ARE A GEM ON BEHALF OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. WE WANT TO THANK YOU FOR MAKING
SURE THE CITY KEEPS REMEMBERING WHERE IT CAME FROM.
AND BEFORE I LET YOU SPEAK, SUPERVISOR MELGAR WOULD LIKE TO
SAY SOME THINGS. >> THANK YOU.
I COULDN'T PASS UP THE OPPORTUNITY AT THIS
COMMEMORATION. I REMEMBER THIS COMMENDATION IS
UP BECAUSE OF YOUR WORK ON THE EARTHQUAKE COMMEMORATION BUT I
ALSO JUST WANTED TO PUT IN THAT ALL THE OTHER THINGS THAT YOU
DO THAT PEOPLE DON'T SEE BEHIND THE SCENES AT BRINGING PEOPLE
TOGETHER, BUILDING COMMUNITY, ENGAGING IN GOSSIP OCCASIONALLY
ESPECIALLY POLITICAL GOSSIP YOU KNOW, SATURDAY LUNCHES AT ST
JOHN'S GRILL AND ALL THE THINGS THAT YOU DO BEHIND THE SCENES
TO MAKE OUR CITY BETTER, A BETTER PLACE, A MORE VIBRANT
PLACE, A MORE CONNECTED PLACE. SO THANK YOU FOR BEING SUCH A
MENSCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR SUPPORT OF
EVERYTHING CIVIC FOR MANY, MANY DECADES.
I AGREE WITH PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN YOU ARE A TRUE GEM
AND YOU HAVE FRIENDS HERE SUPPORTING YOU TO PROVE IT.
THANK YOU SO MUCH LEE YOU HAD A COUPLE OF FRIENDS HERE ON THE
FLOOR AND A FEW OF YOU HAVE PASSED AROUND SOME RATHER
VICIOUS GOSSIP AT WILLIE BROWN TABLE AND THEN TOLD PEOPLE YOU
HEARD IT FROM WILLIE HA HA HA HA WHICH HE GLADLY ACCEPTED.
WHEN I FIRST MOVED HERE I MOVED TO NORTH BEACH AND IT ABOUT
KILLED ME ALL OF THOSE NIGHTCLUBS, ALL THAT FUN AND I
HAD JUST COME UP FROM WORKING IN THE MUSIC BUSINESS FOR A
LONG TIME SO IT SEEMED A NATURAL AND THEN I RAN INTO
KAREN SAPIENZA WHO TOLD ME THERE'S A WHOLE LOT MORE TO SAN
FRANCISCO THAN NORTH BEACH. >> SHE INTRODUCED ME TO HER
FATHER AND LEO SAPIENZA WHO WAS THE PRESIDENT OR TREASURER OF
JUST ABOUT EVERY ORGANIZATION NO STAGE MAINLY MALE WHERE THEY
COULD ESCAPE AND GO DRINKING WITH SOME PURPOSE IN MIND
AND INTO PURPOSE OF THE SOUTH OF MARKET BOYS IT WAS TO MAKE
SOME MONEY AT A DINNER AND THEN PUT A WREATH UP AND IN THOSE
DAYS THERE WERE MANY, MANY, MANY SURVIVORS.
MY JOB FOR THE FIRST 19 YEARS WAS TO GO AND VISIT WITH I
PROBABLY VISITED WITH FOR GOOD LONG TIMES WITH AS MANY AS 100
OR MORE PEOPLE WHO WERE WELL OVER 100.
SOME OF THEM WERE 109 WHO HAD ONE WHO WAS 119 AND TO HEAR
THEIR STORIES AND I HAVE TO MAKE A DIFFICULT DECISION ABOUT
WHO I WOULD OFFER UP TO THE PROCESS IT JUST HAD A GOOD
STORY FOR EVERYBODY. >> TALK ABOUT OUR ROOTS
AND THERE WASN'T A ONE OF THEM THAT WASN'T THE BEST SPEAKER I
EVER HEARD. AND SO OVER THE YEARS WE HAD
HUNDREDS OF SURVIVORS. SO COMING TO THAT POINT WHICH
YOU POINTED OUT ABOUT, THERE'S NO MORE SURVIVORS ANYMORE,
THERE WAS SOME TALK ABOUT USING CARL BUT TOO MANY PEOPLE KNOW
HIM AND KNOW HOW OLD HE IS. SO WE DIDN'T USE IT.
I UNDERSTAND THAT THIS IS ERIC NATION AND I'M VERY HONORED TO
BE ABLE TO IT. THANK YOU RAFFI THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR THANK YOU ALL FOR HONORING ME IN PERSON IN YOUR
HOME. >> I APPRECIATE IT VERY MUCH.
I GET FLOWERS. I SAID THEY'RE NOT GOING TO
GIVE ME FLOWERS
. YEAH, I ALL RIGHT SO OH, THAT
WOULD TAKE US TO OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDERS.
>> OUR FIRST SET WOULD BE ITEM NUMBER 51.
BUT AS THE AGENDA INDICATES, THE PROJECT SPONSOR WOULD
WITHDREW THEIR PROJECT APPLICATION FOR 1200 LARKIN
STREET AND THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT HAS RESCINDED THEIR
ASSOCIATED APPROVAL LETTER AND THAT MEANS THIS MATTER IS
NOW MOOT AND IS NO LONGER UNDER THE JURISDICTION OF THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS. SO WE WILL NOT BE HOLDING THAT
HEARING AND NOR WILL WE BE ABLE TO TAKE PUBLIC COMMENT SINCE
THE MATTER IS NO LONGER BEFORE US.
THE HEARING WAS ONLY AGENDA IS BECAUSE THE PUBLIC HEARING
NOTICE WAS SENT BEFORE THE APPLICATION HAD BEEN WITHDRAWN
. SO MADAM CLERK LET'S CALL OUR
NEXT SPECIAL ORDER ITEM NUMBER 52.
>> ITEM NUMBER 52 IS A HEARING OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
SITTING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE TO EXAMINE THE POTENTIAL
CONSEQUENCES OF KAISER PERMANENTE'S PROPOSALS
IN COLLECTIVE BARGAINING WITH THE NATIONAL UNION OF HEALTH
CARE WORKERS FOR SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENTS AND EMPLOYEES OF CITY
AND TENT, CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO WHO ARE KAISER
FAMILIES FOR BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CLINICIANS EMPLOYED BY KAISER
AND FOR STANDARDS OF BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE PROFESSIONAL
PRACTICE. COLLEAGUES WE ARE NOW SITTING
AS A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE TO EXAMINE THE POTENTIAL
CONSEQUENCES OF KAISER PERMANENTE PROPOSALS
AND COLLECTIVE BARGAINING WITH THE NATIONAL UNION OF HEALTH
CARE WORKERS. WE HAVE VARIOUS INDIVIDUALS
FROM NIH W HERE TO PRESENT TODAY.
SUPERVISOR CHEN THIS IS YOUR HEARING SO I'M HANDING IT OVER
TO YOU. >> THANK YOU.
BOARD PRESIDENT AND COLLEAGUES .
BEHAVIORAL AND MENTAL HEALTH CARE IS TOO IMPORTANT TO TAKE
FOR GRANTED. TODAY I'M CALLING A HEARING TO
PROVIDE PUBLIC OVERSIGHT TO THE POTENTIAL CONSEQUENCES OF
KAISER'S PROPOSAL IN COLLECTIVE BARGAINING WITH THE NATIONAL
UNION OF HEALTH CARE WORKERS. >> THIS NEGOTIATION WILL HAVE
AN UNDUE IMPACT ON CITY RESIDENTS AND EMPLOYEES OF THE
CITY AND COUNTY WHO ARE KAISER ENROLLEES AND FOR BEHAVIORAL
HEALTH CONDITIONS EMPLOYED BY KAISER.
TODAY'S HEARING WILL ALSO CONSIDER STANDARDS OF
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE PROFESSIONAL PRACTICE.
I WANT TO THANK MY CO-SPONSORS FOR THIS HEARING.
>> BOTH PRESENT MANAGEMENT AND SUPERVISOR WALTON
AND MALKIA. I ORIGINALLY CALL FOR THIS
HEARING AFTER HEARING FROM MULTIPLE CONSTITUENTS INCLUDING
KAISER PATIENTS AND KAISER NURSES ABOUT PROPOSALS MADE BY
KAISER IN THEIR BARGAINING THAT HAVE THE POTENTIAL TO GREATLY
UNDERMINE THE QUALITY OF CARE THAT PATIENTS ENTITLE TO CREATE
UNFAIR HARDSHIP FOR WORKERS AND UNDERMINE HEALTH CARE
STANDARDS THAT WERE PUT IN PLACE YEARS AGO.
I KNOW THAT REPRESENT REPRESENTATIVE FROM UNIONS WILL
GET INTO THIS FOR MORE IN DETAILS BUT I SPECIFICALLY
WANT TO CALL ALL THAT I HAVE HER ALLEGATIONS THAT KAISER'S
USING. ALL MACHINE LEARNING TO REPLACE
CLINICAL JUDGMENT. >> I FIND THIS ABSOLUTELY
UNACCEPTABLE. >> MENTAL AND BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
ARE INCREDIBLY COMPLEX FOR PATIENTS EXPERIENCING THEM
AND EVEN OUR BEST AND MOST ROBUST HEALTH CARE SYSTEMS CAN
BE EXTREMELY DIFFICULT TO NAVIGATE ESPECIALLY WHEN
SOMEONE IT'S IN CRISIS. >> THE IDEA THAT WE WOULD ALLOW
A.I. TO PROVIDE CLINICAL TREATMENT OR CHARGE FOR
PATIENTS IS SHOCKING AND I HAVE SERIOUS CONCERN THAT WITHOUT
ADEQUATE PROTECTIVE LANGUAGE AROUND EMERGING TECHNOLOGY WE
COULD AT BEST MAKE THE PATIENT'S MENTAL AND BEHAVIORAL
HEALTH ISSUE MORE I.Q OR AT WORSE AND EVIDENTLY BE
RESPONSIBLE FOR DRIVING SOMEONE TO CASE.
I'M NOT AGAINST TECHNOLOGY BUT WITHOUT MEANINGFUL DATA
EVIDENCE AND CLINICAL VALIDATION THAT EMERGING
TECHNOLOGY IS READY FOR THE KINDS OF WORK THAT IS ALLEGEDLY
BEING EMPLOYED. IT WOULD THROUGH KAISER WE ARE
RISING PUTTING PATIENTS IN HARM'S WAY.
YESTERDAY A COMPELLING WAS FILED BY NIH W WITH THE
CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF MANAGED HEALTH CARE AND THE
U.S. DEPARTMENT OF LABOR ALLEGING THAT KAISER'S
AUTOMATED EVICTS EVICTS EVE VISIT PORTAL FOR BEHAVIORAL
HEALTH MAKES RECOMMENDATIONS WITHOUT LICENSED CLINICIANS TO
REVIEW. THIS IS A THIS IS THE KIND OF
THINGS I DON'T BELIEVE A AI MACHINE LEARNING ARE ABLE TO DO
AT THIS MOMENT A.I. AND OTHER MACHINE LEARNING EMERGING
TECHNOLOGIES ARE NOT OBLIGATE TO PATIENT CARE OR WELLNESS.
THEY DO NOT TAKE OUR HIPPOCRATIC OATH.
THEY ARE NOT SUBJECT TO A STANDARDIZED REGULATIONS, TESTS
OR OVERSIGHT. >> IF SOMEONE IS SEEKING OUT
THEIR HEALTH CARE PROVIDER TO INQUIRE ABOUT BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
TREATMENT AND THEY DESERVE A MINIMUM TO BE ASSISTED BY A
LICENSED CLINICIANS ON INTAKE. BEFORE WE BEGIN.
I'M SHOCKED AND VERY DISAPPOINTED BY KAISER'S
UNWILLINGNESS TO PARTICIPATE IN TODAY'S HEARING ESPECIALLY
IN LIGHT OF THIS NEW COMPLAINT. >> PARTICIPATION IN HEARING
SUCH AS THIS ARE AN IMPORTANT TO THAT THE POOR USES TO
EMPOWER THE PUBLIC ON KEY ISSUES OF CONCERN.
MENTAL WELLNESS IT'S INCREDIBLY IMPORTANT AND HOW WE ARE TAKING
CARE OF OUR PATIENTS AND WORKERS ESPECIALLY WHAT
EMERGING TECHNOLOGY IS MORE IMPORTANT NOW THAN EVER.
I'M GRATEFUL TO THE MEMBERS OF NEW H W SENIOR AND OTHER
EXPERTS ARE TAKING TIME OUT OF THEIR BUSY DAY TO BE HERE
AND TO EDUCATE THE PUBLIC IN GOOD FAITH.
WITH THAT I WOULD LIKE TO CALL UP SAL ROSSELLI PRESIDENT
EMERITA EMIRATIS NATIONAL UNION OF HEALTHCARE WORKERS TO KICK
US OFF. SHOULD WE HAVE SUPERVISOR
WALTON I BELIEVE IS IN THE QUEUE FIRST THOUGH.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT REDMAN AND I JUST WANTED TO ADD
EMPHASIS TO SUPERVISOR CHIN'S STATEMENT AROUND KAISER NOT
SHOWING UP THIS AFTERNOON. I THINK IT IS EXTREMELY
DISRESPECTFUL THAT KAISER IS NOT HERE NOT JUST FOR THE FACT
THAT FAIR. FAIR BARGAINING PRACTICES
SHOULD BE BASIC FOR AN EMPLOYER BUT WHEN THIS BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS MAKES A REQUEST FOR AN EMPLOYER TO ATTEND A HEARING
THEY MOST CERTAINLY SHOULD MAKE SURE THAT THEY ARE
IN ATTENDANCE. SO I JUST WANT TO EMPHASIZE HOW
DISRESPECTFUL THAT IS THAT KAISER HAS DONE THAT AND THEY
NEED TO TAKE NOTE THAT WE KNOW THAT IS DISRESPECTFUL.
THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON SUPERVISOR WONG.
>> COLLEAGUES AS A FORMER HOSPITAL UNION ORGANIZER I
BELIEVE WORKERS DESERVE A FAIR VOICE AT THE BARGAINING TABLE.
BUT THIS ISSUE GOES BEYOND LABOR RELATIONS.
IT IS ALSO ABOUT KEEPING SAN FRANCISCO SAFE, STABLE
AND FUNCTIONING FAMILIES EXPECT THAT WHEN A LOVED ONE NEEDS
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE, A TRAINED PROFESSIONAL WILL BE
AVAILABLE BEFORE A MANAGEABLE PROBLEM BECOMES AN EMERGENCY
WHEN TREATMENT IS DELAYED OR INTERRUPTED, FAMILIES ARE LEFT
STRUGGLING AND SITUATIONS THAT SHOULD BE HANDLED IN A
CLINICIAN'S OFFICE CAN INSTEAD AND IN AN EMERGENCY ROOM A911
CALL OR A RESPONSE FROM POLICE AND FIREFIGHTERS MAINTAINING AN
EXPERIENCED CLINICAL WORKFORCE IS THEREFORE NOT SIMPLY A UNION
ISSUE IT IS PRACTICAL PUBLIC SAFETY, RESPONSIBLE MANAGEMENT
AND BETTER USE OF OUR EMERGENCY RESOURCES.
KAISER SERVES MANY SAN FRANCISCANS INCLUDING THOUSANDS
OF CITY EMPLOYEES. I WAS BORN AT KAISER GEARY.
I URGED KAISER TO BARGAIN IN GOOD FAITH AND REACH A FAIR,
SUSTAINABLE AGREEMENT THAT KEEPS QUALIFIED CLINICIANS ON
THE JOB PROTECTS CONTINUITY OF CARE AND ADDRESSES BEHAVIORAL
HEALTH NEEDS BEFORE THEY BECOME CRISES.
THAT IS GOOD FOR WORKERS, GOOD FOR PATIENTS AND GOOD FOR
PUBLIC SAFETY. >> THANK YOU.
PRESIDENT ROSELLI. AND I'D JUST LIKE TO FIRST
THANK SUPERVISOR SHARON CHEN FOR CALLING FOR THIS HEARING.
PRESIDENT AND ALDERMAN SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
SUPERVISOR WALTON, THANK YOU FOR CO-SPONSORING IT AND ALL OF
YOU FOR YOUR ONGOING COMMITMENT TO ENSURING THAT ALL SAN
FRANCISCO RESIDENTS AND CITY EMPLOYEES HAVE ACCESS TO
TIMELY, APPROPRIATE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE SERVICES.
NO CITY HAS TAKEN STRONGER ACTION OVER THE YEARS TO HOLD
KAISER PERMANENTE ACCOUNTABLE FOR ITS REPEATED MENTAL HEALTH
ACCESS AND PARITY VIOLATIONS AND TO SUPPORT CLINICIANS
IN THEIR FIGHT FOR THE TIME RESOURCES AND RESPECT THAT THEY
NEED TO BEST SERVE THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
THIS HEARING COMES AT A PIVOTAL MOMENT.
AS REPORTED IN TODAY'S SAN FRANCISCO STANDARD WHEN KAISER
IS PROPOSING TO EXPLOIT NEW TECHNOLOGY TO SAVE MONEY
AND AVOID ACCOUNTABILITY RATHER THAN FINALLY PROVIDING THE
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE THAT PATIENTS NEED AND THAT THEY
THEIR EMPLOYERS AND SAN FRANCISCO TAXPAYERS ARE PAYING
FOR THEM TO RECEIVE. OUR MEMBERS STAND READY TO WORK
CONSTRUCTIVELY WITH KP MANAGEMENT TO MAKE KAISER THE
BEST PLACE TO GIVE AND RECEIVE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE.
I STILL BELIEVE THERE'S A LOT WE CAN ACCOMPLISH TOGETHER BUT
WE'LL NEVER MAKE PROGRESS AS LONG AS KAISER'S INTENT
AND TRYING TO SILENCE US AND REPLACE US.
THANK YOU AGAIN FOR HOLDING THIS HEARING AND FOR YOUR
COMMITMENT TO ACHIEVE REAL MENTAL HEALTH PARITY REAL
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH, HEALTH CARE PARITY AND UAW AS A LEGISLATIVE
PUBLIC POLICY DIRECTOR IS GOING TO SPEAK NEXT.
>> BENJAMIN REICHERT, THANK YOU SO.
GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT SUPERVISORS AND MEMBERS OF THE
PUBLIC. MY NAME IS BENJAMIN REICHERT.
I'M THE POLICY DIRECTOR FOR THE NATIONAL UNION OF HEALTH CARE
WORKERS REPRESENTING THE 2400 PSYCHOLOGISTS, LICENSED
CLINICAL SOCIAL WORKERS, MARRIAGE AND FAMILY THERAPISTS
AND OTHER BEHAVIORAL HEALTH PROFESSIONALS WHO CARE FOR
KAISER PERMANENTE PATIENTS THROUGHOUT NORTHERN CALIFORNIA.
THANK YOU FOR HOLDING THIS HEARING.
THIS IS NOT THE FIRST TIME WE'VE BEEN HERE IN 2022.
THIS BOARD HELD A SIMILAR HEARING IN THE MIDST OF A TEN
WEEK STRIKE DURING WHICH KAISER WAS FOUND TO HAVE CANCELED MORE
THAN 100,000 THERAPY APPOINTMENTS REGION WIDE.
THAT STRIKE ITSELF CAME AFTER MULTIPLE PRIOR STRIKES GOING
BACK MORE THAN A DECADE AND MULTIPLE ROUNDS OF STATE OF
STATE SANCTIONS AGAINST KAISER'S BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
SERVICES DATING ALL THE WAY BACK TO 2013 WHICH INCLUDED THE
IMPOSITION OF AN OUTSIDE MONITOR FOR THREE YEARS.
>> WITH YOUR SUPPORT IN 2022 AND YOU W CLINICIANS ONE MORE
TIME FOR PATIENT CARE DUTIES THAT CAN'T BE DONE DURING
APPOINTMENTS LIKE RESPONDING TO PATIENT CALLS AND TAILORING
TREATMENT PLANS. THEY ALSO WANT A VOICE IN THE
MODEL OF CARE. >> SO AFTER NEARLY TWO DECADES
OF DEFICIENCIES AND LABOR STRIFE IT SEEMED LIKE KAISER
WAS READY TO BEGIN REPAIRING ITS RELATIONSHIP WITH
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CLINICIANS. UNFORTUNATELY IT ENDED ALMOST
AS QUICKLY AS IT BEGAN. >> SINCE WE SETTLED THAT
CONTRACT IN 2022, KAISER HAS BEEN ASSESSED $231 MILLION
IN STATE AND FEDERAL PENALTIES AS PART OF TWO SEPARATE
INVESTIGATIONS. IN A 2023 SETTLEMENT WITH THE
CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF MANAGED HEALTH CARE WHICH
INCLUDED A $50 MILLION FINE, KAISER ACKNOWLEDGED THAT IT
LACKS SUFFICIENT BEHAVIORAL HEALTH PROVIDERS AND THAT QUOTE
THIS LACK OF CLINICAL STAFF HAS RESULTED IN EXCESSIVE WAIT
TIMES FOR ENROLLEE INDIVIDUAL THERAPY APPOINTMENTS.
>> THREE YEARS LATER THE DEPARTMENT OF LABOR ORDERED
KAISER TO REIMBURSE PATIENTS MORE THAN $28 MILLION FOR OUT
OF POCKET MENTAL HEALTH CARE COSTS INCURRED BECAUSE KAISER
DIDN'T PROVIDE THEM THE SERVICES THAT THEY PAID FOR
AND WERE ENTITLED TO RECEIVE. THESE PENALTIES MAY SEEM SEVERE
BUT FOR KAISER THEY'RE A DROP IN THE BUCKET.
LAST YEAR KAISER REPORTED PROFITS OF $9.3 BILLION AND BY
YEAR'S END IT HELD NEARLY 73 BILLION IN RESERVES OF CASH
AND INVESTMENTS. YET DESPITE THESE MASSIVE
FINANCIAL RESOURCES, KAISER EXECUTIVES BACKTRACKED ON THEIR
COMMITMENT TO WORK WITH CLINICIANS TO IMPROVE
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE. THE 2022 CONTRACT INCLUDED
LABOR MANAGEMENT MODEL OF CARE COMMITTEES THAT MADE
RECOMMENDATIONS ON IMPROVING CARE.
NOW KAISER HAS STOPPED FUNDING THE RECOMMENDATIONS OF THOSE
COMMITTEES WHICH THEY HAD CONTRACTUALLY COMMITTED TO DO
AT THE VERY SAME TIME THAT KAISER ENTERED INTO ITS $200
MILLION SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT WITH STATE OFFICIALS.
IT STARTED USING QUESTIONNAIRES AND SCORING ALGORITHMS
ADMINISTERED BY CALL CENTER OPERATORS AND ONLINE TOOLS
RATHER THAN LICENSED BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CLINICIANS TO SCREEN
PATIENTS WHO ARE SEEKING THERAPY FOR THE FIRST TIME.
>> HUMAN ENGAGEMENT AND JUDGMENT HAVE BEEN REMOVED
FROM THIS CLINICAL POINT EXCUSE ME CRITICAL POINT IN THE
PROCESS OF INTAKE AND ASSESSMENT AND INITIALLY
ASSIGNING PATIENTS TO A CARE PATHWAY.
>> DESPITE ALL THIS IN U H W CLINICIANS ARE SIMPLY SEEKING A
CONTRACT WITH KAISER THAT REAFFIRMS THE IMPROVEMENTS
WE'VE BEGUN TOGETHER TO MAKE THINGS BETTER FOR PATIENTS.
UNFORTUNATELY SINCE NEGOTIATIONS STARTED OVER A
YEAR AGO, KAISER PROPOSED REVERSING THE MOST IMPORTANT
GAINS THERAPISTS HAVE MADE. KAISER HAS ALSO PROPOSED WHAT
CLINICIANS ARE CALLING THE TERRIBLE THREE.
THESE THREE EXTREME DEMANDS WOULD DEGRADE THE STANDARD OF
CARE FOR PATIENTS AND SET A DANGEROUS COURSE FOR THE FUTURE
OF BEHAVIORAL HEALTH SERVICES THROUGHOUT THE REGION AND THE
STATE OF COURSE THAT OTHER INSURERS AND PROVIDERS WILL
LIKELY EMULATE TO TRY TO SAVE MONEY.
>> THE FIRST DEMAND INVOLVES ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE
AND IT'S SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA CONTRACT WITH NIH W MEMBERS
SIGNED LAST YEAR. KAISER AGREED THAT THE USE OF
NEW TECHNOLOGIES INCLUDING A.I. QUOTE IS NOT TO REPLACE BUT TO
ASSIST BARGAINING UNIT EMPLOYEES IN PROVIDING SAFE,
THERAPEUTIC AND EFFECTIVE PATIENT CARE AND SUPPORT.
BUT NOW KAISER IS REFUSING TO AGREE TO THAT LANGUAGE
IN NORTHERN CALIFORNIA JUST AS IT HAS BEGUN REPLACING
THERAPISTS WITH TECHNOLOGY TO TRIAGE PATIENTS SEEKING CARE TO
MASK ITS INTENTIONS. KAISER IS PROMOTING AN AI
COMMITTEE BUT THE COMMITTEE WOULD HAVE NO POWER AT ALL.
KAISER COULD VETO THE UNION'S APPOINTMENTS TO IT AND IGNORE
THE COMMITTEE'S RECOMMENDATIONS .
THEIR SECOND DEMAND MAKES A MOCKERY OF KAISER'S STATED
COMMITMENT TO AN INTEGRATED MODEL OF CARE WHERE THERAPISTS
CAN WORK CLOSELY WITH DOCTORS AND OTHER CAREGIVERS UNDER A
UNIFIED CLINICAL MANAGEMENT STRUCTURE.
>> INSTEAD, KAISER IS PROPOSING TO ELIMINATE CONTRACT LANGUAGE
COMMITTING THAT THE USE OF SUBCONTRACTED THERAPISTS QUOTE
WILL NOT RESULT IN THE ELIMINATION AND QUOTE OF
EMPLOYED CLINICIANS. THEY'VE EVEN PROPOSED THE
DETAILS OF SEVERANCE PACKAGES FOR CLINICIANS WHO WOULD BE
LAID OFF. THIS WOULD GIVE KAISER A GREEN
LIGHT TO SUBCONTRACT AN EVEN LARGER VOLUME OF BEHAVIORAL
HEALTH SERVICES TO INDEPENDENT PROVIDERS PERFORMING GIG WORK
ON MENTAL HEALTH PLATFORMS. THESE THERAPISTS CAN'T EASILY
COMMUNICATE WITH THE REST OF KAISER'S CARE TEAM LEAVING
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE AS A SEPARATE AND INFERIOR SERVICE
SEGREGATED FROM THE PROMISE OF KAISER'S INTEGRATED HEALTH CARE
SYSTEM. KAISER'S PROPOSAL WOULDN'T JUST
A GREAT CARE FOR KAISER PATIENTS IT WOULD DEGRADE PAY
AND BENEFIT STANDARDS FOR CLINICIANS INCLUDING THOSE
OUTSIDE OF KAISER WHO HAVE NO VOICE THROUGH A UNION AND WORK
AT THE MERCY OF INSURERS, EMPLOYERS AND PLATFORMS WHOSE
ONLY GOAL IS TO KEEP CLINICIAN REIMBURSEMENTS AS LOW AS
POSSIBLE TO MAXIMIZE THEIR OWN PROFITS.
>> THE THIRD PROVISION WOULD HAND KAISER TOTAL CONTROL TO
DETERMINE HOW CARE IS PROVIDED .
FOR THE FIRST TIME KAISER IS DEMANDING A PROVISION IN THE
CONTRACT STATING THAT KAISER HAS THE SOLE DISCRETION TO
QUOTE DETERMINE OR MODIFY THE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH, OPERATING
AND CLINICAL MODELS OF CARE. >> THIS WOULD FORCE THERAPISTS
TO SURRENDER THE CLINICAL AUTONOMY THEY NEED TO DO THEIR
JOBS IN COMPLIANCE WITH PROFESSIONAL STANDARDS
AND STATE LAW. AND IT WOULD INVITE OTHER MAJOR
INSURERS AND EMPLOYERS TO DEMAND THE SAME OF THEIR
CLINICIANS. >> KAISER'S STATED EXCUSE FOR
MAKING THIS DEMAND IS THAT MENTAL HEALTH PROFESSIONALS
IN SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA AGREED TO IT LAST YEAR.
BUT WHAT KAISER DOESN'T SAY IS THAT IT PROPOSED THAT PROVISION
DEEP INTO A NEARLY SEVEN MONTH STRIKE AND THAT WORKERS VERY
RELUCTANTLY AGREED TO IT AS PART OF A PAINFUL COMPROMISE TO
END THAT BITTER STRUGGLE. KAISER'S TERRIBLE THREE DEMANDS
SHOW THAT INSTEAD OF WORKING WITH CLINICIANS TO IMPROVE
CARE, KAISER WANTS TO SILENCE CLINICIANS AND AVOID
ACCOUNTABILITY. IN THE PROPOSALS KAISER IS
MAKING AT THE BARGAINING TABLE HAVE CONSEQUENCES THAT EXTEND
FAR BEYOND ONE EMPLOYER. >> IF KAISER SUCCEEDS
IN SILENCING ITS CLINICIANS WHILE MOVING FULL STEAM AHEAD
TO OUTSOURCE CARE AND PUSH PATIENTS ONTO A.I. PLATFORMS,
OTHER INSURERS AND EMPLOYERS WILL HAVE EVERY INCENTIVE TO
PURSUE SIMILAR CHANGES THAT WOULD DEGRADE THE QUALITY OF
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND ACROSS
CALIFORNIA. THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HAS
CONSISTENTLY STOOD FOR EQUITABLE ACCESS TO CARE.
STRONG PUBLIC HEALTH SYSTEMS AND RESPONSIBLE CORPORATE
CONDUCT OPPOSING KAISER'S TERRIBLE THREE PROPOSALS IS
CONSISTENT WITH YOUR VALUES. IT WOULD SEND A CLEAR MESSAGE
THAT SAN FRANCISCO EXPECTS ITS LARGEST PRIVATE INSURER TO
STRENGTHEN AND NOT WEAKEN BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE.
IT WOULD TELL KAISER THAT INNOVATION SHOULD SUPPORT
CLINICIANS RATHER THAN REPLACE THEM AND THAT INTEGRATED CARE
SHOULD BE MORE THAN A MARKETING STRATEGY.
MOST IMPORTANTLY, IT WOULD TELL THOUSANDS OF KAISER PATIENTS
THAT THEIR CITY STANDS WITH THEM AND THOSE WHO PROVIDE
THEIR CARE TO DEMAND ACCOUNTABILITY FROM THEIR
POWERFUL AND WELL-ENDOWED HMO. THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME, YOUR
LEADERSHIP AND YOUR COMMITMENT TO PROTECTING ACCESS TO QUALITY
MENTAL HEALTH CARE FOR THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO
AND THROUGHOUT CALIFORNIA. NEXT YOU'RE GOING TO HEAR FROM
THREE THERAPISTS AT KAISER WHO ARE MEMBERS OF H.W. ALANA
MARCIE MORRIS, MOLLY PARSONS AND TIANA LOY.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS ALANA MARCIE MORRIS
AND I AM A LICENSED CLINICAL SOCIAL WORKER AND THERAPIST AT
KAISER PERMANENTE IN OAKLAND ADULT PSYCHIATRY.
>> I ALSO SERVE ON MY UNION'S BARGAINING COMMITTEE.
>> FOR MOST OF MY SEVEN YEARS AT KAISER I WORKED AS A TRIAGE
CLINICIAN WHEN SOMEONE CALLED SEEKING MENTAL HEALTH OR
ADDICTION MEDICINE SERVICES WHETHER THEY LIVED IN SAN
FRANCISCO OR STOCKTON. >> THE FIRST PERSON AT KAISER
THEY TALKED TO WOULD BE SOMEONE LIKE ME A LICENSED HUMAN
THERAPIST WITH SPECIALIZED TRAINING TO ASSESS THEIR
CONDITION AND THEIR TREATMENT NEEDS.
>> A TRIAGE SCREENING IS ABOUT DETERMINING RISK AND HOW URGENT
SOMEONE'S TREATMENT NEEDS ARE. >> IS THIS PERSON A THREAT TO
THEMSELVES OR THEIR LOVED ONES? >> OR CAN THEY WAIT TEN DAYS
FOR AN INTAKE APPOINTMENT? >> DO THEY NEED IMMEDIATE
INTERVENTION OR A WELLNESS CHECK?
WE MAKE THESE DETERMINATIONS USING OUR CLINICAL JUDGMENT
AND OUR OWN HUMANITY. >> WE ASK FOLLOW UP QUESTIONS.
>> WE LISTEN TO NOT ONLY WHAT THEY SAY BUT WHAT THEY DON'T
SAY OR HOW THEY SAY IT. >> WE OBSERVE THEIR TONE, THEIR
CONSISTENCY AND LISTEN FOR CUES THAT INDICATE HIGHER RISK OR
IMMEDIATE OR WARRANT IMMEDIATE INTERVENTION.
>> THIS IS THE ACCEPTED STANDARD FOR HOW TRIAGE SHOULD
WORK IN MENTAL HEALTH CARE BUT IT'S NOW THE EXCEPTION AND NO
LONGER THE NORM AT KAISER. >> INSTEAD OF BEING ABLE TO
COUNT ON HUMAN LICENSE THERAPISTS TO ASSESS AND DECIDE
THE BEST FIRST STEPS FOR THEIR TREATMENT RELYING ON OUR
EXTENSIVE TRAINING, PROFESSIONAL JUDGMENT AND MANY
YEARS OF EXPERIENCE CONDUCTING RISK ASSESSMENTS, KAISER
PATIENTS REACHING OUT FOR OUR SERVICES NOW RELY ON THE
INITIAL PHASE OF THEIR CARE BEING DECIDED BY QUESTIONNAIRES
THAT ARE EITHER READ BY TELEPHONE OPERATORS OR
SELF-ADMINISTERED ONLINE. >> THEIR ANSWERS ARE FED INTO
ALGORITHMS THAT INSTANTLY DECIDE IF A PATIENT QUALIFIES
FOR THERAPY A CLASS AN ONLINE COACHING PROGRAM OR NO CARE AT
ALL. WE HAVE FILED COMPLAINTS
AGAINST THIS PRACTICE WHICH STARTED IN 2023.
KAISER HAS REFUSED TO CONFIRM WHETHER THE DIGITAL ALGORITHMS
ARE GENERATED BY ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE BUT THEIR USE
CLEARLY VIOLATES CALIFORNIA LAW REQUIRING TRIAGE ASSESSMENTS TO
BE PROVIDED BY A QUOTE PHYSICIAN REGISTERED NURSE OR
OTHER QUALIFIED HEALTH PROFESSIONAL ACTING WITHIN
THEIR SCOPE OF PRACTICE AND WHO IS TRAINED TO SCREEN OR TRIAGE
AN ENROLLEE WHO MAY NEED CARE END QUOTE.
>> KAISER ISN'T JUST VIOLATING THE LAW BY HAVING NEW
TECHNOLOGY DO THE WORK OF ITS HUMAN CLINICIANS.
>> IT'S VIOLATING PATIENT CARE STANDARDS AND PUTTING PATIENTS
AT RISK. >> ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE
AND ALGORITHMS DON'T CAPTURE WHAT TRAINED HUMANS CAN A
COMMON SYMPTOM OF DEPRESSION, FOR EXAMPLE, IS TO MINIMIZE
YOUR SYMPTOMS WHEN MAKING DETERMINATIONS BASED
EXCLUSIVELY ON PATIENT REPORTING.
>> AN ALGORITHM MAY DEEM A PATIENT WITH MORE SEVERE WITH A
MORE SEVERE CONDITION AS ONLY HAVING A MILD OR LESS
SIGNIFICANT SYMPTOMS. I SEE THIS ALL THE TIME SINCE
KAISER STARTED USING TELEPHONE OPERATORS AND ALGORITHMS TO
SCREEN PATIENTS SEEKING CARE. >> SO AS THAT WORK WAS REDUCED
MY CURRENT JOB WHAT I DO MORE OF THESE DAYS IS PREDOMINANTLY
CONDUCTING SCHEDULED INTAKE ASSESSMENTS WITH PEOPLE WITH
PEOPLE AFTER THEY'VE BEEN QUOTE TRIAGED BY AN UNLICENSED
OPERATOR OR AN E VISIT ON THE KAISER APP.
TYPICALLY AROUND TWO WEEKS LATER THE ACUITY AND CRITICAL
NATURE OF SYMPTOMS I AM SEEN HAS INCREASED SIGNIFICANTLY
BECAUSE THE APP A AI AN ALGORITHM OR AN UNLICENSED
TELEPHONE OPERATOR INCORRECTLY DETERMINED THAT THEY COULD WAIT
TEN DAYS TO SEE ME OR THEY PERHAPS WAITED EVEN LONGER
BECAUSE THEY WERE INAPPROPRIATELY BOOKED
ELSEWHERE AND NOW I HAVE TO FIX THEIR CARE PLAN.
I HAVE WATCHED PATIENTS WITHDRAW FROM SUBSTANCES ON
CAMERA BECAUSE NOBODY TOLD THEM TO GO TO THE E.R.
OR CONSULT A PHYSICIAN SOONER. APOLOGIZING TO PATIENTS DURING
AN INAPPROPRIATE DAILY BOOKED INTAKE APPOINTMENT BECAUSE THEY
EXPECTED TO BE SEEN BY A PSYCHIATRIST CAPABLE OF
REFILLING THEIR CRITICAL MEDICATION HAS BECOME A ROUTINE
PART OF MY DAY'S. AS A MEMBER OF OUR UNION'S
BARGAINING TEAM. I DIDN'T THINK NEW TECHNOLOGIES
LIKE ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE AND ALGORITHMS WERE GOING TO BE
A MAJOR ISSUE IN OUR NEGOTIATIONS.
>> LAST YEAR OUR COUNTERPARTS WHO PROVIDED WHO PROVIDE
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE FOR KAISER IN SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA
SETTLED A CONTRACT WITH LANGUAGE STATING THE INTENTION
OF NEW TECHNOLOGIES WAS TO SUPPORT THERAPIES NOT REPLACE
US. SO WE WERE STUNNED WHEN KAISER
REJECTED THAT EXACT LANGUAGE FOR US HERE IN NORTHERN
CALIFORNIA. WE ASKED THEIR BARGAINING TEAM
FLAT OUT IF THAT MEANT THEY WERE PLANNING TO REPLACE US
AND THEY SAID THAT THEY WANTED THAT FLEXIBILITY.
>> I BELIEVE KAISER CAN'T PROMISE NOT TO REPLACE US WITH
AI IN OUR CONTRACT BECAUSE IT IS ALREADY DOING IT.
>> IT IS ALREADY USING NEW TECHNOLOGY TO TAKE WORK AWAY
FROM US HUMAN LICENSE THERAPISTS AND IT WANTS TO BE
ABLE TO REPLACE US ALTOGETHER. >> KAISER HAS NEVER TRULY
UNDERSTOOD MENTAL HEALTH CARE. THE RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN THE
THERAPISTS AND THE PATIENT IS AN INTEGRAL PART OF OUR
TREATMENT. OUR PATIENTS AREN'T COMING TO
US WITH BROKEN BONES. >> YOU CAN'T FIX DEPRESSION
WITH A SCREW IN A NAIL. >> THIS IS INHERENTLY HUMAN
WORK AND WE HAVE TO USE OUR HUMANITY.
I USE MY HUMAN EMPATHY TO HELP PATIENTS HEAL AND I USE MY
HUMAN ANXIETY TO KEEP MY PATIENTS ALIVE.
WHEN MY ANXIETY GOES OFF MY INTERNAL METER THAT THIS
PATIENT NEEDS A LITTLE BIT MORE OF MY ATTENTION TO STAY SAFE
THAT GIVES ME THE CHANCE TO LEAN INTO THEIR CARE.
WHEN THOSE RISK FACTORS PILE UP AS A HUMAN I AM ALSO
ACCOUNTABLE. >> I CAN LOSE MY LICENSE IF I
COMMIT MALPRACTICE. >> WILL SOFTWARE DEVELOPERS OR
BILLION DOLLAR HEALTH PLANS BE HELD ACCOUNTABLE WHEN
TECHNOLOGY MAKES A FATAL ERROR ?
I DO NOT SEE AI BEING USED FOR GOOD.
>> WHERE I WORK I SEE IT MAKING DANGEROUS PATIENT CARE ERRORS.
I SEE IT REINFORCING RACIAL AND GENDER BIAS.
>> YET KAISER IS PROPOSING TO INCREASE ITS ABILITY TO LAY OFF
THERAPISTS AND OUTSOURCE MORE PATIENTS TO THIRD PARTY
COMPANIES THAT USE CHAT BOT COACHING CHAT BASED THERAPY
AND OTHER INNOVATIVE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH APPS IN ORDER TO REDUCE
ITS NEED FOR HUMAN LABOR. >> THIS ISN'T ABOUT GENUINE
INNOVATION. IT'S ABOUT SAVING A BUCK AT THE
EXPENSE OF PATIENT CARE AND PUBLIC HEALTH.
IF WE DON'T STOP THEM NOW WE WON'T STAND A CHANCE DOWN THE
ROAD. >> THANK YOU.
>> HELLO, EVERYBODY. MY NAME IS MOLLY PARSONS.
I AM A THERAPIST AT KAISER AND I HAVE BEEN FOR FIVE YEARS.
>> BUT I ALSO HAVE A PRIVATE PRACTICE WHERE I WORK WITH AN
AGENCY OR A THIRD PARTY CONTRACTOR AND NON KAISER
PATIENTS. SO MY AGENCY THAT I WORK FOR IS
SIMILAR TO THOSE THAT KAISER WANTS TO OUTSOURCE CARE TO FOR
AS MANY MENTAL HEALTH BEHAVIORAL HEALTH PATIENTS AS
IT CHOOSES EVEN IF THAT MEANS LAYING OFF STAFF THERAPISTS
LIKE MYSELF. NOW IF YOU'VE EVER SEEN A
KAISER ADVERTISEMENT AND THEY'RE HARD TO AVOID, YOU
KNOW THAT KAISER TOUTS ITS INTEGRATED HEALTH CARE SYSTEM.
>> ALL OF YOUR PROVIDERS ARE UNDER ONE ROOF COMMUNICATING
AND COORDINATING COORDINATING CARE FOR YOU SEAMLESSLY.
>> AND IN FAIRNESS, THAT MODEL THAT INTEGRATED HEALTH CARE
SYSTEM IS AN EXCELLENT MODEL. THAT'S WHY I CAN'T REALLY
UNDERSTAND WHY KAISER WANTS TO SEGREGATE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
FROM IT AND TREAT IT AS A SECOND CLASS SERVICE WITHIN
KAISER. >> I COMMUNICATE WITH OTHER
CARE PROVIDERS TO LET THEM KNOW ABOUT WHAT IS GOING ON WITH A
MUTUAL PATIENT TO NUDGE THEM WHEN THEY'VE DROPPED THE BALL
OR VICE VERSA FRANKLY AND TO ADVOCATE FOR THE NEEDS OF
CLIENTS. I CAN SEE WHAT IS PHYSICALLY
IMPACTING PATIENTS IF THEY'VE BEEN HOSPITALIZED OR ADMITTED
TO THE E.R. AND ANY TEST RESULTS.
>> I CAN SEE WHAT APPOINTMENTS THEY'VE ATTENDED OR THOSE THAT
THEY'VE MISSED AND KNOWING ALL OF THIS INFORMATION HELPS ME
PROVIDE BETTER RESOURCES FOR EACH CLIENT AND HELPS ME BETTER
PREPARE FOR EACH SESSION. THE OPPOSITE IS TRUE WHEN I'M
SEEING PATIENTS THROUGH THIRD PARTY CONTRACTORS.
WHEN I OPEN THEIR CHARTS I DON'T SEE ANY NOTES FROM THEIR
PHYSICIANS. I DON'T KNOW WHAT IS HAPPENING
WITH THEM PHYSICALLY OR MEDICALLY.
>> TYPICALLY CLIENTS USE THESE THIRD PARTY CONTRACTORS FOR
THERAPY ONLY AND THEY EVEN GET PSYCHIATRIST CARE ELSEWHERE.
>> IF I HAVE CONCERNS ABOUT PHYSICAL OR MEDICAL ISSUES,
IT'S DIFFICULT TO CONNECT WITH THE OTHER CARE PROVIDERS.
AND SO OFTEN THERE ISN'T ANY CONSULTATION WHEN OUTSIDE
THERAPISTS CANNOT EVEN PRESCRIBE TIME OFF WORK OR GIVE
ACCOMMODATIONS IF THOSE ARE NEEDED.
SO THERE'S SOMETHING ELSE TO UNDERSTAND ABOUT REFERRING
PEOPLE OUTSIDE OF KAISER. >> NEARLY ALL OF THE
APPOINTMENTS WITH KAISER KAISER'S THIRD PARTY BEHAVIORAL
HEALTH CONTRACTORS ARE TELEHEALTH AND THAT DOESN'T
WORK FOR A LOT OF PEOPLE LIKE OLDER ADULTS, YOUNGER KIDS
AND THOSE WHO DON'T HAVE A SAFE SPACE TO TAKE A CALL FROM.
>> THESE ISSUES ARE PART OF THE REASON MANY KAISER PATIENTS WHO
HAVE BEEN REFERRED TO A THIRD PARTY CONTRACTOR END UP
RETURNING TO KAISER. >> PEOPLE'S CONDITIONS OFTEN
GET WORSE WHEN THEY'VE BOUNCED BACK AND FORTH BETWEEN KAISER
AND EXTERNAL PROVIDERS. THE SHUFFLING AMONG MULTIPLE
CLINICIANS INHIBITS THE THERAPEUTIC ALLIANCE
AND DISRUPTS THE CONTINUITY OF CARE.
>> WHAT'S MORE, WHEN THEY RETURN TO KAISER FROM OUTSIDE
TREATMENT IT'S HARDER FOR US TO MEET THEIR NEEDS BECAUSE OUR
SCHEDULES ARE SO FULL. >> WE CAN'T SEE THEM AS QUICKLY
AS THEY NEED TO BE SEEN AND WE CAN'T GIVE THEM THE FREQUENCY
THAT THEY NEED. THEY ARE STUCK THEN CHOOSING
BETWEEN MORE FREQUENT THERAPY WITH AN EXTERNAL PROVIDER
WITHOUT THE INTEGRATED MODEL THEY SIGNED UP FOR AND PAY FOR
OR TO BE SEEN LESS FREQUENTLY THAN THEY NEED.
>> ONE OF THE MOST FRUSTRATING ASPECTS OF THIS THIRD PARTY
CONTRACTORS IS THEY SEE THE EASY CLIENTS WITH MILD ISSUES
THOSE THAT LIKELY COULD BE SEEN LESS FREQUENTLY BUT THEY ARE
THE PEOPLE WHO CANNOT HOOK BUT THEIR EXCUSE ME BUT THEY ARE
THE PEOPLE WHO CAN ACTUALLY SEE CLIENTS WEEKLY.
>> THE THIRD PARTY CONTRACTORS ARE.
>> KAISER KEEPS ALL THE SEVERE AND HIGH NEEDS CLIENTS TO QUOTE
UNQUOTE MONITOR THEM. BUT TELL ME HOW CAN I MONITOR
MY HIGH NEEDS CLIENTS WHEN I DON'T HAVE ANY OPEN
APPOINTMENTS? >> ONE OF THE DEFICIENCIES
KAISER WAS CITED FOR AS PART OF THE 200 MILLION STATE
SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT WAS NOT ADEQUATELY MONITORING ITS
EXTERNAL PROVIDER NETWORKS. I'VE BEEN SEEN AS A CLIENT
MYSELF THROUGH THESE EXTERNAL PROVIDER NETWORKS AND I CAN
ATTEST TO MY NEGATIVE EXPERIENCE.
I'VE HAD A THERAPIST NOT SHOW UP MULTIPLE TIMES, NOT FOCUS ON
THE ISSUES THAT I'VE RAISED. I'VE ASKED FOR SPECIFIC TYPES
OF THERAPY AND BEEN ASSIGNED TO THERAPISTS.
AND WHEN I MEET THEM THEY DON'T PROVIDE THAT AT ALL.
NOW KAISER WANTS TO BE ABLE TO RELY ON EXTERNAL PROVIDER
NETWORKS ENTIRELY AND LAY OFF ITS STAFF THERAPISTS.
>> KAISER'S HYPOCRISY IS MADDENING IN PUBLIC IT SAYS
JOIN US AND YOU'LL GET THE BENEFITS OF INTEGRATED HEALTH
CARE. BUT IN PRIVATE CONTRACT
NEGOTIATIONS, KAISER TELLS US THAT MENTAL HEALTH ISN'T
IMPORTANT ENOUGH TO REMAIN PART OF ITS INTEGRATED HEALTH CARE
SYSTEM. >> LOOK AT THE BIG PICTURE
KAISER HAS $73 BILLION IN RESERVES AND IT HAS RACKED
UP $231 MILLION IN PENALTIES FOR MENTAL HEALTH VIOLATIONS
OVER THE PAST THREE YEARS ALONE.
>> YET ONE OF THE MAIN REASONS WE DON'T HAVE A CONTRACT OVER A
YEAR OF NEGOTIATIONS IS THAT KAISER IS INSISTING ON BEING
ABLE TO PROVIDE A LESSER STANDARD OF CARE TO BEHAVIORAL
HEALTH PATIENTS AND THE CHANGES IT WANTS TO MAKE COMPLETELY
CONTRADICT HOW KAISER MARKETS ITSELF TO THE PATIENTS WE
SERVE. MAKE IT MAKE SENSE TO ME.
WHAT KAISER IS PROPOSING WOULDN'T JUST BE BAD FOR KAISER
PATIENTS IT WOULD BE BAD FOR BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND CALIFORNIA. >> KAISER'S PROPOSAL WOULD
FURTHER ENCOURAGE OTHER HMOS AND PROVIDER GROUPS TO TREAT
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH AS A SEPARATE AND THEREFORE LESSER SERVICE
AND FOLLOW KAISER IN TAKING STEPS TO LOWER THEIR COSTS
AND REPLACE HUMAN CARE WITH TECHNOLOGY.
>> AT A MOMENT WHEN INSURERS ARE ALREADY CUTTING
REIMBURSEMENT RATES FOR MENTAL HEALTH THERAPY, KAISER'S
PROPOSAL WOULD DRIVE EVEN MORE CALIFORNIA THERAPISTS TO FORGO
INSURANCE AND ONLY SEE PATIENTS WHO CAN PAY OUT OF POCKET.
>> KAISER CLEARLY WANTS TO RADICALLY DOWNSIZE ITS
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH WORKFORCE AND RELY MORE ON APPS
AND EXTERNAL VENDORS. WE WANT KAISER TO PROVIDE GOOD
CARE AND GOOD JOBS JUST LIKE THEIR ADS SAY THEY WILL.
>> THANK YOU. >> BEFORE THE NEXT SPEAKER I
WOULD LIKE TO TELL MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC THERE IS A
PROHIBITION ON AUDIBLE SOUNDS OF SUPPORT OR OPPOSITION
OUTSIDE OF OUR ACCOMMODATION PERIOD.
SO IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SHOW YOUR SUPPORT PLEASE USE YOUR
HANDS. >> THANK YOU.
>> HI MY NAME IS TIANA LE AND I'M A THERAPIST FOR KAISER
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO. I STARTED LATE LAST YEAR TO BE
PART OF A NEW LGBTQ PLUS TREATMENT TRACK LAST MONTH.
>> I TOLD MANAGEMENT THAT I WAS LEAVING KAISER BECAUSE THE
TRACK HAD NOT YET MATERIALIZED AND I WASN'T TREATING THE
PEOPLE I KNEW THAT COULD BEST SERVE.
>> BUT I'M STILL HERE BECAUSE TO MY SHOCK MANAGEMENT
RESPONDED BY FINALLY GETTING THE LGBTQ PLUS TRACK UP
AND RUNNING. >> I'M GIVING IT A SHOT BUT
THERE ARE STILL REALLY BIG PROBLEMS.
>> SO TO START WE DON'T HAVE ENOUGH STAFF OR CLINICAL
AUTONOMY TO DO OUR BEST FOR PATIENTS AND THERE IS
ABSOLUTELY NO EXCUSE FOR THIS. INSTEAD OF SEEING PEOPLE EVERY
TWO WEEKS AS REQUIRED BY STATE LAW, MY PATIENTS ON AVERAGE IF
THEY'RE LUCKY, HAVE TO WAIT 3 TO 4 WEEKS BETWEEN
APPOINTMENTS. THERE HAVE BEEN TIMES WHEN A
CLIENT HAS REACHED OUT TO ME SAYING I'VE HAD A LOVED ONE
PASS AWAY. DO YOU HAVE AN APPOINTMENT?
CAN I BE SEEN SOONER? AND I HAVE TO SAY NO.
>> OTHER TIMES I'VE HAD THE LAST MINUTE AND TAKE
APPOINTMENTS WITH PATIENTS WHO ARE HIGHER RISK AND NEED TO BE
SEEN WEEKLY BUT I CAN'T SEE THEM FOR THREE WEEKS BECAUSE I
DON'T HAVE ANY APPOINTMENTS. >> KAISER IS A MODEL OF CARE.
>> FLAT OUT DOES NOT WORK. IT OFTEN TAKES PATIENTS A MONTH
BETWEEN WHEN THEY ARE FIRST SCREENED FOR TREATMENT AND WHEN
THEY ACTUALLY START TREATMENT WITH THEIR KAISER THERAPIST.
BY THE TIME THEY COME TO US THEIR SYMPTOMS ARE OFTEN WORSE
AND THEY'RE UPSET OVER HOW THEY'VE BEEN TREATED AND THAT
THEY'RE GOING TO HAVE TO WAIT ANOTHER FEW WEEKS TO BE SEEN
AGAIN. AND SO THE CYCLE CONTINUES.
>> THE SCREENING PROCESS ITSELF HAS BEEN DEGRADED.
NOW THAT KAISER USES TELEPHONE OPERATORS AND ALGORITHMS TO
SCREEN PATIENTS, THERE IS NO METHOD FOR THEM TO REQUEST
PREFERENCES IN A THERAPIST THAT MIGHT INFLUENCE TREATMENTS SUCH
AS CULTURAL BACKGROUND OR GENDER IDENTITY.
I'VE HAD LGBTQ PLUS PATIENTS TELL ME THEY'VE WAITED FOREVER
TO FIND A CLINICIAN WITH MY BACKGROUND AND THAT THEY WERE
GOING TO FOREGO TREATMENT IF THEY DID NOT COME TO SOMEONE
LIKE ME. >> WHEN PATIENTS ARE
ESSENTIALLY TOLD HERE IS YOUR OPTION, TAKE IT OR LEAVE IT
THAT IS NOT ETHICAL AND THAT IS NOT GOOD CLINICAL CARE.
>> NOT AT ALL. >> KAISER IS A MODEL DOESN'T
JUST SHORTCHANGE PATIENTS ON THEIR WAY INTO THE SYSTEM.
>> THERE'S A TREND WE HAVE CALLED KAISER EYES.
SO KAISER TAKES UP IN SPACE TREATMENTS AND OFFERS PATIENTS
LESS THAN A CLINICAL STANDARD. SO FOR EXAMPLE A 90 MINUTE
SESSION BECOMES A 60 MINUTE SESSION AT KAISER A PROGRAM
THAT REQUIRES 12 SESSIONS TO GRADUATE BECOMES AN EIGHT
SESSION PROGRAM A KAISER KAISER MODEL IS TO KEEP PUTTING LESS
CHEERIOS IN THE BOX AND HOPE THAT NO ONE NOTICES DENIALS.
>> A VOICE IN THE MODEL OF CARE WOULD HELP ENSURE NO SORRY
WOULD HELP KAISER ENSURE NO ONE EVER NOTICES.
>> KAISER'S APPROACH TO BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE BOILS
DOWN TO THIS. KEEP STAFFING LOW AND MAKE
EVERYONE DO NONSTOP WORK. >> IN PREVIOUS JOBS I'VE HELD
I'D HAVE ABOUT 20 TO 25 POINTS PER WEEK.
>> BUT AT KAISER I'M EXPECTED TO SEE 31 PATIENTS PER WEEK.
>> THERE IS ALMOST NEVER ENOUGH TIME FOR CHART REVIEW
PREPARATION. >> CLINICAL DOCUMENTATION
AND FOLLOW UP CARE COORDINATION AND CONSULTATIONS.
>> IF I HAVE A CANCELLATION ON MY SCHEDULE I HAVE TIME TO
AND DRINK WATER. IF I'M LUCKY BUT THEN TYPICALLY
I'M IMMEDIATELY BOOKED AT THE LAST MINUTE USUALLY WITH A HIGH
ACUITY PATIENT AND ALMOST NEVER ENOUGH TIME TO REVIEW THEIR
CHARTS. >> KAISER WANTS MAXIMUM
PRODUCTIVITY BUT WE'RE NOT MAKING WIDGETS.
WE'RE HELPING PEOPLE CONFRONT DEVASTATING TRAUMA AND DISCUSS
THEIR MOST PRIVATE THOUGHTS. >> WE NEED TO BE 100% PRESENT.
>> BUT IS MY LAST PATIENT OF THE DAY GETTING AS MUCH AS ME
AS MY FIRST PATIENT? >> MY ONLY HOPE IN TRYING TO
STAY WITH KAISER IS THAT WE'RE BARGAINING FOR A NEW CONTRACT
AND THAT WE CAN MAKE THINGS BETTER.
BUT KAISER WANTS TO MAKE THINGS WORSE.
>> THEY WANT TO BE ABLE TO PUT PATIENTS INTO THE PRECIOUS HOUR
OR SO A PERSPECTIVE TIME I GET EVERY DAY TO PREPARE FOR
APPOINTMENTS AND THEN FRANTICALLY RESPOND TO PATIENT
CALLS AND EMAILS, FINISH MAKING NOTES AND PATIENT CHARTS
AND CALL SOCIAL SERVICE AGENCIES.
>> IF KAISER PREVAILS AND CONTRACT NEGOTIATIONS I
WON'T BE ABLE TO DO THIS JOB ANYMORE.
>> THERE WOULD BE NO BREAK WHATSOEVER JUST TO BREATHE.
IT WOULD BE PHYSICALLY MENTALLY AND EMOTIONALLY IMPOSSIBLE TO
DO THE JOB BECAUSE WE'RE ALREADY STRETCHED SO THIN.
>> IT'S ONE THING TO WORK FRANTICALLY KNOWING THAT YOUR
WORK IS MAKING A DIFFERENCE BUT IT'S INTOLERABLE WHEN YOU KNOW
THAT AS FAST AND AS HARD AS YOU WORK IT'S NOT ENOUGH FOR THE
PEOPLE WHO DEPEND ON YOU. WHEN I SEE PATIENTS ONLY ONCE A
MONTH IT'S HARD TO BUILD RAPPORT.
IT FEELS LIKE EACH TIME YOU MEET YOU'RE STARTING OVER.
IT'S TERRIBLE FOR PATIENTS. THEY GET FRUSTRATED.
SOMETIMES THEY GET INTO CRISES AND NEED A HIGHER LEVEL OF
CARE. WE ALL KNOW THAT KAISER HAS A
PROBLEM WHEN IT COMES TO BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE.
>> THE QUESTION IS HOW DO WE SOLVE IT?
KAISER THINKS THAT ONLY MANAGEMENT CONTROL CAN FIX THE
PROBLEM BUT THEY DON'T KNOW WHAT THE REAL PROBLEM IS.
THEY THINK THE PROBLEM IS THAT THEY'RE GETTING FINED
AND PENALIZED AND THE SOLUTION IS TO SILENCE THOSE OF US WHO
BLOW THE WHISTLE ON THEM. >> SO FOR CLINICIANS LIKE ME,
THE GOAL IS NOT TO HELP KAISER STAY OUT OF TROUBLE WITH STATE
AND FEDERAL REGULATORS. OUR GOAL IS TO HELP OUR
PATIENTS TO THE BEST OF OUR ABILITY.
>> WE CAN'T DO THAT IF WE HAVE NO SAY IN KAISER'S MODEL OF
CARE. >> DO YOU REALLY TRUST THAT
KAISER MANAGEMENT ALONE CAN FIX THIS PROBLEM?
>> BECAUSE AFTER A YEAR AT KAISER I CERTAINLY DON'T THANK
YOU. >> THANK YOU ALL THE
PRESENTERS. BEFORE WE GOT TO QUESTIONS
LET'S COP ALL THE PRESENTATIONS .
LET'S CAN WE HAVE DR. ADJUSTMENTS MYTH ASSOCIATE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE NATIONAL ASSOCIATION OF SOCIAL
WORKERS CALIFORNIA CHAPTERS UP AND THEN AFTER DR. SMITH LET'S
HAVE DR. LINDA MICHAELS CHAIR OF THE CELL THERAPY ACTION
NETWORK. >> DR. SMITH GOOD AFTERNOON
PRESIDENT, CHAIR AND SUPERVISORS THANK YOU FOR
THE OPPORTUNITY TO JOIN THE DISCUSSION TODAY.
MY NAME IS DR. JASMINE SMITH. I'M A DOCTOR OF SOCIAL WORK
AND LICENSED CLINICAL SOCIAL WORKER AND THE ASSOCIATE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE NATIONAL ASSOCIATION OF SOCIAL
WORKERS CALIFORNIA CHAPTER WHERE I LEAD STATEWIDE
PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT POLICY ADVOCACY AND LEGISLATIVE
INITIATIVES THAT STRENGTHEN BEHAVIORAL HEALTH WORKFORCE
AND REPRESENT MORE THAN 9000 PROFESSIONAL AND STUDENT SOCIAL
WORKERS SUPPORTING VULNERABLE COMMUNITIES.
SOCIAL WORKERS ARE GUIDED BY THE ENHANCED W CODE OF ETHICS
GROUNDED IN THE PRINCIPLES OF SERVICE SOCIAL JUSTICE, DIGNITY
AND WORTH OF THE PERSON. THE IMPORTANCE OF HUMAN
RELATIONSHIP UP'S INTEGRITY AND COMPETENCE THEY ARE ETHICAL
OBLIGATIONS THAT GUIDE EVERY CLINICAL DECISION WE MAKE
IN EVERY RELATIONSHIP THAT WE BUILD WITH THOSE WE SERVE.
ADDITIONALLY, AS REGISTERED ASSOCIATES AND LICENSED
PROFESSIONALS WE ARE ALSO HELD ACCOUNTABLE TO THE CALIFORNIA
BOARD OF BEHAVIORAL SCIENCES TO PROVIDE COMPETENT APPROPRIATE
CARE CONSISTENT WITH OUR ETHICAL AND LEGAL
RESPONSIBILITIES. HOWEVER, MANY OF OUR MEMBERS
EMPLOYED BY KAISER HAVE REPORTED THAT THEY FELT
SYSTEMIC BARRIERS DIRECTLY IMPACTED THEIR ABILITY TO
ADHERE TO THE CODE OF ETHICS. FIRST, BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
SCREENINGS ARE TYPICALLY A CLIENT'S FIRST INTERACTION
IN SEEKING MENTAL HEALTH CARE AND IT IS CRUCIAL THAT THEY ARE
MET WITH AN ETHICALLY AND CULTURALLY COMPETENT
PROVIDER WHO CAN NOT ONLY PROVIDE THE EMPATHY AND WARMTH
REQUIRED TO AUTHENTICALLY BUILD RAPPORT BUT AID THEM SCUSE ME
AID THE CLIENT IN SHARING THEIR CONCERNS AND SYMPTOMS.
THE LICENSED CLINICIAN CONDUCTING THE ASSESSMENT HAS
THE EXPERTISE AND KNOWLEDGE TO RECOGNIZE THE SUBTLE SIGNS OF
CRISIS TRAUMA OR ESCALATING RISK THAT MAY NOT BE OBVIOUS
IN A SCRIPTED CONVERSATION. IT IS DEEPLY CONCERNING TO
LEARN THAT KAISER PERMANENTE HAS REPLACED LICENSED
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH PROFESSIONALS.
WHAT UNLICENSED STAFF AN ALGORITHM WILL SCUSE ME
ALGORITHMICALLY DIRECTED SCREENING TOOLS DURING THE
INITIAL INTAKE PROCESS SINCE JANUARY 2020 FOR THE CALL
CENTER OPERATORS WHO APPLY THESE TOOLS ARE NOT QUALIFIED
TO RECOGNIZE RISK FACTORS EXERCISE PROFESSIONAL JUDGMENT
AND DETERMINE THE APPROPRIATE LEVEL AND URGENCY OF CARE.
>> ADDITIONALLY, KAISER HAS REFUSED TO ANSWER WHETHER
SCREENING TOOLS RELY IN ANY WAY ON ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE.
>> A.I. CAN ONLY REFLECT THE DATA THAT IT IS TRAINED ON.
AND WE KNOW THAT HEALTH CARE DATA REFLECTS LONG STANDING
IN EQUITIES. >> RESEARCHERS INCLUDING DR.
TIERRA TANSLEY HAS RECENTLY HIGHLIGHTED HOW I CAN REINFORCE
EXISTING DISPARITIES WHEN HISTORIC BIAS IS BUILT INTO THE
DATA USED TO DEVELOP THESE TOOLS.
>> A 2022 STUDY AND FOUND THAT A MACHINE LEARNING SYSTEM
ALGORITHM CAUSED BLACK PATIENTS TO EXPERIENCE 33% LONGER WAIT
TIMES BECAUSE IT RELIED ON FACTORS THAT WERE CLOSELY TIED
TO RACE. >> AND MORE RECENTLY IN 2020
FOR A SYSTEMIC REVIEW FOUND THAT RACIAL DISPARITIES
IN HEALTH CARE AI ARE DRIVEN BY BIASED DATASETS HISTORICAL
INEQUITIES, ALGORITHM DESIGN AND THE WAY THESE SYSTEMS ARE
IMPLEMENTED. KAISER PERMANENTE PLANS TO
EXPAND THE USE OF AI ALGORITHMS AND BEHAVIORAL HEALTH SCREENING
AND TREATMENT BUT WHEN THEY ARE DOING THAT THESE STUDIES CANNOT
BE IGNORED. >> DECISIONS ABOUT HOW QUICKLY
SOMEONE RECEIVES TREATMENT OR WHAT LEVEL OF CARE THEY NEED
SHOULD NOT BE INFLUENCED BY TECHNOLOGY THAT REINFORCES
EXISTING DISPARITIES. I CAN BE A HELPFUL TOOL TO
SUPPORT ADMINISTRATIVE TASKS OR ASSIST CLINICIANS BUT IT SHOULD
NEVER REPLACE THE PROFESSIONAL JUDGMENT OF LICENSED BEHAVIORAL
HEALTH PROVIDERS ESPECIALLY WHEN PATIENTS ARE SEEKING HELP
DURING MOMENTS OF CRISIS. KAISER'S ACTIONS MAY PUT IT OUT
OF COMPLIANCE WITH THE CALIFORNIA'S REQUIREMENT UNDER
THE HEALTH AND SAFETY CODE SECTION 1367 .03, WHICH DIRECTS
THAT BEHAVIORAL HEALTH SERVICES MUST BE ASSESSED AND REFERRED
BY LICENSED BEHAVIORAL HEALTH PROVIDERS.
THESE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH ASSESSMENTS SIMPLY CANNOT BE
REDUCED TO SCRIPTED QUESTIONS OR ALGORITHMS BECAUSE THEY SET
THE FOUNDATION FOR TREATMENT AND GETTING THEM WRONG CAN HAVE
SERIOUS CONSEQUENCES FOR PATIENT SAFETY.
WHILE KAISER MAY CLAIM THAT THERE ARE BENEFITS FROM THIS
CHANGE SINCE JANUARY OF 2025, THERAPISTS HAVE DOCUMENTED MORE
THAN 70 EXAMPLES OF NEGATIVE PATIENT CARE OUTCOMES
ASSOCIATED WITH THESE NEW SCREENING PROCESSES SUCH THAT
PATIENTS DETERMINED TO BE HIGH RISK EXPERIENCE LONGER WAIT
TIMES OF MORE THAN ONE WEEK TO INITIATE SERVICES AGAIN
JEOPARDIZING THEIR SAFETY. I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO ADDRESS
THE CONCERN OF PROVIDER BURNOUT IN RELATION TO CLIENT CARE.
A 2025 STUDY FOUND THAT HIGH LEVELS OF BURNOUT AMONG MENTAL
HEALTH PROFESSIONALS OFTEN CALLED THEM CAUSE THEM TO LEAD
TO INCREASED STAFF TURNOVER CAUSING A RIPPLE EFFECT
IN WHICH REMAINING STAFF MEMBERS TAKE ON HEAVIER
CASELOADS LEADING TO FURTHER BURNOUT AND EXASPERATING THE
CYCLE OF STAFF DEPARTURES. THIS CREATES AN UNHEALTHY
ENVIRON IN WHICH INSUFFICIENT RESOURCES ARE THERE TO MEET
PATIENT NEEDS CAUSING THE PROVIDERS TO HAVE LESS TIME TO
DEDICATE TO EACH PATIENT LESS INDIVIDUALIZED PATIENT CARE
AND IN ADDITION TO THE REDUCED TIME FOR PATIENT INTERACTIONS.
BURNOUT HAS BEEN ASSOCIATED WITH DECREASED PRODUCTIVITY
AND LOWER QUALITY OF WORK BUT MOST IMPORTANTLY IT UNDERMINES
THE THERAPEUTIC RELATIONSHIP AS IT IMPACTS THE CLIENT'S
ENTOMBMENT WITH THEIR CLIENTS AND ABILITY TO ENGAGE WITH
EMPATHY. WE HAVE ALSO HEARD FROM OUR
MEMBERS AS THEY HAVE SHARED THE OVERWHELMING BURDEN OF NOT ONLY
HAVING ENOUGH TIME TO DECOMPRESS AND PROCESS BETWEEN
PATIENTS. ONE NOTED THAT THEY HAVE MADE
MULTIPLE ERRORS WITH CLIENTS AS THEY CANNOT BE ENTIRELY PRESENT
DUE TO THEIR WORK OVERLOAD. >> ANOTHER NOTED THAT THEY SEE
6 TO 8 CLIENTS A DAY AND END UP WORKING AN ADDITIONAL UNPAID
THREE HOURS AFTER AN A SCHEDULED EIGHT HOUR DAY EVERY
SINGLE DAY OF THEIR SHIFT JUST TO ENSURE THAT THEY ARE MEETING
THEIR PRODUCTIVITY QUOTAS AND FEAR OF TERMINATION AND OR
RETALIATION. >> LASTLY, ONE SHARE THAT THEY
CANNOT FEASIBLY PROVIDE CLIENTS THE CARE THEY NEED OUTSIDE OF
THEIR APPOINTMENT TIME BECAUSE THEY STRUGGLE WITH THE REALITY
THAT THEIR CLIENTS MAY NOT BE SEEN FOR ANOTHER MONTH AS THEIR
SCHEDULE IS CONSTANTLY FILLED REGARDLESS OF THE APPROPRIATE
OR ACUITY OF THE SYMPTOMS. WHILE INCREASING APPOINTMENT
VALUES MAY APPEAR EFFICIENT, REDUCE PROTECTIVE TIME FOR
PATIENT CARE SUPPORT OUTSIDE OF APPOINTMENTS LIMITS CLINICIANS
ABILITIES TO PROVIDE THOUGHTFUL, COORDINATED
AND COMPREHENSIVE CARE. FINALLY, WE ARE DEEPLY
CONCERNED ABOUT KAISER PERMANENTE'S INCREASING
RELIANCE ON SUBCONTRACTED BEHAVIORAL HEALTH PROVIDERS
THROUGH DIGITAL PLATFORM SUCH AS GROWTH THERAPY, HEADWAY
IN OCD, OPEN MIND RULER SOUNDER MINE AND UPLIFT.
>> OUR MEMBERS HAVE SHARED THAT WHEN A PATIENT'S REGULAR
CLINICIAN IS TEMPORARILY UNAVAILABLE THEY ARE OFTEN
REDIRECTED TO AN OUTSIDE PROVIDER INSTEAD OF RETURNING
TO THEIR ESTABLISHED THERAPIES. >> THESE DISRUPTIONS CAN MAKE
IT HARDER FOR PATIENTS TO MAINTAIN CONSISTENT CARE
AND REBUILD TRUST WITH THEIR NEW PROVIDER WHICH IS
ESPECIALLY CHALLENGING AND BEHAVIORAL HEALTH WHERE THE
THERAPEUTIC RELATIONSHIP IS CENTRAL TO TREATMENT.
>> THIS IS ESPECIALLY CONCERNING AS KAISER HAS LONG
PROMOTED A INTEGRATED MODEL OF CARE WHERE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
PROVIDERS WORK TOGETHER ACROSS DISCIPLINES TO SUPPORT
PATIENTS. >> HOWEVER OUR SOCIAL WORKERS
HAVE SHARED CONCERNS THAT THEIR EXPERIENCE RECOMMENDATIONS
AND CLINICAL PERSPECTIVES ARE NOT BEING MEANINGFULLY
CONSIDERED WHEN DECISIONS ARE MADE ABOUT HOW CARE IS
DELIVERED. >> THEY DESCRIBE SITUATIONS
WHERE THEY ARE DIRECTED TO FOLLOW WORKFLOWS, TREATMENT
TIMELINES, REFERRAL PROCESSES THAT DO NOT ALIGN WITH THEIR
PROFESSIONAL JUDGMENT INCLUDING PRESSURE TO END TREATMENT
BEFORE PATIENTS WERE READY. KEEP PATIENTS IN PROGRAMS THAT
DID NOT FULLY MEET THEIR NEEDS OR DELAY REFERRAL FOR HIGHER
LEVEL OF CARE EVEN WHEN NEEDED. >> THESE EXPERIENCES HIGHLIGHT
WHY IT IS IMPORTANT THAT SOCIAL WORKERS HAVE A MEANINGFUL VOICE
IN SHAPING THE SYSTEMS AND POLICIES THAT DIRECTLY
IMPACT PATIENT CARE. PATIENTS DESERVE TIMELY ACCESS
TO LICENSED CLINICIANS AND PROVIDERS DESERVE THE TIME
NECESSARY TO DELIVER ETHICAL AND EFFECTIVE CARE
AND TECHNOLOGY SHOULD ENHANCE HEALTH CARE RATHER THAN REPLACE
THE EXPERTISE AND HUMAN CONNECTION.
FOR ALL THESE REASONS THE NSW CALIFORNIA URGES KAISER
PERMANENTE TO WITHDRAW ITS TERRIBLE THREE CONTRACT
PROPOSALS AND REALIGN THEIR PRACTICES WITH ETHICAL CARE BY
INVESTING IN LICENSED BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
PROFESSIONALS, PRESERVING INTEGRATED CARE, PROTECTING
CLINICIANS ABILITY TO PROVIDE QUALITY CARE AND ENSURING THAT
TECHNOLOGY IS IMPLEMENTED IN WAYS THAT ADVANCE EQUITY
RATHER THAN DEEPENING EXISTING DISPARITIES.
WE ASK THAT YOU JOIN A JOIN US IN THIS CALL UPON KAISER AND WE
THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME
. CAN YOU DO PERCENT REVIEW WHERE
THE NOTES ARE ON THE SIDE? OKAY GREAT.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR YOUR
INTEREST IN THESE ISSUES. I'M HERE TO TALK ABOUT THEM
FROM THE STANDPOINT OF THE EVIDENCE BASE OF HOW AND WHY
PSYCHOTHERAPY WORKS AND TO SHARE SOME RESEARCH FINDINGS
THAT ARE RELEVANT TO THE KAISER PROPOSAL.
>> OKAY. THERE WE GO.
I'M A LICENSED CLINICAL PSYCHOLOGIST.
I'M IN PRIVATE PRACTICE IN CHICAGO.
I'M ALSO THE CHAIR AND CO-FOUNDER OF PSYCHOTHERAPY
ACTION NETWORK, A NONPROFIT THAT ADVOCATES FOR THE PUBLIC'S
ACCESS TO CARE AND ALSO FOR CLINICIANS AND THE CLINICAL
STANDARDS NEEDED TO PROVIDE THAT CARE.
WE CONDUCT A LOT OF OUR OWN RESEARCH AND WE PRODUCED A LOT
OF PUBLICATIONS FROM WHITE PAPERS TO ARTICLES TO A BOOK
ADVANCING PSYCHOTHERAPY FOR THE NEXT GENERATION AND FOUNDED
IN 2017. WE HAVE GROWN SUBSTANTIAL
REALLY SINCE THEN. I'M SORRY WHICH IS TRUE.
>> OKAY. OKAY.
GOTCHA. THANKS.
OKAY. SO WHAT MAKES PSYCHOTHERAPY
EFFECTIVE? IT'S THE RELATIONSHIP YOU'VE
HEARD A LOT ABOUT THE ALLIANCE BETWEEN THE THERAPIST AND THE
PATIENT. >> THIS HAS BEEN STUDIED FOR
DECADES IN MANY DIFFERENT FORMS OF RESEARCH AND THE SAME
CONCLUSION IS REACHED TIME AND TIME AGAIN.
>> THIS MEANS THE THERAPIST MUST BE ABLE TO ASSESS, BUILD,
MAINTAIN AND ADAPT THAT ALLIANCE WITH EACH INDIVIDUAL
PATIENT OVER TIME. WHEN YOU MESS WITH THE
ALLIANCE, YOU MESS WITH WHAT MAKES THERAPY WORK AND YOU MESS
WITH WHAT MAKES THERAPY THERAPY.
YEAH. >> EFFECTIVE TREATMENTS MUST
ALSO BE INDIVIDUAL LIVES NOT STANDARDIZED FOR EACH PATIENT
AND THEY MUST BE OF SUFFICIENT DEPTH AND DURATION TO ENSURE
RECOVERY. EACH PERSON IS UNIQUE IN TERMS
OF MANY FACTORS AS THEIR DIAGNOSIS, THEIR COMPLEXITY,
THEIR PERSONALITY, COEXISTING ISSUES, TRAUMA HISTORY,
RESOURCES, IDENTITIES AND MORE. AND THE CARE MUST BE
INDIVIDUALIZED TO THEM. HELPING PEOPLE WITH ISSUES LIKE
TRAUMA ADDICTION, ABUSE, RELATIONSHIP STRESSORS IT
DOESN'T WORK LIKE AN ANTIBIOTIC DOES WHERE IT'S THE SAME
TREATMENT FOR EVERYBODY. WHEN IT COMES TO MENTAL HEALTH
. DIFFERENT PEOPLE NEED DIFFERENT
APPROACHES AND DIFFERENT MODELS OF CARE.
>> EVIDENCE BASED STANDARDS OF CARE SHOW THIS AS WELL.
WE HAVE TO TREAT UNDERLYING AND CHRONIC CONDITIONS.
AND WHEN WE TALK ABOUT DEPTH, WE'RE TALKING ABOUT GETTING
UNDERNEATH THOSE SUPERFICIAL SYMPTOMS.
AND WHEN WE TALK ABOUT DURATIONS, WE'RE TALKING ABOUT
FOR MANY PEOPLE 40, 50 OR 75 SESSIONS OF CARE.
THIS IS THE STANDARD OF CARE. >> SO KAISER'S FIRST PROPOSAL
IS TO HAVE SOLE DISCRETION OVER THE MODEL OF CARE.
>> THIS DIRECTLY INTERFERES WITH WHAT WE'VE JUST DISCUSSED
ABOUT HOW AND WHY THERAPY WORKS.
THIS IS MESSING WITH THE ALLIANCE MANDATING A SINGLE
STANDARDIZED MODEL OF CARE. IT CONTRADICTS THE EVIDENCE
BASE AND THE IMPORTANCE OF THE THERAPIST TO ASSESS, TREAT
AND ADAPT TO EACH PATIENT INDIVIDUALLY.
ONE SIZE FITS ALL WORKS FOR NO ONE.
WITH THIS PROPOSAL I WOULD PREDICT THAT OUTCOMES WILL
WORSEN AND PEOPLE WILL NOT FEEL HELPED OR UNDERSTOOD AND THEY
WILL DROP OUT OF CARE. >> SECONDLY, KAISER WANTS
FLEXIBILITY OVER SUBSTITUTING THE WORK OF LICENSED CLINICIANS
WITH AI AND A REFUSAL TO MAINTAIN THE LANGUAGE THEY
AGREED TO IN SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA.
THIS IS VERY SERIOUS. THIS WON'T BODE WELL FOR MENTAL
HEALTH OUTCOMES EITHER. IT'S REALLY BEST TO THINK OF
A.I. MENTAL HEALTH TOOLS AS SELF-HELP.
THAT'S WHERE THEY ARE TODAY. THERE ARE SELF-HELP INTERACTIVE
GUIDES, INTERACTIVE JOURNALS. THEY ARE NOT AN EQUIVALENT LET
ALONE A REPLACEMENT FOR PSYCHOTHERAPY BY ANY MEANS.
SO USING MORE A.I. MEANS GIVING PEOPLE SELF-HELP TOOLS.
>> THE SAFETY RISKS ARE VERY HIGH.
I'M SURE YOU'VE ALL HEARD IN THE PRESS TRAGIC CASES OF
PEOPLE DYING BY FOLLOWING THE INSTRUCTIONS OF A.I. CHAT BOTS
AND THE BIASES AND STIGMATIZED INFORMATION THAT'S INHERENT
IN THE LARGE LANGUAGE MODELS. NO LONG TERM STUDIES EXIST TO
SHOW WHETHER AI ENABLED TREATMENTS EVEN WORK.
AND SEVERAL STATES INCLUDING MINE ILLINOIS HAVE ALREADY
RESTRICTED AI FOR THESE REASONS TO A SUPPORT ROLE ONLY WHICH IS
WHERE I THINK IT NEEDS TO BE. AND THESE TOOLS ALSO NEED TO BE
REGULATED BY THE GOVERNMENT, BY THE FDA.
JUST LIKE ANY OTHER MEDICAL INTERVENTION I'M NOT GOING TO
GO THROUGH ALL OF THESE BUT I JUST WANT TO SHOW THIS SLIDE
THE RISKS OF TRYING TO REPLACE PSYCHOTHERAPY WITH AI.
THE LIST IS LONG AND THERE'S A LOT OF SERIOUS ITEMS ON THIS ON
THIS LIST. >> AS FAR AS OUTSOURCING
WITHOUT RESTRICTION, KAISER WANTS THE FLEXIBILITY TO
OUTSOURCE PSYCHOTHERAPY TO OUTSIDE PROVIDERS WHICH IS VERY
CONCERNING IN TERMS OF THAT THERAPEUTIC ALLIANCE AS WELL AS
CLINICIAN AUTONOMY AND JOB SATISFACTION SENDING PATIENTS
TO OTHER CLINICIANS DIRECTLY SEVERS THE ALLIANCE.
THIS WILL COMPROMISE TREATMENT OUTCOMES TO SATISFY PATIENTS
DISSATISFIED THERAPISTS AND INCREASE PATIENT DROPOUT
RATES. THIS IS MESSING WITH THE
ALLIANCE. WELL THIS MAY SAVE KAISER MONEY
IN THE SHORT TERM. IT'S A VERY COSTLY LONG TERM
STRATEGY. WHEN PEOPLE GET EFFECTIVE
PSYCHOTHERAPY THEY ACTUALLY HAVE FEWER ER CRISES AND ER
VISITS, LOWER HOSPITALIZATIONS AND ACTUALLY LOWER OVERALL
MEDICAL SPENDING. THEY TAKE BETTER CARE OF THEIR
MENTAL AND PHYSICAL HEALTH. THE ENTITIES THAT KAISER WANTS
TO OUTSOURCE TO ARE PARTICULARLY PROBLEMATIC.
THERE'S ALREADY RESEARCH AND STUDIES OUT THERE SHOWING
THAT THESE PLATFORM DOES HAVE SIGNIFICANT PROBLEMS IN A
VARIETY OF AREAS FROM TREATMENT EFFICACY TO THERAPIES,
SATISFACTION AND CONFIDENCE IN THE PLATFORMS PATIENT
PRIVACY, TRANSPARENCY AND MORE .
>> HERE'S A BIT MORE DETAIL ON THESE PROBLEMS.
THIS IS FROM A RESEARCH STUDY THAT WE CONDUCTED AND PUBLISHED
LAST YEAR ON THESE PLATFORMS. PRIVACY PROBLEMS THESE
COMPANIES DON'T ADEQUATE PROVIDE PROTECT PATIENT
INFORMATION. THIS IS THE FOUNDATION OF CARE.
THEIR INVESTORS ARE BIG TECH FIRMS AND THEY OUTSOURCE TO AI
COMPANIES AND THERE'S A LOT OF DATA SHARING AND AI TRAINING
GOING ON. LACK OF TRANSPARENCY REGARDING
REALLY BASIC THINGS SUCH AS WHO OWNS THESE COMPANIES?
WHO ARE THE MAJOR INVESTORS? HOW ARE THERAPISTS EVEN PAID?
THESE ARE QUESTIONS THAT THERAPISTS WHO USE THESE
PLATFORMS CURRENTLY DO NOT KNOW THE ANSWER TO.
AND THERE ARE A SERIES OF POLICIES THAT MANY OF THESE
PLATFORMS HAVE WHICH REALLY ARE ADDING UP TO TRYING TO REPLACE
ACTUAL PSYCHOTHERAPY WITH MERE CRISIS MANAGEMENT.
>> REGARDING KAISER'S DESIRE TO NO LONGER PROTECT THE FULL
MEANING OF CLINICAL CARE. CLINICAL TIME INCLUDES NOT JUST
THE FACE TO FACE MEETING WITH THE PATIENT.
THERE'S A LOT OF CONSULTATION, COLLABORATION AND COORDINATION
WITH OTHER THERAPISTS. IF YOU'RE SEEING A COUPLE OR A
FAMILY YOU HAVE TO INTERACT WITH THE OTHER THERAPIST.
>> SEEING THE OTHER PART OF THE COUPLE, THE PARENTS, THE KIDS
PSYCHIATRISTS THERE MAY BE MEDICAL DOCTORS INVOLVED IF
THERE ARE SERIOUS MEDICAL ISSUES GOING ON.
THESE TESTS ARE JUST PART OF CARE AND THEY NEED TO AND THEY
TAKE TIME. >> IF NEW INTAKES ARE SCHEDULED
INTO THIS BLOCK OF TIME, THIS IS ACTUALLY QUITE BAD FOR THOSE
NEW PATIENTS BECAUSE THEY'RE UNLIKELY TO BE SEEN AGAIN
ANYTIME SOON AND IT'S ALSO NOT GOOD FOR KAISER.
THEY WILL BE CREATING A SYSTEM THAT JUST GIVES AN ILLUSION OF
ACCESS WITHOUT ANY REAL MEANINGFUL ACCESS TO CARE FOR
THERAPIES AS HAVING BASIC AUTONOMY OVER THEIR OWN
SCHEDULE IS A DOCUMENTED PROTECTIVE FACTOR AGAINST
BURNOUT. BURNOUT IS A DIRECT PRECURSOR
OF TURNOVER AND TURNOVER AS YOU KNOW WOULD BE EXCEEDINGLY
EXPENSIVE FOR KAISER. IT'S ALSO REALLY COSTLY FOR
PATIENTS WHEN THEIR THERAPIST LEAVES.
MOST OF THEM DROP OUT OF TREATMENT ALTOGETHER.
>> KAISER'S PROPOSALS TAKEN TOGETHER WILL UNDERMINE THE
VERY FACTORS THAT MAKE PSYCHOTHERAPY EFFECTIVE
AND EVEN POSSIBLE AND THERE WILL BE NEGATIVE RESULTS
AND HIGH COSTS TO CLINICIANS, TO PATIENTS AND EVEN TO KAISER
ITSELF. >> I STRONGLY URGE THE BOARD TO
REJECT THE KAISER PROPOSALS AND SUPPORT CLINICIANS AND THE
THERAPEUTIC ALLIANCE AND WHAT WE KNOW MAKES FOR EFFECTIVE
CARE. IF YOU SAID WE'RE GOING TO
ASSESS AND DIAGNOSE BY A ROBOT AND THEN GIVE THE SAME
TREATMENT TO EVERYONE REGARDLESS OF HOW THEY RESPOND
TO IT OVER TIME AND MESS WITH THE VERY THING THAT MAKES
THERAPY EFFECTIVE. YOU KNOW THIS SOUNDS LIKE A
TERRIBLE IDEA. SO PLEASE I URGE YOU TO STAND
UP FOR THE PRINCIPLES OF EFFECTIVE EVIDENCE BASED CARE
AND WHAT WE KNOW AS FAR AS WHAT WORKS FOR CLINICIANS
AND PATIENTS. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> THANK YOU, DR. MICHAELS. AND LET'S HAVE OUR LAST
PRESENTER SYDNEY SIMPSON, REGISTERED NURSE.
>> SHE'S THE SAN FRANCISCO MEMBER OF SYDNEY.
>> GOOD EVENING, SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS SYDNEY SIMPSON.
I'M A MEMBER OF THE CALIFORNIA NURSES ASSOCIATION.
I WORKED AS A REGISTERED NURSE AT KAISER SAN FRANCISCO
AND INTERVENTIONAL RADIOLOGY. MY SIBLINGS FROM ANY AGE W HAVE
HIGHLIGHTED THE DANGERS OF UNREGULATED AI IN OUR HEALTH
CARE SYSTEM. I JUST WANT TO KIND OF BUILD ON
THAT AND TALK ABOUT IT FROM OUR PERSPECTIVE THE NURSE
PERSPECTIVE AND HOW IT ALL SORT OF FITS TOGETHER INTO A REALLY
DANGEROUS PATTERN OF DECISIONS BEING MADE BY KAISER.
>> THAT BLATANTLY PRIORITIZES PROFITS OVER PATIENT SAFETY
AND QUALITY OF CARE. >> SINCE THE TRUMP INAUGURATION
LAST YEAR WE'VE SEEN KAISER TAKE AN INCREASINGLY HOSTILE
APPROACH TOWARDS THEIR UNIONIZED NURSES.
KAISER HAS COMMITTED LARGE SCALE WAGE THEFT AGAINST NURSES
AND IS REFUSING TO REMIT OWED RETROACTIVE PAYMENTS.
KAISER IN SAN FRANCISCO AND BEYOND IS CUTTING MANY
VACANT ARE RN AND NURSE PRACTITIONER POSITIONS LEAVING
OUR DEPARTMENTS DANGEROUSLY UNDERSTAFFED.
>> HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO KAISER HAS ADMINISTERED CUTS TO OUR
IN STAFFING AND PRIMARY CARE AND THE EMERGENCY DEPARTMENT
WHICH OF COURSE ARE THE MAIN DEPARTMENTS BY WHICH PATIENTS
ACCESS CARE. THESE CUTS HAVE RESULTED
IN INCREASED DELAYS IN CARE. I HAVE PERSONALLY SEEN KAISER
PATIENTS INCLUDING MY OWN COWORKERS STRUGGLE TO ACCESS
MEDICALLY NECESSARY CARE AND ACTUALLY LEAVE THE CITY OR
EVEN THE STATE TO ACCESS THAT CARE.
>> WHILE KAISER HAS FULLY LAUNCHED ITS NEW VIRTUAL CENTER
PROGRAM IN WHICH A REMOTE MONITORED IPAD IS RESPONSIBLE
FOR PREVENTING PATIENT FALLS ON THE INPATIENT SIDE, THE KAISER
SAN FRANCISCO EMERGENCY DEPARTMENT HAS SEEN A TRULY
SHOCKING INCREASE IN PATIENT FALLS.
NURSES HAVE SUBMITTED PETITIONS AND WRITTEN LETTERS TO KAISER
ADMINISTRATORS REQUESTING PLANS OF CORRECTIVE ACTION TO ADDRESS
THE CUTS TO STAFFING AND THE SUBSEQUENT IMPACTS TO PATIENT
SAFETY. KAISER REFUSES TO DISCLOSE THIS
INFORMATION. ADDITIONALLY, KAISER'S VAST
INVESTMENT IN UNTESTED AI SIGNALS AN EFFORT TO DIVERT
FUNDING FROM IN-PERSON CAREGIVERS TO NEW UNTESTED
TECHNOLOGIES. >> NURSES ARE NOT AGAINST
SCIENTIFIC OR TECHNOLOGICAL ADVANCEMENT BUT WE WILL NOT
ACCEPT ALGORITHMS REPLACING EXPERTISE, EXPERIENCE HOLISTIC
AND HANDS ON APPROACHES THAT WE BRING TO PATIENT CARE.
IF IT'S WHAT YOU WOULD DEMAND FOR YOUR FAMILY THAT IS ALL
THAT IS ALL WE ARE DEMANDING FOR ALL OF OUR PATIENTS.
KAISER IS USING ALGORITHMIC SYSTEMS TO QUANTIFY NURSING
WORKLOADS AND PATIENT ACUITY LEVELS WHICH INCLUDES SHIFTS.
STAFFING DECISIONS ARE INTO PATIENT ASSIGNMENTS.
THIS OFTEN RESULTS IN INAPPROPRIATE NURSE TO
PATIENT RATIOS AND UNPREDICTABLE SCHEDULING.
INSTEAD, PATIENT ACUITY MEASUREMENT SHOULD BE BASED ON
AN RN'S CLINICAL JUDGMENT AND A HANDS ON ASSESSMENT.
>> KAISER'S ALSO IMPLEMENTED A TECHNOLOGY THAT THEY IRONICALLY
CALLED THE CASTE SYSTEM. AND YES, THAT IS REALLY THE
NAME OF THIS TECHNOLOGY THAT THE TEXT SCANS A PATIENT'S
CHART AND DETERMINES HOW MUCH TIME THE PATIENT WILL RECEIVE
FOR THEIR PRE SURGICAL SCREENING APPOINTMENT
AND WHETHER THEY WILL HAVE ACCESS TO A DOCTOR OR NURSE
PRACTITIONER. WE HAVE ASKED KAISER REPEATEDLY
WHAT'S SPECIFIC INFORMATION? THE CASTE SYSTEM ROBOT USES TO
DETERMINE AND RATION THAT CARE. >> KAISER REFUSES TO DISCLOSE
THIS INFORMATION. CNA REPRESENTED NURSE
PRACTITIONERS DISCOVERED THAT LANGUAGE TRANSLATION NEEDS OF A
PATIENT ARE NOT FACTORED INTO THE APPOINTMENT TIME OF THE
CASTE SYSTEM. THIS IS FUNDAMENTALLY
DISCRIMINATORY AS TRANSLATION OBVIOUSLY TAKES TIME.
WITHOUT INCREASING THE LENGTH OF APPOINTMENT TIMES FOR
PATIENTS WITH TRANSLATION NEEDS, KAISER THEREFORE IS
PROVIDING SUCH PATIENTS WITH LESS TIME IN THEIR PRE SURGICAL
SCREENING APPOINTMENTS THAN THAT AFFORDED TO PATIENTS
WITHOUT TRANSLATION NEEDS. >> KAISER IS ALSO ACCELERATED
THE OUTSOURCING OF OUR PATIENTS CARE TO THIRD PARTY FACILITIES
AND ENTITIES THAT DO NOT HAVE THE SAME OVERSIGHT AND UNION
PROTECTIONS KAISER IS PUSHING. ACUTE CARE PATIENTS OUT OF THE
HOSPITAL AND INTO THE HOME THROUGH THEIR ADVANCED CARE AT
HOME INITIATIVE. THIS PROGRAM PLACES CAMERAS
IN THE HOMES OF ACUTE CARE PATIENTS AND PLACES TO REPLACES
24 HOUR NURSING CARE WITH 24 HOUR SURVEILLANCE.
KAISER HAS CONTRACTED NONUNION NURSES TO SURVEIL THESE
PATIENTS FROM REMOTE AND UNDISCLOSED LOCATIONS.
>> KAISER IS RELIEVED OF THE OBLIGATION OF CLEANING
AND CARING FOR AND COMFORTING THESE PATIENTS AND THIS LABOR
NOW FALLS SOLELY ON TO THE PATIENT'S FAMILY MEMBERS.
>> >> OUR NURSES ARE REPORTING THAT MANY OF THE PATIENTS
PLACED IN THE ADVANCED CARE AT HOME PROGRAM WE CALL THIS CARE
ALL ALONE. INSTEAD OF ADVANCED CARE AT
HOME, OUR NURSES ARE REPORTING THAT MANY OF THE PATIENTS
PLACED IN THE ADVANCED CARE AT HOME PROGRAM ARE BEING
READMITTED TO THE HOSPITAL DUE TO PREMATURE DISCHARGE
AND FRACTURED CONTINUITY OF CARE.
IN SAN FRANCISCO MANY SURGICAL PATIENTS UNDER KAISER ARE SENT
TO THE S.F. SURGERY CENTER WHICH IS ADORNED WITH KAISER
PERMANENTE SIGNAGE. BUT IT IS IN FACT A DISTINCT
AND VERY SEPARATE ENTITY FROM KAISER AND THE NURSES WORKING
THERE HAVE NO UNION PROTECTIONS.
NURSES HAVE REQUESTED INFORMATION ON THE POLICIES
AND PROCEDURES THE INFECTION CONTROL PROTOCOLS AND THE
PATIENT INCLUSION AND EXCLUSION CRITERIA FOR THE S.F. SURGERY
CENTER. KAISER REFUSES TO DISCLOSE THIS
INFORMATION. CNN HAS RECEIVED REPORTS FROM
NURSES WORKING AT THE S.F. SURGERY CENTER THAT WITHOUT
UNION PROTECTION THERE FEAR FEARFUL TO SPEAK UP
AND ADVOCATE FOR PATIENT SAFETY WITH THEIR MULTIBILLION DOLLAR
PROFIT, KAISER COULD EASILY EXPAND STAFFING TO EXTEND THE
HOURS OF BOTH INPATIENT AND OUTPATIENT OPERATING ROOMS
TO MEET THE SURGICAL NEEDS OF OUR PATIENTS.
BUT KAISER HAS REFUSED SUCH PROPOSALS AND CONTINUES TO
CONTRACT OUT CARE AND OPERATIONS.
>> SO IN CLOSING WE CALL ON KAISER TO DO BETTER AND TURN
THEIR RHETORICAL CLAIMS INTO ACTION.
WITH SO MANY CITY WORKERS AND S.F. RESIDENTS DEPENDENT ON
KAISER'S CARE, WE APPRECIATE THIS BOARD WORKING TO ENSURE
THAT THE MILLIONS OF DOLLARS OF PUBLIC FUNDS THAT ARE REMITTED
TO KAISER ANNUALLY ARE BEING SPENT BACK INTO THE CARE OF
CITY WORKERS AND S.F. RESIDENTS .
>> KAISER CAN DEMONSTRATE THEIR COMMITMENT TO IMPROVING PATIENT
CARE BY ONE REPLACE VACATED POSITIONS TO INCREASE STAFFING
AND PATIENT CARE CAPACITIES. THREE INSOURCE OUTSOURCED WORK.
>> AND FOUR PROVIDE TRANSPARENCY AND OVERSIGHT OF
ALL NEW TECHNOLOGIES. >> OUR EXPERIENCE OF KAISER IS
INCREASINGLY BLATANT DISREGARD FOR ACCEPTED STANDARDS OF CARE.
IT'S INAPPROPRIATE AT DEPLOYMENT OF AI AND OTHER TECH
IN PLACE OF HUMAN HEALTH CARE PROFESSIONALS AND ITS GROWING
AGGRESSION TOWARDS ITS UNIONIZED WORKFORCE IS PARALLEL
TO THAT EXPERIENCED BY UAW MEMBERS.
SIENNA SHARES NH W'S ASSESSMENT OF THE NEGATIVE EFFECTS OF
KAISER'S TERRIBLE THREE BARGAINING DEMANDS AND WE JOIN
IN W IN CALLING ON KAISER TO WITHDRAW THEM.
WE ASKED THAT S.F. BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SUPPORT BOTH UNIONS
IN PROTECTING PATIENTS FROM THESE ATTACKS.
NURSES KNOW THAT KAISER CAN SERVE OUR CITY BETTER AND STOP
USING THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AS A MEANS TO
COLLECT REVENUE FOR THEIR PRIVATE INVESTMENT STRATEGIES.
RATHER, THEY NEED TO INVEST THEIR MULTIBILLION DOLLAR
PROFITS MUCH OF IT COLLECTED HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO BACK INTO
THE CARE OF OUR COMMUNITIES. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, SIDNEY. >> NOW LET'S GO TO QUESTIONS.
MY FIRST ROUND OF QUESTIONS WILL GO TO MR. IGER.
>> WOULD YOU COME BACK TO THE PODIUM, PLEASE?
>> MR. IGER KAISER HAS A LONG BEEN KNOWN AS A LABOR FOR ANY
HEALTH CARE EMPLOYER AND TOWARDS ITS HISTORY OF
LABOR MANAGEMENT PARTNERSHIP. >> WHEN AND HOW DID THIS GO
WRONG IN THE SPECIFIC CASE OF BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE MOSTLY
MOST RECENTLY. >> HOW CAN IT BE THAT THE MODEL
OF CARE COMMITTEES WERE ABANDONED AND THE THERAPISTS
GUARANTEED A TIME FOR PATIENT CARE SUPPORT WAS ALSO CUT IT
AFTER KAISER HAD AGREED TO THEM AS PART OF THE 2022 STRIKE
SETTLEMENT. >> TELL US WHAT HAPPENED.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FOR THE QUESTION.
I WISH THAT I COULD GIVE YOU A SATISFYING ANSWER.
I DON'T KNOW WHY KAISER HAS CHANGED HIS ATTITUDE TOWARDS
ITS EMPLOYEES. IF THEY WERE HERE MAYBE THEY
WOULD TELL US BUT THEY DECLINED TO COME.
BUT YOU HEARD JUST FROM THE REPRESENTATIVE FROM THE
CALIFORNIA NURSES ASSOCIATION THAT THEY HAVE BEEN TAKING AN
INCREASINGLY ANTI-UNION YEN ATTITUDE TOWARD THEIR EMPLOYEES
AND THE UNIONS THAT THEIR EMPLOYEES HAVE CHOSEN TO
REPRESENT THEM. >> WE AS I MENTIONED IN MY
TESTIMONY WE THOUGHT THAT THE CONTRACT IN NORTHERN CALIFORNIA
IN 2022 WAS A SIGN THAT THINGS WERE GOING TO IMPROVE.
BUT IT DIDN'T LAST LONG. VERY SHORTLY AFTER THAT, KAISER
CHANGED THE WAY IT STARTED TO TREAT ITS EMPLOYEES.
DURING THIS ROUND OF NEGOTIATIONS AS I SAID IN MY
TESTIMONY, THEY HAVE GONE BACK ON THEIR COMMITMENT TO FUND THE
RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE MODEL OF CARE COMMITTEES.
AND I THINK THAT IF YOU LOOK AT THE MODEL OF CARE AND THE
PATIENT CARE SUPPORT TIME ISSUE, KAISER'S PROPOSALS ARE
REALLY JUST ABOUT SQUEEZING MORE APPOINTMENTS INTO
PROVIDERS OF SCHEDULES. SO THAT THEY CAN SEE MORE
PATIENTS WITH FEWER STAFF AND REDUCE THEIR NEED TO
SUBCONTRACT. THEY RECENTLY TOLD PROVIDERS
IN THE NORTH VALLEY THAT THEY CAN ONLY HIRE MORE STAFF IF
EXISTING PROVIDERS ARE MORE PRODUCTIVE AND DISCHARGE
PATIENTS FASTER. SO I THINK THAT THE CHANGE
IN BEHAVIOR THAT YOU'RE NOTICING AND THAT WE'RE SEEING
IS REALLY ABOUT KAISER BEGINNING TO BEHAVE MORE
AND MORE LIKE A FOR PROFIT TYPE OF ENTITY AND TRYING TO SQUEEZE
EMPLOYEES MORE TO MAXIMIZE REVENUE.
>> THANK YOU. IT'S REALLY CLEAR TO ME I THINK
AND AND I IN THIS CASE I THINK KAISER IS REALLY USING
SUBCONTRACTING AND TECHNOLOGY TO PAPER OVER ITS CARE, ITS
EFFICIENCIES RATHER THAN SPENDING TIME AND AMPLE
RESOURCES TO CONTINUE TO RECRUIT AND RETAIN ENOUGH
DIAPERS TO MEET PATIENTS NEEDS. >> CAN YOU ALSO ELABORATE ON
THE EXTENT TO WHICH KAISER CURRENTLY RELIES ON STAFF
THERAPISTS AS OPPOSED TO SUBCONTRACTORS WHO PROVIDE
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE AND ALSO HOW THE RAW NUMBERS AND THE
RATIO BETWEEN THEM HAVE SHIFTED RECENTLY?
>> YES. >> SINCE THE TEN WEEK STRIKE
IN 2022 TO ESTABLISH OUR CURRENT CONTRACT KAISER
ENROLLMENT IN NORTHERN CALIFORNIA HAS INCREASED
SLIGHTLY TO 4.6 MILLION ENROLLEES WHILE THE NUMBER OF
STAFF THERAPISTS HAS INCREASED VERY SLIGHTLY IF AT ALL.
DESPITE KAISER'S ACKNOWLEDGMENT AS PART OF ITS SETTLEMENT
AGREEMENT WITH THE STATE AND FEDERAL GOVERNMENT THAT IT
LACKS THE CAPACITY TO PROVIDE ACCESS TO CARE CONSISTENT WITH
THE TIMELY ACCESS REQUIREMENTS OF THE LAW.
>> THE MOST IMPORTANT FACT IS THIS SINCE THE PANDEMIC THE
NEED FOR BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE HAS RISEN DRAMATICALLY,
ESPECIALLY AMONG YOUTH. IN 2023, KAISER CEO GREGG ADAMS
ACKNOWLEDGED THAT 20% MORE PEOPLE CAME IN FOR BEHAVIORAL
HEALTH CARE THAN AT THE SAME POINT THE PRIOR YEAR.
SO WHAT WE'RE SEEING IS THAT ENROLLMENT IS BASICALLY STEADY.
THE NUMBER OF STAFF THERAPISTS IS BASICALLY STEADY BUT PATIENT
NEED FOR CARE HAS INCREASED SIGNIFICANTLY.
IN ORDER TO MEET THIS INCREASE IN REALLY DEMAND FOR CARE
WITHIN THE TIMEFRAMES PRESCRIBED BY LAW, KAISER IS
OUTSOURCING TREATMENT TO PLATFORM PROVIDERS
AND SUBSTITUTING TECHNOLOGY FOR HUMAN CARE.
IT'S STRETCHING ITS STAFF THERAPISTS TO SEE MORE PATIENTS
IN THE SAME AMOUNT OF TIME AND IT'S ALSO SIMPLY CONTINUING
TO VIOLATE THE REQUIREMENTS OF THE LAW AND FAILING TO MEET THE
INCREASE IN ITS ENROLLEES NEEDS.
HENCE THE MULTIPLE AND REPEATED SETTLEMENT AGREEMENTS AND FINES
. >> OKAY I'M FORTUNATELY KAISER
IS NOT HERE. >> THIS IS WILL BE A QUESTION
THAT I ALSO WOULD LOVE TO ASK KAISER.
SO YOU TOLD ME THAT YOU HAVE TOLD US NOT JUST MYSELF ABOUT
KAISER'S DEMAND FOR CONCESSIONS BUT WHAT IS AND YOU WHICH
DOUBLE AND YOU W PROPOSING IN NEGOTIATION AND WHAT HAS
BEEN KAISER'S RESPONSE TO YOUR PROPOSALS?
>> THANK YOU. YOU KNOW REALLY IN UAW MEMBERS
ARE NOT PROPOSING ANYTHING PATH BREAKING.
WE ARE OUR BARGAINING COMMITTEE HAS PROPOSED A MODEST FINANCIAL
INCREASES COMPLETELY IN LINE WITH WHAT KAISER HAS PROVIDED
TO THE UNION EMPLOYEES OF OTHER UNIONS.
YOU KNOW, IN RECENT NEGOTIATIONS.
AS MENTIONED, WE'VE PROPOSED LANGUAGE REGARDING A.I.
AND TECHNOLOGY THAT KAISER HAS AGREED TO IN OTHER PLACES BUT
IS REFUSING TO AGREE TO IN NORTHERN CALIFORNIA.
>> I THINK THERE'S ONE EXAMPLE THAT REALLY UNDERSCORES WHAT WE
SEE AS KAISER'S UNREASONABLENESS IN THESE
NEGOTIATIONS IN WHICH TO BE CLINICIANS HAVE REQUESTED A
MECHANISM TO CAP CASELOAD FOR PROVIDERS AND THIS IS SIMILAR
TO THE WAY THAT DOCTORS AT KAISER HAVE A CAP.
>> AND WHAT WE'VE PROPOSED WOULD ACCOMPLISH PRECISE WHAT
THE DEPARTMENT OF LABOR SETTLEMENT DIRECTED KAISER TO
DO WHICH IS ENSURE THAT PROVIDERS AREN'T GIVEN NEW
PATIENTS WHEN THEIR SCHEDULES ARE SO IMPACTED THAT THEY CAN'T
PROVIDE THEIR CURRENT PATIENTS THE ACCESS THAT THEY NEED THAT
MEETS THE LEGAL REQUIREMENTS FOR TIMELY CARE.
>> SO IN OTHER WORDS ANY W MEMBERS AT THE BARGAINING TABLE
HAVE PROPOSED A TRANSPARENT AND ACCOUNTABLE PROCESS FOR
ACCOMPLISHING WHAT KAISER IS REQUIRED TO DO PER THE TERMS OF
ITS SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT THAT IT AGREED TO AND SIGNED WITH
THE DEPARTMENT OF LABOR. BUT KAISER WON'T AGREE TO THAT
PROPOSAL AND HAS NOT GIVEN US A COUNTERPROPOSAL OF THEIR OWN.
AND SO I THINK YOU LOOK AT ALL OF THIS WHAT'S HAPPENING AT THE
BARGAINING TABLE AND WHAT'S BEEN TALKED ABOUT HERE TODAY
AND IT'S CLEAR THAT KAISER HAS ONE STANDARD FOR MEDICAL HEALTH
CARE AND A LESSER STANDARD FOR BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE.
>> OUR MEMBERS ARE TRYING TO REBALANCE THAT.
>> AND KAISER IS REFUSING THANK YOU FOR A RESPONSE.
I WOULD LIKE TO CALL UP TOKYO FLU CLINICIAN WHO MR. IF KAISER
WERE TO WORK IN EARNEST WOULD YOU AND OTHER STAFF THERAPISTS
IN ESTABLISHING AND IMPLEMENTING ITS MODEL OF
CARE? >> WHAT DO YOU THINK THE RESULT
WOULD BE? I THINK PATIENTS WOULD GET MUCH
BETTER CARE. >> I MEAN THE WHOLE GOAL RIGHT
IS TO HAVE MORE CLINICIANS PROVIDING CARE SO THERE WOULD
BE A LOT LESS PRESSURE FOR US TO GRADUATE PATIENTS FROM
TREATMENTS BEFORE THEY'RE EVEN READY AND THEN WE'LL HAVE MORE
REASONABLE CASELOADS FOR CLINICIANS FOR US.
SO THEN WE CAN TRULY FOCUS ON PROVIDING THAT COMPREHENSIVE
TREATMENT THAT THAT KAISER SO TOUTS.
RIGHT. AND I THINK ESPECIALLY WITH
THERAPY AND TREATMENT IT'S REALLY IMPORTANT TO UNDERSTAND
THAT IT'S NOT IT'S NOT ALWAYS A TIME A TIME LOOM TO PROCESS
WHICH IS WHAT KAISER WANTS US TO THINK, RIGHT?
BECAUSE I WANT FOLKS TO THINK SO.
SO IN PRESENTATIONS REQUIRE CHRONIC CARE AND TREATMENT.
AND OFTENTIMES PATIENTS COME TO US AFTER WAITING SO LONG FOR
CARE AND ARE FRUSTRATED WITH US WHEN WE CAN ONLY SEE THEM EVERY
3 TO 4 WEEKS AT BEST AND THEN THEY GIVE UP ON TREATMENT
AND THERAPY ALTOGETHER SO THEY JUST QUIT.
WE'RE WE ARE COMPLETELY LETTING DOWN OUR COMMUNITIES OR
PATIENTS AND PEOPLE DON'T REALIZE THAT CLINICIANS AT
KAISER ARE OFTEN IN SUCH SORRY WE ARE WE ARE UNDER SUCH
INTENSE PRESSURE TO GRADUATE OUTPATIENTS WHEN REPORT HAS
HARDLY EVEN BEEN BUILT AND A LOT OF TRAUMAS AND OTHER THINGS
HAVEN'T EVEN BEGUN TO BE PROCESSED.
>> THANK YOU. AND AND I THINK WHAT YOU JUST
SHARE THAT IT'S REALLY SHORTCUTTING CLINICAL STANDARDS
AND IT'S VERY CONCERNING WHAT HAVE YOU AND YOUR COWORKERS
DONE TO PUSH BACK AGAINST THIS PRACTICES AND WHAT DOES KAISER
SAY WHEN YOU CONFRONT MANAGEMENT AND WHAT HELP HAVE
YOU GOTTEN FROM PROFESSIONAL BODIES THAT ESTABLISH GENERALLY
ACCEPTED STANDARDS OF CARE IN TERMS OF MANAGING MENT
SUPPORT IN ALL HONESTY I HAVEN'T GOTTEN VERY MUCH
MANAGEMENT SUPPORT AND THIS IS JUST MY OWN OPINION BECAUSE I
ONLY WORK FOR SAN FRANCISCO, KAISER AND MAYBE DIFFERENT
IN OTHER PLACES BUT IT REALLY FEELS LIKE IT'S PUSHING AGAINST
A BRICK WALL. WE'RE TRYING OUR BEST TO GET
PATIENTS IN WITHIN LIKE YOU KNOW ALLOTTED AMOUNT OF CARE
TIME, YOU KNOW, ACCORDING TO STATE LAW.
BUT OFTENTIMES WE ARE IN A WAY ENCOURAGED BY MANAGEMENT TO HOW
TO SEE TO IN A WAY SO WHEN OUR CLINICAL JUDGMENT AS THERAPISTS
DICTATES THAT A PATIENT BE SEEN SOONER THEN WE CAN ACTUALLY SEE
THEM AGAIN. THE PRESSURE FROM MANAGEMENT IS
THAT IT'S TO PLEASE REVISE HER JUDGMENT AND SAY IT'S
APPROPRIATE TO SEE THEM EVERY 3 TO 6 WEEKS SO THAT THE DELAY
WON'T VIOLATE STATE LAW. >> SO I WOULD SAY THAT IN TERMS
OF GETTING SUPPORT FROM MANAGEMENT, IT IS MORE OF A
PUSHBACK TO FOLLOW THEIR POLICIES, THEIR PROCEDURES
INSTEAD OF OUR CLINICAL PRACTICE, OUR ETHICS AND WHAT
WE SHOULD BELIEVE IN AND HOW YOU ACTUALLY DID THE PRACTICE
OF PUSHING LIKE BECAUSE WE HAVE THE FOLLOW THE LEGALITY OF LATE
THE MONTHS AND THEN YOU ACTUALLY PUSH A PATIENT AND SAY
THAT YOU KNOW IT'S OKAY TO SEE TO REVISIT AGAIN IN COUPLE OF
MONTHS LATER IT BUT IT'S VERY CONCERNING TO ME.
>> YES NO AND I WOULD SAY YOU KNOW, IT DEFINITELY VARIES FOR
ME AND MY OWN EXPERIENCE AND HOW I WORK WITH PATIENTS.
THAT IS SOMETHING I DEFINITELY DON'T SEE.
I TRY MY BEST TO FIT THEM IN AS SOON AS I CAN AND IN ALL
HONESTY TRANSPARENCY IS KEY HERE, RIGHT?
WE'RE ALL WORKING WITHIN A SYSTEM THAT IS HARD TO PUSH
BACK AND CHANGE AGAINST. >> YEAH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COURAGE. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. MY NEXT SET OF QUESTION IS FOR
DR. MICHAELS. DR. MICHAELS, BASED ON THE
TESTIMONY WE HAVE HEARD FROM AND YOUR MEMBERS, IT SEEMS LIKE
KAISER IS INCREASINGLY OUTSOURCING CLINICAL WORK TO
PRACTICE MANAGEMENT COMPANIES COMPANIES WHICH MOST PEOPLE
CALL INTERNAL INTERNET THERAPY PLATFORMS.
>> WHAT CONCERNS SHOULD WE HAVE ABOUT HOW THESE COMPANIES ARE
STRUCTURED IT AND HOW THEY MANAGE THE CLINICIANS WHOM THEY
USE AS INDEPENDENT CONTRACTORS ?
WELL, THANK YOU FOR THAT IMPORTANT QUESTION.
THESE COMPANIES THESE PLATFORMS ARE BACKED BY THREE LARGE
AND POWERFUL GROUPS. >> FIRST, PRIVATE EQUITY
AND VENTURE CAPITAL INVESTORS. SECOND BIG TECH COMPANIES
INCLUDING GOOGLE AND AMAZON. AND THIRD, THE MAJOR
TRADITIONAL INSURANCE COMPANIES.
YES, THEY ARE DIRECTLY INVOLVED AND ARE MAJOR INVESTORS IN IN
THESE PLATFORMS. SO THIS TRIO THEY SHARE A FOCUS
ON PROFITS AND THEY SHARE A FOCUS ON PURSUING GROWTH
AND COST CUTTING. WHAT THEY ALSO SHARE IS THAT
THEY DON'T NECESSARILY KNOW ALL THAT MUCH ABOUT PSYCHOLOGY OR
MENTAL HEALTH CARE. >> THEY'RE VERY CONCERNED
AND ORGANIZED AROUND HOW THEY CAN MAKE MONEY AND MAKE MONEY
FOR THEIR INVESTORS AND THEY ARE NOT CONCERNED OR ORGANIZED
AROUND WHAT MAKES FOR QUALITY CARE OR THE CONDITIONS NEEDED
FOR PATIENTS OR THERAPISTS TO PROVIDE THAT.
ALSO CLINICIANS WHO ARE CONNECTED TO THESE PLATFORMS
ARE 1099 CONTRACTORS. >> THIS IS AN UBER MODEL.
THE PLATFORMS HAVE A TREMENDOUS AMOUNT OF CONTROL OVER THE
POLICIES AND THINGS ACTUALLY THAT RIGHTLY SHOULD BE CLINICAL
DECISIONS. >> SO PLATFORMS ARE OBTAINING
CLINICAL DATA DIRECTLY FROM PATIENTS WITHOUT EVEN ASKING OR
INFORMING THERAPIES AS THEY'RE GOING AROUND THE THERAPIST TO
GET THIS DATA. >> THERE ARE ALSO PRESSURING
FOR EXAMPLE THERAPISTS AND DIFFERENT WAYS TO USE THEIR
AI SCRIBING AND DOCUMENTATION AND TOOLS AND THEY'RE
COLLECTING A MASSIVE AMOUNT OF DATA AND THIS INCLUDES
RECORDING AND RETAINING ENTIRE TRANSCRIPTS OF THERAPY SESSIONS
. SO YES, THEY WANT THE DATA
WHICH IS EXTREMELY VULNERABLE AND PRIVATE.
>> SO THEY ARE ON THE PATH TO TRAINING THEIR OWN CHAT BOTS
AND ALSO DEVELOPING CAPITATED PAYMENT MODELS THAT WILL
RADICALLY CHANGE THE VIABILITY OF MENTAL HEALTH PRACTICE.
SO MANY, MANY CONCERNS AND WE DOCUMENTED IT A LOT OF THIS
IN OUR RESEARCH REPORT ON THESE COMPANIES LAST YEAR.
>> THANK YOU, DOCTOR, MY MICHAEL AND ALSO MY NEXT
QUESTION IS WHAT ELEMENTS OF WHAT KAISER IS PROPOSING ARE
DIFFERENT FROM WHAT YOU HAVE SEEN FROM OTHER INSURERS
AND WHAT IMPACT DO YOU THINK THEY WOULD HAVE ON INDUSTRY?
>> WHY PRACTICES AFFECTING PATIENTS ACCESS TO AFFORDABLE
QUALITY CARE AND THE ABILITY OF CLINICIANS TO PROVIDE ITS
ETHICS PROVIDES CARE ETHICALLY AND SUSTAINABLY?
>> WELL INSURERS ARE NOT PROPOSING MODELS OF CARE.
FOR ONE, THEY ARE NOT MESSING WITH THE ALLIANCE DIRECTLY AS
AS KAISER WOULD BE AND THEIR PROPOSALS.
TRADITIONAL INSURERS ARE NOT MANDATING USAGES OF AI.
>> THEY ARE DOING OTHER THINGS WITH AI.
THEY'RE TRYING TO CREATE THEIR OWN AI MODELS AND PRODUCTS.
AETNA EVEN ANNOUNCED A SINGLE SESSION AI PRODUCT FOR 2027
WHICH IS EXTREMELY PROBLEMATIC. BUT THEY ARE NOT SHOWING THE
SAME KINDS OF INTENT TO WITH WHAT KAISER'S WANTING TO DO
WITH SUBSTITUTING OR USING AI IN THOSE WAYS.
>> BUT YOU KNOW INSURERS DO TRY TO CUT COSTS SIMILAR TO I THINK
WHAT KAISER IS DOING BUT THEY'RE NOT REALLY INSERTING
THEMSELVES INTO THE DEFINITIONS OF OF TREATMENT AND OVER
DIRECTLY OVERRIDING CLINICIAN AUTONOMY IN THE WAYS THAT WE'VE
TALKED ABOUT AND YOU'VE HEARD ABOUT TODAY.
I THINK ALL OF THESE PROPOSALS FROM KAISER WOULD REALLY ADD UP
TO DRASTICALLY REDUCED ACCESS TO CARE FOR PATIENTS.
THEY'RE GOING TO GET LESS QUALITY CARE.
AND THESE PROPOSALS WILL DRIVE THERAPISTS OUT OF THE KAISER
NETWORK. SO IF PATIENTS WANT CARE WITHIN
KAISER THEY'RE GOING TO HAVE TO WAIT FOR IT.
AND IF IF THEY CAN AFFORD IT THEY WILL PROBABLY BE LIKELY TO
SEEK IT OUTSIDE OF KAISER AND PAY FOR IT THEMSELVES.
SO I THINK THAT IT WOULD BE A VERY BAD RECIPE FOR CLINICIANS
AND AND FOR THE PUBLIC. THANK YOU, DOCTOR MICHAELS
LOPEZ AND I DON'T HAVE MORE QUESTIONS IF ANY OF MY
COLLEAGUES WOULD LIKE TO ASK ANY THEY DO.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
I THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR CALLING
THESE HEARINGS AND FOR YOUR REALLY GOOD QUESTIONS.
I HAVE BEEN A KAISER MEMBER SINCE I WAS 18.
>> ALL THREE OF MY DAUGHTERS WERE BORN AT KAISER.
I HAVE GOTTEN EXCELLENT CARE AT KAISER NOT JUST THROUGH, YOU
KNOW, PREGNANCIES AND CHILDBIRTH BUT ALSO MY
HUSBAND, YOU KNOW, WHILE AGO HAD A VERY SERIOUS HEALTH ISSUE
THAT GOT HIM TO SPEND ABOUT A MONTH AT KAISER AND GOT NOTHING
BUT EXCELLENT CARE FROM THAT VERY DEDICATED AND PROFESSIONAL
STAFF THERE. AND FOR ALL OF THESE YEARS THE
ONE EXCEPTION TO THAT EXCELLENT CARE FOR MY FAMILY WAS MENTAL
HEALTH RELATED WHEN ONE OF MY DAUGHTERS HAD AN ACUTE CRISIS.
AND WHAT WE ACCESS AT KAISER WAS NOT GREAT AND LEFT US
HAVING TO SEEK OTHER RESOURCES AND WHAT WE WERE PAYING FOR WE
HAD PAID FOR FOR DECADES AND SO I TAKE THIS ISSUE VERY, VERY
SERIOUSLY HAVING LIVED THROUGH IT AND HAVING BEEN A LOYAL
AND DEDICATED KAISER MEMBER AND FOR MOST OF IT AT MOST OF
IT, YOU KNOW, HAVING RECEIVED REALLY EXCELLENT CARE PROVIDED
BY THE STAFF. SO I THANK YOU AGAIN SUPERVISOR
CHAN FOR CALLING THIS HEARING. I RECOGNIZE THAT THERE ARE SOME
TOPICS THAT ARE BEST DISCUSSED AT THE BARGAINING TABLE OR AT
MEDIATION BUT YOU KNOW THERE'S ALSO A LEVEL OF TRANSPARENCY
THAT I THINK WE NEED TO HAVE. >> GIVEN THAT THIS HEARING IS
BEING HELD IN PUBLIC BECAUSE YOU KNOW, KAISER IS SUCH AN
IMPORTANT PART OF THE NETWORK OF CARE IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND ALSO KAISER PROVIDES HEALTH CARE FOR A BIG PART OF THE
EMPLOYEES OF THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO
MYSELF INCLUDED IN OUR DEPENDANCE.
SO I WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT KAISER WITH OUR CONTRIBUTIONS
ARE PUTTING PATIENTS INTERESTS FIRST AND CONNECTING PATIENTS
WITH WHAT THEY NEED AND NOT PUTTING THAT SORT OF SECOND.
IT IS AN ISSUE OF PUBLIC INTEREST.
I AM REALLY DISAPPOINTED THAT THEY'RE NOT HERE AT THE LAST
TIME I MET WITH KAISER LEADERSHIP WAS IN MY ROLE AS A
LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE CHAIR BECAUSE THEY'RE
SEEKING AN EXPANSION OF THEIR CAMPUS WHICH I SUPPORT AND THE
CITY YOU KNOW IN COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO WILL NEGOTIATE WITH
THEM. BUT YOU KNOW THEY'RE COMING TO
US ASKING FOR SOMETHING AND I THINK THAT IT IS FAIR TO BE
TRANSPARENT ABOUT WHAT IS GOING ON.
SO I HOPE THEY'RE LISTENING TODAY.
I AM DISAPPOINTED THAT THEY'RE NOT HERE AND I THINK THAT THEY
MIGHT HAVE TRIED A DIFFERENT APPROACH IN THEIR RELATIONSHIP
WITH US. >> BUT THAT AND I WILL IN A
DIRECT SOME OF MY QUESTIONS TO ELENA WHO SPOKE EARLIER.
>> ELLEN, YOU'RE STILL HERE. THERE ARE SO YOU TALKED A
LITTLE BIT ABOUT WHAT HAPPENED WHEN TOOLS WERE FIRST DEPLOYED
DURING YOUR WORK. SO I'M HOPING THAT YOU CAN TALK
US THROUGH LIKE WHAT HAPPENED YOU KNOW, WHEN THIS WAS ROLLED
OUT. WHAT WAS YOUR RESPONSE?
YOU KNOW, NOT JUST AT THE BARGAINING TABLE BUT LIKE WHAT
WAS YOUR RESPONSE LIKE WITH YOUR COWORKER OR IS WHEN YOU
WERE TOLD THIS IS WHAT'S GOING ON NOW LIKE WHAT DID THAT LOOK
LIKE WITH YOUR SUPERVISOR? >> SURE.
AS SOON AS WE FOUND OUT THAT KAISER HAD UNLICENSED CLERICAL
STAFF DOING TRIAGE WORK WHICH WAS KIND OF THE BEGINNING OF
THIS EROSION OF TRIAGE, WE FILED A GRIEVANCE WHICH OVER
TWO YEARS LATER HASN'T BEEN SCHEDULED FOR ARBITRATION.
WE ALSO FILED A CHARGE WITH THE NLRB NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS
BOARD WHICH THEY HAVE SINCE DEFERRED BACK TO THE GRIEVANCE
AND ARBITRATION PROCESS. >> AND WE FILED A COMPLAINT
WITH THE DAMAGE SEE ALLEGING VIOLATIONS OF CALIFORNIA LAW
WHICH LIMITS TRIAGE TO QUALIFIED LICENSED INDIVIDUALS
AND THE DAMAGE C REPORTS TO US THAT THEY ARE STILL
INVESTIGATING. BUT INTERPERSONALLY WE WERE
VERY ALARMED. >> RIGHT.
BECAUSE I YOU KNOW, SHARE YOUR EXPERIENCE AS HAVING PHENOMENAL
CARE. I'VE HAD TWO BABIES AT KAISER.
I'M A LIFETIME MEMBER AND AS AN EMPLOYEE IN PSYCHIATRY I HAVE
SEEN A MUCH DARKER SIDE OF KAISER THAN I EVER SAW AS A
PATIENT PRIOR. >> SO MY COLLEAGUES AND I WERE
ALARMED, RIGHT? I MEAN I HAVE BEEN TRAINED.
>> IT TOOK ME A DECADE AND A HALF THROUGH EXPERIENCED
PRACTICE GOING THROUGH ALL THE STATE REQUIREMENTS AND I WAS
TOLD WHEN I WAS GOING THROUGH THAT BY THE STATE YOU YOU WILL
YOU KNOW, YOU HAVE TO GO THROUGH THIS BECAUSE PUBLIC
SAFETY IS IN YOUR HANDS. SO MY COLLEAGUES AND I ALL
TOGETHER ESSENTIALLY YOU KNOW, WE'VE WORKED OUR ENTIRE CAREERS
TO ACCESS DOING CLINICAL TRIAGE AND TO QUICKLY LEARN THAT
OPERATORS AND ALGORITHMS CAN JUST QUICKLY DO WHAT HAS TAKEN
ME MANY, MANY YEARS OF EXPERIENCE AND MY COLLEAGUES WE
WERE ALL VERY, VERY FRUSTRATED .
>> SO ELENA, WHAT HAPPENS TO THE PATIENT?
SO IF THEY ARE TRIAGED BY SOMEONE YOU KNOW, SOMEONE WHO
IS NOT LICENSE OR SOMEONE IS THAT EVEN A PERSON?
WHAT HAPPENS IF THEN THEY'RE ASSIGNED TO SOMETHING THAT'S
NOT APPROPRIATE OR THAT THEY FEEL IS NOT HELPING THEM OR
THAT DOESN'T MEET THEIR NEEDS? THEN WHAT IS WHAT IS THEIR
RECOURSE? RIGHT.
SO TO TO ANSWER BLUNTLY WE DON'T ALWAYS KNOW WHAT HAPPENS
TO THOSE PATIENTS WHEN THE BOTS AND OPERATORS GET IT WRONG,
ESPECIALLY WHEN THEY'RE OUTSOURCED BECAUSE THEY'RE
THERE NOW OUTSIDE OF THE INTEGRATED HEALTH PLAN.
SO I ONLY REALLY KNOW OF THE PATIENTS WHO EITHER A PROVIDER
OR THEMSELVES ARE STRONG SELF ADVOCATES.
SO WHEN PATIENTS ADVOCATE FOR THEMSELVES OR THE EXTERNAL
PROGRAM DETERMINES THAT THEY'RE NOT APPROPRIATE FOR THEIR
PROGRAM, THEY END UP BOOKED WITH ME AND INSTEAD OF TALKING
TO ME A MONTH AGO, YOU KNOW WE'RE TALKING DOWN THE ROAD
WHEN THE PATIENT IS FRUSTRATED LIKELY DETERIORATE IT.
A LOT OF THE EVIDENCE SUGGESTS THAT THE BEGINNING OF ONES CARE
EPISODE IS THE OPPORTUNITY TO INSTILL HOPE AND WHEN WE CAN
INSTILL THAT HOPE AND THE BEGINNING A LOT OF PEOPLE GIVE
UP. >> SO WHEN THEY MAKE IT TO ME
AFTER GREAT DELAYS I ACTUALLY CONDUCT A THOROUGH ASSESSMENT
TO CORRECT THEIR TREATMENT PLAN AND CONNECT THEM TO THE
CLINICALLY APPROPRIATE CARE. OFTENTIMES PATIENTS ARE
CONFUSED, UPSET AND THEY OFTEN GET ANGRY THAT THEY'RE GOT
MISDIRECTED IN THE FIRST PLACE. YOU KNOW, AS I SAID EARLIER,
APOLOGIZING HAS BECOME A ROUTINE PART OF MY DAY.
>> SO YOU KNOW, I'M DOING WHAT I CALL SERVICE RECOVERY AS
OPPOSED TO THE ORIGINAL TRIAGE AND CLINICAL ASSESSMENT JOB
THAT I SIGNED UP FOR MANY YEARS AGO.
BOTTOM LINE PATIENTS THAT ARE ALREADY SUFFERING FROM THEIR
PSYCHIATRIC IMPAIRMENT ARE SUFFERING EVEN FURTHER FROM THE
DELAYS IN CARE THAT THE UNLICENSED OPERATOR OR
ALGORITHMIC BASED TRIAGE CREATES AND THOSE CONSEQUENCES
ARE UNFORTUNATELY QUITE DIRE. >> THANK YOU.
THAT'S MY QUESTIONS. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MIDDLEMEN THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR CALLING FOR THIS HEARING.
THANK YOU TO EVERYONE WHO'S SHOWN UP TODAY.
I HAVE A QUESTION FOR DR. MICHAELS.
>> DR. MICHAELS, AT THE END OF YOUR TESTIMONY YOU PREDICTED A
SET OF NEGATIVE RESULTS FOR CLINICIANS, PATIENTS AND KAISER
ITSELF IF KAISER MANAGEMENT WERE TO SUCCEED IN FORCING ITS
TERRIBLE THREE CONTRACT DEMANDS ON UAW MEMBERS COULD YOU EXPAND
ON HOW YOU INFERRED THOSE SPECIFIC RESULTS FROM THE
SPECIFIC CONTENT OF WHAT KAISER MANAGEMENT IS ASKING ANY UAW
MEMBERS TO ACCEPT? SURE.
THANK YOU. I MEAN IT'S NOT TOO VAGUE OF AN
INFERENCE THESE THINGS HAVE BEEN TRIED IN OTHER SETTINGS
AND THERE'S EVIDENCE TO SHOW THAT THIS IS WHAT THESE ARE THE
RESULTS. THIS IS WHAT HAPPENED.
SO FOR EXAMPLE, IF WE THINK ABOUT FOR PATIENTS IF IF THERE
IS A ONE SIZE FITS ALL OR A STANDARDIZED MODEL WHICH IS ONE
OF THE THINGS THAT KAISER WANTS TO DO, WE KNOW THAT THAT'S NOT
GOING TO WORK FOR EVERYBODY. DIFFERENT PEOPLE NEED DIFFERENT
TREATMENT APPROACHES WHICH IS WHY WE HAVE DIFFERENT MODELS
AND THERAPISTS ARE TRAINED IN MULTIPLE MODELS AND ALSO USE
THE INFORMATION THEY OBTAINED FROM THEIR WORK WITH EACH
INDIVIDUAL PATIENT TO ADAPT EVEN WITHIN A SESSION AS WELL
AS OVER TIME. SO WE KNOW THAT WHEN SOMEBODY
RECEIVES TREATMENT THAT IS NOT THE RIGHT MODEL OR THE RIGHT
APPROACH FOR THEM, THEY DON'T FEEL GOOD, THEY DON'T FEEL
HELP, THEY DON'T FEEL UNDERSTOOD.
THEY THINK THERAPY DOESN'T WORK OR THERAPY DOESN'T WORK FOR ME
MAYBE I'M NOT ABLE TO BE HELPED.
THEIR SYMPTOMS MAY WORSEN. THEY MAY DROP OUT OF TREATMENT
ALTOGETHER. >> DROPOUT WILL ALSO PROBABLY
INCREASE FROM THE OUTSOURCING SITUATION WHEN PATIENTS ARE
SHUTTLED TO TWO DIFFERENT THERAPISTS OR THEY HAVE TO
INTERACT WITH AN AI. YOU KNOW THIS IS A DIRECT
INTERRUPTION OF THE ALLIANCE. AND SO THE ALLIANCE IS THE
REASON AND THE METHOD BY WHICH THERAPY WORKS.
AND WHEN YOU'RE INTERRUPTING THAT ALLIANCE AND MESSING WITH
IT, RESULTS ARE GOING TO DECREASE.
OUTCOMES WILL WORSEN. AND THEN FINALLY, YOU KNOW,
WHEN THERE IS A LACK OF AUTONOMY FOR THE THERAPIST
AND MORE BURNOUT, MORE TIME PRESSURES ETC. AND YOU KNOW
THERE'S MORE TURNOVER OF TURNOVER OF THERAPISTS THAN
PATIENTS ARE ALSO LIKELY TO DROP OUT OF CARE WHEN THEY'RE
THERAPIST LEAVES. THEY'LL PROBABLY LEAVE AS WELL.
SO ADDING ALL OF THIS UP TOGETHER FOR FOR THE PATIENTS I
THINK OUTCOMES WILL WILL WORSEN PEOPLE WILL SUFFER MORE
AND IT'S UNNECESSARY. THERE'S ALSO FOR THE CLINICIAN
IT'S AS SOME PEOPLE HAVE SAID WE ARE DUTY BOUND BY OUR CODE
OF ETHICS. EACH DEGREE OR DISCIPLINE HAS A
SPECIFIC CODE OF ETHICS AND WE HAVE A STATE LICENSE AND WE ARE
ACCOUNTABLE TO PROVIDING CARE ACCORDING TO THOSE ETHICAL
STANDARDS AND THE TERMS OF OUR LICENSE IF SOMETHING GOES WRONG
IT'S ON US AND IN THESE SOME OF THESE CHANGES THAT KAISER IS
PROPOSING THAT ACCOUNTABILITY AND RESPONSIBILITY WOULD BE
DIFFUSED AND TAKEN AWAY AND THE AI DOESN'T HAVE A LICENSE.
IT DOESN'T IT DIDN'T GO TO GRADUATE SCHOOL.
THIS IS NOT A VERY GOOD PLAN AT ALL FOR QUALITY CARE AND I
THINK WELL A LOT OF THESE POLICIES MAY SAVE KAISER MONEY
IN THE SHORT TERM WHICH I IMAGINE THAT IS THEIR MAIN
MOTIVATION FOR FOR PROPOSING THESE THINGS.
>> THEY WILL ACTUALLY CREATE NEW AND HIGHER COSTS IN THE
LONG TERM IN TERMS OF REPLACING THERAPIES, IN TERMS OF MEDICAL
COSTS FOR FOR PATIENTS WHO DON'T GET APPROPRIATE CARE.
>> IT'S A VERY COSTLY LONG TERM GAMBIT THAT KAISER IS PLAYING
HERE AND IT'S NOT GOOD FOR PATIENTS FOR THERAPISTS OR
REALLY EVEN FOR KAISER ITSELF. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR WALTON WAS OBSERVING TO ME
EARLIER THAT THIS HEARING REALLY WOULD HAVE BEEN A MORE
USEFUL EXERCISE FOR THE MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IF
KAISER HAD DEEMED HAD DEIGNED TO SEND REPRESENTATION AND I
CAN CERTAINLY UNDERSTAND THEM NOT WANTING TO BE HERE TO HEAR
THIS STORY AND RESPOND TO OUR QUESTIONS.
ON THE OTHER HAND, THEIR NON PRESENCE, YOU KNOW SUGGESTS TO
ME THAT THE STORY IS BASICALLY RIGHT AND THAT THE PICTURE
THAT'S BEING PAINTED BY THE BY THE WORKERS IS IS PRETTY OR
ACCURATE OF A LARGE BUSINESS THAT IS INTERESTED IN SQUEEZING
EFFICIENCIES OUT OF AN UNDER RESOURCED POOR PART OF ITS OF
ITS OPERATION AND WITH BAD CONSEQUENCES THAT ARE A CONCERN
TO THIS BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. SUPERVISOR MELGAR YOU KNOW AS
AS YOU INDICATED I MEAN WE ARE CONCERNED ABOUT HOW WORKERS GET
TREATED IN OUR CITY. WE ARE CONCERNED ABOUT HOW
FOLKS WHO LIVE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND HAVE WHO ARE MEMBERS OF
KAISER AND HAVE MENTAL HEALTH NEEDS ARE TREATED AND GET CARE
OR DO NOT GET CARE BUT WE ARE ALSO A PURCHASER.
>> WE HAVE YOU KNOW, MANY, MANY, MANY SAN FRANCISCO CITY
EMPLOYEES WHO EITHER THEMSELVES OR THEIR FAMILIES AT SOME POINT
ARE GOING TO NEED BEHAVIORAL HEALTH RESOURCES AND WE DO NOT
WANT TO BE SUBJECTING OUR EMPLOYEES TO A SIT AND OUR
RETIREES TO A SITUATION WHERE THEY CAN'T ACTUALLY GET THE
CARE THAT THEY NEED. THE PICTURE WE'VE HEARD IS
PRETTY DYSTOPIAN. I MEAN IT'S SORT OF YOUR
IMAGINATION OF THE WORST CALL CENTER EXCEPT YOU'RE NOT
ARGUING ABOUT, YOU KNOW, WITH THIS BOT ABOUT, YOU KNOW, SOME
PRODUCT OR YOU KNOW SOME YOU KNOW THE SHOES YOU'RE ARGUING
WITH THE BOT ABOUT THE THE KIND OF CARE THAT YOU'RE GOING TO
GET FOR YOUR KID AND THAT'S YOU KNOW, NOT GOOD I GUESS I THINK
I YOU KNOW, I GUESS I WOULD LIKE TO INVITE MS..
MISS MARKEY MAURICE TO COME BACK.
>> YOU'RE IN HIGH DEMAND. I MEAN IT WOULD BE INTERESTING
AGAIN IF KAISER WERE HERE WE COULD HAVE A CONVERSATION ABOUT
HOW MIGHT A WHAT ARE YOU TRYING TO DO WITH A I AND THE WAYS
IN WHICH YOU KNOW I MEAN IT SOUNDS ENTIRELY BELIEVABLE THAT
THEY'RE, YOU KNOW, TRYING TO TURN OVER THIS KIND OF INTAKE
WORK TO A PROCESS THAT DOES NOT INVOLVE PEOPLE AND THAT SEEMS
REALLY WRONG IN AND I GUESS ILLEGAL IN IN THIS CONTEXT.
BUT I MEAN I DON'T THINK THAT THE AS I UNDERSTAND IT THE
CLINICIANS AT KAISER ARE NOT SAYING NO I NEVER YOU'RE SAYING
YES BUT USE IT TO MAKE US BETTER AS CLINICIANS I THINK.
BUT CAN YOU TALK A LITTLE BIT MORE ABOUT HOW AIR COULD BE
DEPLOYED RESPONSIBLY IN WAYS THAT WOULD SUPPORT THERAPIES
WORK RATHER THAN REPLACING IT INAPPROPRIATELY AND HOW COULD I
HELP ADDRESS THE STAFFING SHORTAGE?
>> SURE. I YOU KNOW, THERE'S A LONG
HISTORY OF, YOU KNOW, TECHNOLOGY AND INNOVATION
REALLY HELPING THE MEDICAL FIELD.
SO I MYSELF AND AS A UNION WE ARE NOT ANTI AI, WE ARE NOT
ANTI INNOVATION. I KNOW THAT I SOUND SKEPTICAL
ABOUT THE USE OF AI BUT THAT'S BECAUSE I CARE DEEPLY ABOUT
PATIENT PRIVACY AND CARE EFFECTIVENESS.
AS DR. MICHAEL SHARED YOU START RECORDING SESSIONS, YOU ENTER A
THIRD PARTY INTO THE ROOM. THE NATURE OF THAT ALLIANCE IS
IS SEVERED. THERE'S JUST NO DATA THAT
SUPPORTS IT. SO I WANT TO SEE THAT DATA
FIRST BEFORE MAKING MASSIVE PUBLIC HEALTH DECISIONS.
>> BUT I HAVE SEEN HOW KAISER HAS TIME AND TIME AGAIN MADE
CHANGES IN OUR DAILY OPERATION IN THE NAME OF IMPROVING ACCESS
OR PATIENT CARE WHEN THE CHANGES ARE MORE ABOUT THEIR
BOTTOM LINE. SO AS A UNION WE'RE NOT AGAINST
THE RESPONSIBLE USE OF AI USING AI THAT SUPPORTS THERAPISTS
PROTECT PATIENT PRIVACY AND DOES NOT REMOVE REMOVE
HUMANS FROM THIS HUMAN WORK OF THERAPY.
>> I CAN SEE I USE TO REMOVE SOME MENIAL TASKS ADDRESS
OPERATIONAL INEFFICIENCIES LIKE PAPERWORK OR ADMINISTRATIVE
LAG. WE'RE SEEING THE SAME PROBLEMS
IN THOSE REALMS THAT WE DID A DECADE AGO SO I'D LIKE TO SEE
USE THERE OR MAYBE EVEN IN WAYS THAT WOULD HELP US HONE OUR
SKILLS AS HUMAN THERAPISTS. BUT BEFORE A.I. IS DEPLOYED
IN ANY MANNER IT IS ABSOLUTELY NECESSARY THAT THE THERAPISTS
WHO WILL BE USING OR AFFECTED BY AI TOOLS HAVE A REAL VOICE
AND HOW IT'S DEPLOYED. I FEAR THAT THE TECH INDUSTRY
ALONGSIDE MY EMPLOYER SIMPLY SEES A PROFIT MAKING
OPPORTUNITY INCLUDING THE COST SAVINGS OF LAYING OFF HUMAN
PROVIDERS AND IS NOT GENUINELY MOTIVATED BY IMPROVING ACCESS
TO INNOVATION OR OVERALL CARE EXPERIENCES AND YOU MENTIONED
THE SHORTAGE SO VERY RESPECTFULLY WE PUSH BACK ON
THE TRUE EXISTENCE OF A THERAPIST SHORTAGE ESPECIALLY
IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> I CANNOT THROW A ROCK ON
MARKET STREET WITHOUT HITTING FIVE MUFTIS.
>> YOU KNOW THE SHORTAGE IS NOT KEYSTONES.
>> I WILL NOT SCOUTS. I PROMISE DO NO HARM.
AM I RIGHT? THE SHORTAGE IS NOT AVAILABLE.
THERAPISTS, SUPERVISORS THE SHORTAGE OUR THERAPISTS THAT
CAN MAKE A LIVING ON THE PAY RATES UNILATERALLY DETERMINED
BY THE HEALTH PLANS THE SHORTAGE OUR PROVIDERS TAKING
INSURANCE OR WILLING TO ACCEPT FACTORY ASSEMBLY LINE WORKING
CONDITIONS THAT NOW WANT TO PUSH QUESTIONABLE TECHNOLOGY ON
US AS WELL. >> THAT'S THE SHORTAGE HERE.
>> THERE ARE PLENTY OF US WILLING TO WORK AND SUPPORT
HUMAN HEALING WHEN GIVEN THE APPROPRIATE RESOURCES TO DO SO
ACCORDING TO INDUSTRY STANDARDS OF CARE AND JUST FROM A MENTAL
EXERCISE PROFESSOR SUBJECTIVE IF THERE IS A HUMAN SHORTAGE
HELP ME UNDERSTAND WHY LAYING OFF THE HUMANS COMMITTED TO THE
WORK IS THE VIABLE SOLUTION. I QUOTE MY COLLEAGUE MAKE IT
MAKE SENSE. >> SO THAT'S THAT'S THAT'S HOW
I FEEL ABOUT THAT. I MEAN THANK YOU FOR THAT.
IT IS YOU KNOW IF OUR OUR KAISER REPRESENTATIVE IS WERE
HERE I WOULD LOVE IT. >> I WOULD ASK YOU TO I WOULD
ASK THEM, YOU KNOW WHY THIS LANGUAGE THAT SEEMS PRETTY
REASONABLE AND HAS WORKED ITS WAY INTO A ANOTHER CONTRACT YOU
KNOW WOULD NOT WORK IN NORTHERN CALIFORNIA.
BUT OF COURSE WE CANNOT ASK THAT QUESTION OR AT LEAST WE
CAN ASK IT BUT IT'S GOING TO AVOID.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. YEAH.
AND THEN I DO HAVE A COUPLE OF QUESTIONS FOR MS..
>> PARSONS. >> WELCOME BACK.
HELLO. HELLO.
SO YOU HAVE YOU'RE IN AN INTERESTING SPOT IN THAT YOU'RE
BOTH YOU'RE BOTH INSIDE AND OUT.
YOU'RE BOTH YOU ARE BOTH A KAISER THERAPIST AND YOU'VE
YOU'VE WORKED ARE CURRENTLY WORK AS AN INDEPENDENT
PROVIDER, CORRECT? >> I DO NOT SEE KAISER CLIENTS
THROUGH THAT. OKAY.
WE'RE NOT ALLOWED TO. OKAY.
>> EVERYONE HEARD THAT RIGHT. SO I'M WONDERING GIVEN THAT IF
YOU COULD TALK A LITTLE BIT MORE ABOUT THE DIFFERENCES
IN THE PROBLEMS THAT YOU FACE WORKING AS A KAISER STAFF
THERAPIST AND THE PROBLEMS WE FACE WORKING AS AN INDEPENDENT
CONTRACTOR, INDEPENDENT CONTRACTOR, INDEPENDENT
PROVIDER AND TELL US WHAT YOU THINK ARE THE BEST AND WORST
PARTS OF THE WORK ON BOTH SIDES OF THAT DIVIDE.
>> YEAH SO I ALREADY NAMED RIGHT THAT THE INTEGRATED CARE
MODEL THAT KAISER SAYS IT HAS WHEN IT ACTUALLY WORKS IT WORKS
VERY WELL, RIGHT? SO AS A KAISER STAFF THERAPIST
I CAN SEE WHAT'S GOING ON WITH MY CLIENTS, RIGHT?
A PERFECT EXAMPLE IS I HAD A WOMAN WHO WAS 41 WEEKS PREGNANT
AND SHE WAS TERRIFIED OF GETTING AN INJECTION AND I
COULD JUST LOOK IN HER CHART TO SEE HOW SHE GIVEN BIRTH YET.
IS SHE IN THERE? WHAT'S GOING ON?
WHAT'S HAPPENING? RIGHT.
AND IN ANY OPENING I HAD I ACTUALLY SCHEDULED HER TO CALL
HER BECAUSE SHE WAS TERRIFIED AND I ACTUALLY SAME AS SOME OF
US HERE RIGHT HAVE HAVE BEEN THROUGH THAT.
I'VE GIVEN BIRTH AT KAISER. I WAS INDUCED TWO TIMES.
SO I CAN USE THAT PERSONAL EXPERIENCE TO SAY LIKE HEY,
THIS IS WHAT YOU MIGHT BE ABLE TO EXPECT.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT YOUR ANXIETY.
LET'S TALK ABOUT YOUR WORRY. I CANNOT DO THAT AS A WHEN I
WORK AS A THIRD PARTY CONTRACTOR BECAUSE I DON'T HAVE
ANY OTHER NOTES THAN MY OWN RIGHT.
THERE'S NO INFORMATION. THERE'S NO TEST RESULTS.
THERE'S NO DOCTORS THAT I CAN JUST MESSAGE AND SAY HEY,
WHAT'S GOING ON? HEY, THIS IS A CONCERN THEY
HAVE, RIGHT? THIS PARTICULAR CLIENT I
MESSAGED HER OB AND SAID THIS IS A BIG CONCERN SHE HAS JUST
WANT TO GIVE YOU A HEADS UP. >> RIGHT.
SO THAT'S PROBABLY THE DOWNFALL OF WORKING WITH A THIRD PARTY
CONTRACTOR IN TERMS OF KAISER, THE BIGGEST CHALLENGE IS TIME,
RIGHT? I MEAN WE'VE ALL TALKED ABOUT
IT BUT IN OUR CONTRACT RIGHT NOW EVERY SINGLE RETURN PATIENT
WE HAVE MEETING WE'VE SEEN THEM BEFORE AND THEY ARE RETURNING
TO US THOSE SLOTS RIGHT FOR EVERY FIVE OF THOSE WE SEE WE
HAVE ONE INTAKE MEETING. WE'VE NOT SEEN THIS PERSON
BEFORE OR AT LEAST NOT IN THE LAST YEAR.
AND SO THE EXPECTATION IS IF I'M GETTING FIVE NEW CLIENTS A
WEEK LET'S SAY RIGHT LET'S SAY I SEE 30 PATIENTS AND FIVE OF
THEM ARE NEW TO MAKE THAT ALL FIT I HAVE TO BE TERMINATING OR
CLOSING SERVICES WITH FIVE RETURN PATIENTS WHICH IS JUST
NOT HAPPENING OF COURSE, RIGHT? >> ESPECIALLY BECAUSE WE DON'T
REALLY GET TO SEE RETURN PATIENTS AS MUCH AS WE SHOULD.
SO IF I SEE A RETURN PATIENT ONCE EVERY 4 TO 6 WEEKS IT'S
OBVIOUSLY GOING TO TAKE LONGER FOR THEM TO RECOVER IF I COULD
SEE THEM WEEKLY. THERE ARE ALSO CERTAIN MODELS
OF CARE WHERE REALLY ETHICALLY I SHOULD BE SEEING THEM WEEKLY
. >> YOU KNOW MDR, FOR EXAMPLE IS
A SERVICE WE OFFER. YOU NEED TO SEE SOMEONE WEEKLY
FOR THAT BUT THEY'RE NOT BOOKED WEEKLY BECAUSE THERE'S JUST NOT
TIME FOR THAT. >> THE ANOTHER ISSUE I SEE
WITHIN KAISER IS I'M A SPECIALIST SO I DO COUPLES
THERAPY. I'M A CERTIFIED SEX THERAPIST.
I'M A PERINATAL MENTAL HEALTH SPECIALIST.
THOSE ARE ALL THINGS THAT PEOPLE REALLY WANT, RIGHT?
>> I'M ONE OF THREE SEX THERAPISTS WITHIN THE ENTIRE
NORTHERN CALIFORNIA REGION. RIGHT.
AND I CAN PUT THAT ON MY PROFILE IN TERMS OF A THIRD
PARTY CONTRACTOR. >> RIGHT.
THEY CAN GO THEY CAN SEE LIKE OH, SHE DOES THIS, SHE DOES
THAT. THAT'S GREAT.
I WANT TO BOOK WITH HER WITHIN KAISER.
I HAVE WORKED THERE FOR FIVE YEARS ABOUT FOUR YEARS AGO OR
SORRY ABOUT ONE YEAR AGO SO FOUR YEARS THEN I FOUND OUT
THAT THERAPISTS COULD CREATE THEIR OWN MY DOCTOR ONLINE
PROFILE WHICH IF YOU'VE HAD A PCP, IF YOU'VE BEEN WITH KAISER
YOU CAN GO AND LOOK AT THE DOCTORS AND THEY SAY
INFORMATION ABOUT THEM. >> I DIDN'T KNOW WE COULD DO
THAT IN MENTAL HEALTH SO ABOUT A YEAR AGO I FILLED ONE OUT
AND THEN I STARTED GETTING REFERRALS FOR CERTIFIED SEX
THERAPISTS AND MY MANAGER WHO WANTED THAT SERVICE MY MANAGER
TOLD ME TO TAKE THAT OFF MY PROFILE BECAUSE MY SCHEDULE WAS
GETTING TOO FULL WITH PEOPLE OUTSIDE OF MY SERVICE AREA.
I REFUSED SO I KEPT IT ON THERE BECAUSE LEGALLY SPEAKING YOU
CAN BE SEEN ANYWHERE WITHIN THE NORTHERN CALIFORNIA REGION AS A
KAISER PATIENT BUT THAT'S ANOTHER PROBLEM RIGHT?
EVEN IF YOU HAVE AN ISSUE WITHIN KAISER YOU'RE NOT
DIRECTED TO THAT SPECIALIST AND THIS HAS BECOME MORE OF AN
ISSUE SINCE TRIAGE LEFT OR RIGHT SINCE WE'VE HAD ROBOTS
AND PEOPLE I DON'T EVEN KNOW YOU KNOW, SCHEDULING INTO OUR
APPOINTMENT SLOTS BECAUSE YOU KNOW IF LIKE AN I I'M TRYING
NOT TO USE THE TERMINOLOGY AND SHORTCUTS IF AN INTAKE
ASSESSMENT COORDINATOR WHO WORKS IN MY OFFICE SAYS OH THIS
PATIENT IS YOU KNOW HAS POSTPARTUM DEPRESSION, HE'S
GOING TO REACH OUT TO ME OR BOOK THEM IN MY SCHEDULE RIGHT
? >> A ROBOT CERTAINLY CAN'T DO
THAT, YOU KNOW. SO THAT'S ANOTHER BIG ISSUE
WITHIN WORKING WITH KAISER IS THAT CLIENTS DON'T ALWAYS GET
THE SPECIALIZED CARE THEY NEED .
SO NOTWITHSTANDING THOSE CHALLENGES IT SEEMS LIKE IT
WOULD BE GOOD TO BRING MORE CARE BACK IN-HOUSE AND I'M
WONDERING IF YOU HAVE THOUGHTS ON THINGS THAT KAISER COULD DO
TO DO THAT AND WHAT BENEFITS THAT WOULD HAVE FOR THE CURRENT
WORKFORCE AND FOR KAISER ENROLLEES.
>> RIGHT. SO I MEAN YOU HEARD THAT
KAISER'S YOU KNOW, AMOUNT OF ENROLLEES HAS BEEN ABOUT THE
SAME THE AMOUNT OF THERAPIES HAS BEEN ABOUT THE SAME BUT THE
ENROLLEES WANTING MENTAL HEALTH CARE HAS GONE UP BY 20% WHICH
IS SIGNIFICANT. THAT'S A HUGE JUMP.
SO OBVIOUSLY IT MAKES SENSE TO HAVE MORE CLINICIANS RIGHT?
>> THAT'S THE OBVIOUS ANSWER AND GIVING US CASELOAD CAPS
WHICH ALSO MAKES SENSE. YOU KNOW, AGAIN I CAN'T BE
IN TAKING PATIENTS IF I HAVE NO OPEN SLOTS AND I CAN'T BE
SEEING MY PATIENTS AS MUCH AS THEY NEED WHAT IS ACTUALLY
ETHICAL IF I HAVE NO SLOTS? >> SO KEEPING A FULL STAFF OF
THERAPISTS RIGHT PSYCHIATRIST CASE MANAGERS ASSESSMENT INTAKE
COORDINATORS INTENSIVE OUTPATIENT PROGRAM CLINICIANS
RIGHT. AND IT DOES MEAN HIRING MORE
CLINICIANS BUT INSTEAD KAISER IS PAYING TO OUTSOURCE CARE TO
CLINICIANS WHO WORK FOR THIRD PARTY CONTRACTORS WHO DO HAVE
CASELOAD CAPS, RIGHT? >> THOSE THIRD PARTY
CONTRACTORS WE SEE IT ALL THE TIME LIKE OH WE NEED TO REFER
TO THE EXTERNAL PROVIDER NETWORK WHICH IS A WHOLE LIST
OF PEOPLE AND SOMETIMES THOSE CERTAIN YOU KNOW LIKE GROW OR
RULE OR WHATEVER THERE ARE NO OPEN SLOTS TO REFER TO BECAUSE
THEIR CLINICIANS HAVE CASELOAD CAPS AND IF THERE ARE NO
CLINICIANS WHO HAVE OPENINGS THAT IS NOT A RESOURCE THAT WE
CAN SEND TO. SO WE HAVE TO LOOK FOR A
DIFFERENT ONE. >> ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU. YEAH, THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
IF OTHER COLLEAGUES HAVE QUESTIONS OR OH, THERE WE GO.
SUPERVISOR JAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN THANK YOU
SIR ROGER CHAN FOR TODAY'S HEARING.
>> I DO NOT HAVE ADDITIONAL QUESTIONS.
I THINK WHAT I WOULD LIKE TO SEE IS IF WE'RE AT TOWARDS THE
AT THE END OF THIS HEARING IS SINCE WE'RE HOLDING THIS
HEARING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE IS THAT PERHAPS IS WE
COULD EITHER SUBPOENA KAISER OR THAT WE ISSUE A LETTER ON
BEHALF OF THE BOARD SUPERVISOR TO KAISER INDICATING ALL THE
QUESTIONS THAT WE HAD TODAY COLLECTIVELY AS A COMMITTEE OF
THE WHOLE AND BE ABLE TO SUBPOENA KAISER FOR THE ANSWER
TO OUR QUESTIONS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISOR
CHEN, DO YOU HAVE ANY COMMENTS BEFORE WE GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT
? >> NO I DO.
LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT FIRST AND I'M GOING TO OFFER A
CLOSING REMARKS THE PUBLIC COMMENT RIGHT.
>> IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO PROVIDE PUBLIC COMMENT ON ITEM 52
PLEASE LINE UP TO SPEAK NOW ON THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE
CHAMBER. >> ONCE WE EXHAUST THE IN LINE
IN PERSON LINE WE WILL GO TO OUR REMOTE CALLERS.
IF YOU ANTICIPATE PROVIDING PUBLIC COMMENT THE TELEPHONE
NUMBER AND MEETING 90 ARE PUBLISHED ON THE AGENDA
AND STREAMING ON YOUR SCREEN. >> FIRST PUBLIC COMMENT OR HERE
IN PERSON EXCUSE ME. OH MY NAME IS BARRY TORONTO
AND I AM A KAISER PATIENT. I WANT TO SPEAK FIRST BECAUSE I
HAVE A KAISER CLASS ONLINE AND IN TEN MINUTES SO IT HAS TO
RELATE TO THIS TOPIC MATTER THEY OFFER GREAT CLASSES
AND ALSO DID A GREAT JOB ON MY CATARACTS FOR MY EYES THE ONLY
THING I DON'T UNDERSTAND IS WHY THEY DON'T CARE ABOUT TOM ABOUT
DOING GREAT JOB ON MENTAL HEALTH COUNSELING.
I DON'T THAT DOESN'T MAKE SENSE TO ME HOW YOU YOU PROVIDE ALL
THESE GREAT SERVICES BUT YOU DON'T WANT TO CONTINUE IT.
YEAH I MEAN I. I MEAN IF YOU WATCHED TWO AND A
HALF MEN AND AND AND CHARLIE SHEEN AND THE THERAPIST YOU
KNOW YOU YOU GOT TO HAVE A THERAPIST THE BACK AND FORTH I
IS DOESN'T HAVE THE GRADUATE DEGREE WHICH IS TRUE I DON'T
DOESN'T MAKE SENSE TO DO IT THIS WAY WHEN WHEN ALL LOGIC GO
GOES THE OTHER WAY SO KAISER HAS GREAT EMPLOYEES AND NOT
ONLY THAT BUT THEY'RE NOT HERE FOR THEIR PAY.
THEY'RE HERE FOR THEIR PATIENTS .
SO SO IT SHOWS KAISER SHOULD BE HAPPY AND BE HERE TO SEE ALL
THE SUPPORT FOR KAISER PATIENTS BUT OBVIOUSLY IT'S ABOUT KAISER
TRYING TO SAVE MONEY RATHER THAN CARE ABOUT THEIR PATIENTS
HEALTH. SO SO I'M VERY MUCH CONCERNED
SO CARING ABOUT ABOUT OUR FELLOW HUMAN UNION BROTHERS
AND SISTERS I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT THAT WE GET ANSWERS
FROM KAISER AND ASK THEM TO JOIN JOIN THE CROWD AND THE
COMMUNITY TO CARE ABOUT THE MENTAL HEALTH OF THE CITY
AND AND ESPECIALLY THEIR PATIENTS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU, MR. TORONTO FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER BY SUPERVISORS IAN
LEWIS UNITE HERE THE HOTEL AND RESTAURANT WORKERS UNION
AMONG OUR MEMBERS WE HAVE FOUGHT FOR AND WON HEALTH CARE
BENEFITS FOR 65,000 KAISER PATIENTS AROUND THIS COUNTRY
INCLUDING 14,000 HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND YOU KNOW IT'S ESPECIALLY THE PEOPLE CHOOSE KAISER
BECAUSE OF THE PROMISE OF KAISER, THE PROMISE OF
INTEGRATED COORDINATED HUMAN BASED CARE THAT'S ESPECIALLY
IMPORTANT TO A COMMUNITY LIKE OURS WHERE THREE QUARTERS ARE
BORN OVERSEAS, GREW UP SPEAKING DIFFERENT LANGUAGES, INCREDIBLY
IMPORTANT TO NAVIGATE A HEALTH SYSTEM AND THEY CHOOSE KAISER
DESPITE THE PRICE YOU ALL KNOW HOW HARD OUR UNION HAS FOUGHT
FOR HEALTH CARE ESPECIALLY IN THIS CITY.
THE U.S. SPENDS TWICE AS MUCH AS ANY OTHER COUNTRY ON HEALTH
CARE. NORTHERN CALIFORNIA SPENDS
TWICE THAT OUR HEALTH BENEFITS FOR A FAMILY COST $18.40 A
KAISER THAT COMES OUT OF OUR MEMBERS POCKETS HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO THAT'S ALMOST FIVE TIMES THE MINIMUM SPENDING
REQUIREMENT IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR HEALTH CARE.
IT'S ALMOST NOT QUITE THE MINIMUM WAGE IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND I BRING THAT UP BECAUSE IT'S NOT FOR A LACK OF
RESOURCES THAT ALL OF THIS IS HAPPENING.
IT'S BECAUSE OF CONCERTED CHOICES AND I KNOW THE FACT
THAT KAISER UNDERVALUES BEHAVIORAL HEALTH COMPARED TO
OTHER HEALTH CARE IS NOT A SURPRISE TO ANYBODY HERE BUT
WHAT YOU HEARD TODAY SHOULD TERRIFY YOU AS LEADERS OF A
CITY WHICH IS THE BIGGEST PURCHASER OF HEALTH CARE
BENEFITS AND LEADERS OF A COUNTY THAT IS ENTRUSTED WITH
THE PUBLIC HEALTH, IT SOUNDS TO ME LIKE KAISER IS LEADING US
DOWN THE TRACK OF A K-SHAPED ECONOMY IN HEALTH CARE WHERE
FOR WORKING PEOPLE EVEN THOSE WHO CAN GIVE UP $18 AN HOUR FOR
EXCELLENT HEALTH CARE BENEFITS, WE ARE OFFERED IN-HOME
AND TECHNOLOGY AND PRECARIOUS GIG WORKERS AND THE ONLY PEOPLE
WHO ARE GOING TO BE LEFT WITH TRUE HUMAN BASED CARE ARE THOSE
WHO CAN PAY OUT OF CASH. >> IT'S NO POLITICAL COMMUNITY
COLLEGES FOR CUTTING YOU OFF. WE ARE PROVIDING EVERYBODY THE
SAME. TWO MINUTES NEXT SPEAKER KIM
CARR VALLONE SAN FRANCISCO LABOR COUNCIL AND WE LIVE
IN VERY STRANGE TIMES AND ALL OF YOU SHOULD BE VERY CONCERNED
ABOUT THE HEALTH AND WELFARE OF OUR CITY EMPLOYEES.
WE'VE ALREADY HAD A TRAGEDY HAPPENED DOWN IN VTA AND SAN
JOSE. >> THE MENTAL HEALTH OF OUR
CITY EMPLOYEES IS CRITICAL TO THEM BEING ABLE TO DO THEIR
JOBS DAY IN AND DAY OUT. >> THE FACT THAT KAISER WANTS
TO LEAD WITH THE SAME I THAT CAN'T DISTINGUISH A CONE FROM A
DOG TO A PERSON ON THE STREET AND PUT THAT IN CHARGE OF
MENTAL HEALTH CARE YOU SHOULD ALL BE LIKE TERRIFIED OF WHAT
CAN HAPPEN TO OUR WORKERS AND WHAT HAPPENS IN OUR CITY
AND COUNTY. >> WE KNOW AI IS IMPERFECT BUT
WE CANNOT ALLOW KAISER TO EXPERIMENT ON OUR CITY
AND COUNTY WORKERS. WE KNOW IT DOESN'T WORK.
>> WE KNOW A.I. DOESN'T VALUE LIFE.
IT CAN'T IT'S NOT ALIVE BUT ALLOWING OUR CITY AND COUNTY
WORKERS TO RECEIVE THIS TYPE OF CARE IS COMPLETELY UNACCEPTABLE
ON SO MANY LEVELS. >> I CAN'T VALUE LIFE.
IT DOESN'T DISTINGUISH WHETHER THE CONE HAS A LIFE A DOG HAS A
LIFE OR A PERSON HAS A LIFE AND THEM TAKEN AWAY MEANS
NOTHING TO THE MACHINE OTHER THAN SOMEONE HAS TO TELL IT
THAT IT WAS WRONG. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS TO THE NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS BENJAMIN KAMLA.
I SERVE AS THE POLICY MANAGER FOR THE NATIONAL ASSOCIATION OF
SOCIAL WORKERS CALIFORNIA CHAPTER.
IN RESPONSE TO KAISER PERMANENTE'S TERRIBLE THREE
PROPOSALS WE ASKED OUR SOCIAL WORK MEMBERS COMPRISED OF
KAISER PATIENTS AND EMPLOYEES HOW THESE CHANGES ARE AFFECTING
CARE. AND THE FEEDBACK WE RECEIVED
WAS CONSISTENT THESE PROPOSALS SHIFT THE FOCUS AWAY FROM
CLINICAL CLINICAL DECISION MAKING TOWARDS REDUCING COSTS.
>> ONE MAJOR CONCERN WAS A PROPOSAL TO HAVE BEHAVIORAL
HEALTH TRIAGE CONDUCTED BY CALL CENTERS FOR NON-LICENSED
PERSONNEL INSTEAD OF LICENSED BEHAVIORAL HEALTH PROVIDERS.
AS ONE OF OUR SOCIAL WORKERS SHARED QUOTE IF WE WANT BETTER
TRIAGE, KAISER NEEDS A FORMAL INTAKE DEPARTMENT NOT A CALL
CENTER AND QUOTE ANOTHER SHARED THAT EVEN WHEN THEY IDENTIFY A
PATIENT IS IN URGENT NEED OF THERAPY THEY MUST STILL SEND
THAT PATIENT THROUGH A PHONE TRIAGE PROCESS WITH AN
UNLICENSED REPRESENTATIVE BEFORE CONNECTING THEM WITH
CARE. >> AND OF THOSE WE CONTACTED
95% REPORTED BEING NOT AT ALL CONFIDENT THAT KAISER CELL
PHONE SERVICE REPRESENTATIVES ARE CONSISTENT WITH MEETING
CALIFORNIA'S REQUIREMENTS THAT LIMIT NON-LICENSED STAFF FROM
MAKING CLINICAL ASSESSMENTS ON DETERMINING WHEN PATIENTS NEED
LICENSED BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE PROVIDERS ALSO RAISE CONCERNS
ABOUT THE LOSS OF CONTINUITY OF CARE.
PATIENTS ARE BEING REDIRECTED TO OUTSIDE PROVIDERS TO MEET
THOSE ACCESS METRICS EVEN WHEN THEY HAVEN'T ESTABLISHED A
THERAPEUTIC RELATIONSHIP. >> ONE PROVIDER DESCRIBED
PATIENTS BEING REFERRED TO QUOTE A BRAND NEW PROVIDER
INSTEAD OF BOOKING A SOONER APPOINTMENT WITH THEIR REGULAR
PROVIDER MADE TO START ALL OVER AGAIN.
SO TAKEN TOGETHER THESE CONCERNS REFLECT A NEED TO
PRIORITIZE CLINICAL EXPERTISE, CONTINUITY OF CARE AND PATIENT
SAFETY OVER ADMINISTRATIVE EFFICIENCY.
WE URGE KAISER PERMANENTE TO LISTEN TO THE CONCERNS OF
PATIENTS AND PROVIDERS. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. SO THE NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> HELLO. GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS DR. GUILLERMO RODRIGUEZ AND I'M THE REGION B
DIRECTOR FOR NSW CALIFORNIA CHAPTER.
IT'S A PLEASURE TO BE HERE. I'M HERE TO ADVOCATE FOR ALL
THE SOCIAL WORKERS, FOR THE TEAM HERE, FOR THE VOICES WHO
ARE HERE TODAY ADVOCATING USUALLY POLICIES GET
IMPLEMENTED WHEN SOMETHING TRAGIC HAPPENS THAT'S NOT GET
TO THAT POINT. WE WANT TO IMPLEMENT POLICIES
TO STOP ANY TRY TO GS OF MENTAL HEALTH.
>> ON KAISER'S WEBSITE IT STATES QUOTE WE BELIEVE A
PERSON'S PHYSICAL HEALTH, MENTAL HEALTH AND SOCIAL HEALTH
ARE CONNECTED AND ESSENTIAL TO A PERSON'S OVER ALL WELL-BEING.
>> I END QUOTE. >> AS SOCIAL WORKERS WE AGREE
WITH THAT. BUT THOSE WORDS MUST BE
REFLECTED INTO PRACTICE. >> WITH KAISER NOT BEING HERE
IT SPEAKS VOLUMES. >> IT HURTS A LITTLE BIT OR A
LOT FOR SOME OF US BUT I WISH THAT COULD BE HERE SO I COULD
HEAR WHAT THEY HAVE TO SAY IN REGARDS TO THE VOICES
IN TODAY'S ROOM. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
AND AS THIS SPEAKER APPROACHES THE MICROPHONE, IF WE HAVE
ANYONE ELSE IN THE ROOM WHO HAS PUBLIC COMMENT FOR THIS
COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE HEARING FROM WHOM WE HAVE NOT YET
HEARD, YOU MAY LINE UP TO SPEAK ALONG THAT WESTERN WALL.
NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE. >> GOOD EVENING.
THIS HAS BEEN AN EXTREMELY INTERESTING PRESENTATION AND I
CERTAINLY THINK IT'S IMPORTANT TO KEEP THE HUMANITY
IN MEDICINE AND IN OTHER ACTIVITIES CERTAINLY
IN THERAPY. THERE WERE MANY ISSUES RAISED
ABOUT QUALITY PRIVACY ACCOUNTABILITY, WHO CONTROLS
THE VAT? WHO CONTROLS CHANGES THAT MIGHT
BE MADE? THERE'S NO SUCH THING AS A
FIXED ITEM. THERE APPARENTLY MANY
DIFFERENCES IN HOW A.I. IS WORKING WHO IS RESPONSIBLE FOR
MAKING SUPPOSED IMPROVEMENTS OR PROVIDING SO-CALLED GUARDRAILS
WHICH WE'VE HEARD AND READ ABOUT FAILING QUITE A LOT.
THE NEW YORK TIMES HAD AN EXTENDED STORY ABOUT A COUPLE
WHOSE SON TEENAGE SON WAS HELPED BY A CHAT PAL AS IT WERE
BASICALLY TO WORK OUT ALL THE DETAILS OF HOW TO COMMIT
SUICIDE. AND AS THE VERY LAST STEP, THE
SON FOR NOW A SECOND TIME SAID I'M THINKING OF AND THE TIMES
GOT THE EXCHANGES BETWEEN THE THEIR SON AND THE CHAT.
>> HE SAID I'M THINKING OF LEAVING THE ROPE LYING AROUND
SO SOMEBODY WILL FIND IT. AND THE CHAT ANSWERED AND I'M
PARAPHRASING NOT SUCH A GOOD IDEA.
MAYBE YOU SHOULD LET THE FOLKS LEARN WHAT YOU HAVE PLANNED
WHEN YOU HAVE SUCCEEDED BASICALLY WHEN THEY FIND YOU
IN THE CLOSET HANGING FROM THE BAR WITH A ROPE.
THAT THE CHAT HELPED THE KID MAKE.
SO THE A.I. IS WORKING WITH A WHOLE DIFFERENT WORLD OF WHO
KNOWS WHAT MOTIVES AND PURPOSES MAKING MONEY FOR THE COMPANY
THAT MADE IT AND SO ON. BIG PROBLEM.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> SEEING NO OTHER INDIVIDUALS
WHO ARE IN PERSON WE WILL GO TO OUR CALL IN LINE IF YOU HAVE
NOT ALREADY DONE SO PLEASE PRESS STAR THREE TO LINE UP
REMOTELY WHEN IT'S YOUR TURN TO SPEAK LISTEN CAREFULLY AND WHEN
THE SYSTEM SAYS YOU HAVE BEEN UNMUTED THAT WILL BE THAT IS
YOUR CUE TO BEGIN YOUR COMMENTS.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR FIRST CALLER.
WELCOME SPEAKER THANK YOU. >> CAN YOU HEAR ME?
>> YES, WE CAN HEAR YOU. I SUPPORT THE PRI, THE WORKERS
AREA. I USE THE DEMO IT FOR WORKING
PARTY LIKE DOROTHY AND MANAGEMENT.
>> IT'S PAUSING THE SPEAKERS TIME WE WILL BE REDIRECTING
AND MOVING ON TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
NEXT CALLER. >> THAT CONCLUDES THE COMMENT.
Q MR. PRESIDENT, THAT MESSAGE WAS BROUGHT TO YOU BY YOUR
CALIFORNIA STATE LEGISLATURE WHICH IS NOT SUBJECT TO THE
REQUIREMENTS OF REMOTE PUBLIC COMMENT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED AND SUPERVISOR CHEN, THIS IS
YOUR HEARING. >> THANK YOU BILL PRESS
AND MANAGEMENT. I WOULD LIKE TO TAKE A MOMENT
TO THANK EVERYONE WHO ATTENDED TODAY'S HEARING.
I ESPECIALLY WANT TO APPRECIATE THE WORKERS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR TAKING TIME OFF
TO EDUCATE US ON EVERYTHING THAT YOU ARE GOING ON AT YOUR
WORKPLACE, YOUR COMMITMENT TO PATIENT CARE, QUALITY, PATIENT
SAFETY. IT'S LOUD AND VERY CLEAR THE
THINGS THAT WE DISCUSSED TODAY ARE INFURIATING, CONCERNING
AND UNACCEPTABLE. >> IT IS A SHAME THAT KAISER
DIDN'T SEND A REPRESENTATIVE TO ANSWER OUR QUESTIONS OR AT
LEAST TO LISTEN TO TESTIMONY PROVIDED TODAY.
NEXT TUESDAY I WILL BE INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
CALLING ON KAISER TO DROP ITS TERRIBLE STORY CONTRACT EVENTS.
AS HIGHLIGHTED BY THE TESTIMONY AND PRESENTATION WE HEARD TODAY
. WITH THAT I WANT TO SHOUT OUT
TO MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE JACKIE PRAGER FOR HER WORK ON THIS
HEARING AND ALSO THE RESOLUTION THAT I WILL BE INTRODUCING NEXT
TUESDAY. >> THROUGH THE CHAIR I WOULD
LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION TO FILE THIS HEARING.
>> ALL RIGHT. I THINK I JUST GAVEL THAT
RIGHT. OKAY.
THIS MATTER HAS BEEN HEARD AND IS NOW FILED.
ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR NEXT SPECIAL ORDER
PLEASE CALL ITEMS 53 AND 54 TOGETHER.
>> YES. ITEM 53 IS A HEARING AT THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SITTING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE TO
CONSIDER THE RENEWAL AND EXPANSION OF A PROPERTY
BASED BUSINESS IMPROVEMENT DISTRICT KNOWN AS A DOWNTOWN
COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT. ITEM 54 IS THE COMPANION
RESOLUTION TO ESTABLISH THE PROPERTY BASED BUSINESS
IMPROVEMENT DISTRICT KNOWN AS THE DOWNTOWN COMMUNITY BENEFIT
DISTRICT ORDERING THE LEVY AND COLLECTION OF ASSESSMENTS
AGAINST PROPERTY LOCATED IN THAT DISTRICT FOR TEN YEARS
COMMENCING WITH FISCAL YEAR 2026 2027 SUBJECT TO CONDITIONS
AS SPECIFIED AND MAKING ENVIRONMENTAL FINDINGS.
>> THE PURPOSE OF THIS COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE IS TO
HEAR TESTIMONY ON THE PROPOSED LEVY OF ASSESSMENTS OF THE
PROPERTY AND BUSINESS IMPROVEMENT DISTRICT AND NAME
THE DOWNTOWN COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT.
PURSUANT TO THE BOARD'S RESOLUTION OF INTENT INTENTION
ADOPTED MAY 19TH, 2026 WHICH SET TODAY'S HEARING DATE
AND ALSO APPROVED THE MANAGEMENT DISTRICT PLAN THE
ENGINEER'S REPORT AND THE FORM OF BALLOTS FOR PROPERTY OWNERS.
DETAILS ON THE COVERED AREA CAN BE FOUND IN THE LEGISLATIVE
FILES. AFTER THE HEARING IS CLOSED,
THE DEPARTMENT OF ELECTIONS WILL COUNT ALL BALLOTS
SUBMITTED INCLUDING ANY ADDITIONAL BALLOTS RECEIVED
DURING THE PUBLIC HEARING TODAY AND SUBMIT THE TABULATION BACK
TO THE BOARD. MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC MAY VIEW
THE BALLOT TABULATION BY THE DEPARTMENT OF ELECTIONS ON THE
BASEMENT LEVEL OF CITY HALL IN ROOM 59.
IF THE TABULATION OF THE WEIGHTED BALLOTS SHOWS A
MAJORITY PROTEST, THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WILL NOT APPROVE
THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE DISTRICT OR IMPOSE THE
ASSESSMENTS. IF THERE IS NOT A MAJORITY
PROTEST THE BOARD MAY THEN VOTE TO ESTABLISH THE DISTRICT
AND IMPOSE THE ASSESSMENTS. A MAJORITY PROTEST WOULD EXIST
IF THE WEIGHTED BALLOTS SUBMITTED IN OPPOSITION TO THE
ESTABLISHMENT OF THE ASSESSMENT DISTRICT EXCEED THE WEIGHTED
BALLOTS SUBMITTED IN FAVOR OF ESTABLISHMENT.
BALLOTS ARE WEIGHTED ACCORDING TO THE PROPOSED FINANCIAL
OBLIGATION OF EACH AFFECTED PROPERTY.
THE HEARING IS NOW OPEN. >> SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MAILMAN AND I WANT TO SAY A FEW REMARKS BEFORE WE
CONTINUE ON WITH THE PROCEEDINGS.
YOU KNOW, I THINK I HAVE THE PLEASURE OF HAVING THE MOST
COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICTS OF ANY DISTRICT IN THE CITY AND IT
IS A REAL HONOR TO WORK WITH DOWNTOWN PARTNERSHIP.
THIS IS A REALLY SPECIAL GROUP OF PEOPLE AND THE WORK THAT
THEY DO IS REALLY PHENOMENAL. THERE'S A FEW THINGS I WANT TO
HIGHLIGHT AND A FEW THINGS THAT I THINK REALLY DESERVE TO BE
RECOGNIZED ABOUT HOW WE'RE DOING THIS.
AND THE FIRST IS THAT THIS IS A PARTNERSHIP MODEL.
THIS IS IN FACT THE FIRST TIME THAT THE PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO
IS OPTING TO JOIN A COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT.
I MEAN I THINK THAT SAYS A LOT ABOUT THE PORT AND PARTICULARLY
THE NEW LEADERSHIP OF OUR NEW DIRECTOR MIKE MARTIN.
>> WE ALSO HAVE REC PARK LOOKING TO WORK WITH THE
COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT PARTICULARLY TO BRING THE NEW
EMBARCADERO PLAZA AND SUE BERRYMAN PARK IMPROVEMENTS TO
LIFE. >> AND YOU KNOW, I THINK AS
YOU'LL HEAR AND AS YOU PROBABLY HAVE HEARD BEFORE, THIS IS A
COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT THAT WAS STOOD UP AT THE BEGINNING
OF THE PANDEMIC THE WORST POSSIBLE TIME BUT ALSO THE TIME
THAT WE REALLY NEEDED YOU THE MOST.
AND YOU HAVE GONE ABOVE AND BEYOND IN SOME OF THE MOST
CHALLENGING YEARS IN OUR CITY BEGINNING WITH THE PANDEMIC
THROUGH THE ECONOMIC RECOVERY AND NOW AS WE'RE STARTING TO
SEE LIGHT ON THE OTHER SIDE OF THINGS IN IT.
YOU KNOW, THIS IS A PROCESS WHERE WE ARE LITERALLY ASKING
PROPERTY OWNERS TO TAX THEMSELVES MORE AND THAT IS A
TALL TASK. BUT DESPITE THAT I'VE HEARD
NOTHING BUT EXCITEMENT AND CONFIDENCE AND TRUST COMING
FROM PROPERTY OWNERS DOWNTOWN. THERE'S A REAL APPETITE
AND EAGERNESS FOR THIS EXPANSION AND YOU KNOW, I THINK
PROPERTY OWNERS HAVE A LOT TO LOOK FORWARD WITH WITH THIS
EXPANSION. THE DOWNTOWN PARTNERSHIP HAS
DONE A FANTASTIC JOB OF WORKING WITH OUR OFFICE AND WITH ALL
THE CITY DEPARTMENTS THROUGH THIS RENEWAL PROCESS.
IT IS AN EARLY RENEWAL WHICH IS EXTREMELY RARE.
BUT AGAIN I THINK IT SPEAKS TO THE AMBITION OF THIS GROUP OF
INDIVIDUALS IN THIS COLLECTIVE BODY HERE NOT ONLY THE CBD BUT
THE CITY DEPARTMENTS THAT I MENTIONED THAT ARE WORKING WITH
. I DO WANT TO DO A FEW SPECIFIC
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS AND RECOGNITIONS.
OF COURSE ROBBIE SAW ROBBIE SILVER, EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF
DOWNTOWN PARTNERSHIP THE FEARLESS LEADER OF THIS
ORGANIZATION, THE STEERING COMMITTEE THAT REALLY DUG INTO
THE WEEDS OF HOW THIS EXPANSION COULD WORK AND AND WILL WORK
BEING DAN KINGSLEY AND THEN CHRIS REESE AS WELL.
>> AND YOU KNOW I MENTIONED SOME OF THE DEPARTMENTS THAT
ARE PARTNERING ON THIS. THERE'S ALSO A LOT OF CORPORATE
PARTNERS, COMMUNITY PARTNERS THAT HAVE STEPPED UP
PARTICULARLY I WANT TO SHOUT OUT B AND AARON FENTON WHO HAVE
BEEN WORKING CLOSELY ON THE EMBARCADERO PLAZA ELEMENT
AND PARK OVERLAY OF THIS AND LASTLY JACKIE HAZELWOOD WHO
HAS DONE A FANTASTIC JOB STEERING THIS FORWARD.
SO I KNOW THERE'S MORE STEPS AND BALLOTS NEED TO BE COUNTED
BUT I REALLY AM CONFIDENT HERE AND LOOK FORWARD TO THIS
EXPANSION AND THANK EVERYONE FOR BRINGING THIS TO THE TABLE
TODAY. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SAUTER I BELIEVE THAT WE HAVE THE MAYOR'S OFFICE
OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT, JACKIE HAZELWOOD
AND THEN THE DOWNTOWN CBD. >> ROBBIE SILVER THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MIDDLEMAN AND GOOD GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS JACKIE HAZELWOOD. I'M THE COMMUNITY BENEFIT
DISTRICT PROGRAM DIRECTOR WITH THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC
AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT. I OVERSEE AND ADMINISTER THE
CBD PROGRAM ON BEHALF OF IWD. I'M JOINED HERE BY CASTILLO
HOLLICK FROM OUR TEAM AS WELL. SO TODAY'S HEARING IS THE
CULMINATION OF A MULTIYEAR PLANNING EFFORT DRIVEN BY THE
DOWNTOWN COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT WHICH DOES BUSINESS AS
DOWNTOWN AS A PARTNERSHIP OR DFP.
THROUGH THIS EFFORT DFP ENGAGED PROPERTY OWNERS, COMMUNITY
STAKEHOLDERS, CITY DEPARTMENTS AND PARTNER AGENCIES TO DEVELOP
THE PROPOSED RENEWAL AND EXPANSION OF THE DISTRICT
PENDING THE RESULTS OF THE FORTHCOMING BALLOT TABULATION
LATER TONIGHT. IF APPROVED, THE RESOLUTION
BEFORE YOU TODAY WOULD AUTHORIZE DE SFP TO CONTINUE
OPERATING FOR A NEW TEN YEAR TERM UNDER AN UPDATED
MANAGEMENT PLAN. BEFORE I INTRODUCE ROBBIE
SILVER, EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF DFP TO PRESENT ON THE
ORGANIZATION'S EFFORT AND THE VISION OF THE PROPOSED RENEW
DISTRICT. I'D ALSO LIKE TO JUST
ACKNOWLEDGE SEVERAL INDIVIDUALS WHOSE WORK HAS SUPPORTED THIS
PROCESS. MY SINCERE THANK YOU TO THE
MAYOR AND TO HIS STAFF PARTICULARLY ADAM SONGS THAT TO
SUPERVISOR SAUTER AND TO HER STAFF PARTICULARLY TO GABEL TO
SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND TO HIS STAFF MADISON TAM TO OUR
DIRECTOR AT AWP AND TOPIA. CHRIS CAUCUS IN CASE YOU
HOLLICK DIRECTOR MIKE MARTIN SCOTLAND'S IT ALL.
AMY COHEN WITH THE PORT DIRECTOR SARAH MADELINE DANA
KETCHUM AND BEP ING WITH RYAN PARK STAFF FROM THE CLERK'S
OFFICE INCLUDING LISA SAMARA, JOHN CARROLL AND MANY CREIGHTON
DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEYS MONEY PYTHON AND HUGO CABRERA.
AND ESPECIALLY KWONG QUACH PRISCILLA TOVE AND ALICE ALICE
LAU WITH THE DEPARTMENT OF ELECTIONS.
THANK YOU ALL FOR YOUR COLLABORATION AND PARTNERSHIP
THROUGH THIS PROCESS. THERE'S A LOT OF FOLKS CLEARLY
THIS TAKES A VILLAGE. I ESPECIALLY NOW LIKE TO
RECOGNIZE SFP EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR ROBBY SILBER AND HIS
STAFF AND SPS BOARD OF DIRECTORS MANY OF WHOM ARE HERE
TODAY FOR THEIR ONGOING SUPPORT THROUGHOUT THIS CAMPAIGN.
SO TURNING NOW TO THE ITEM BEFORE THE BOARD TODAY.
SO THE DOWNTOWN COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT WAS ORIGINALLY
ESTABLISHED BY THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IN 2019 FOR A 15
YEAR TERM BEGINNING ON JANUARY 1ST, 2020 AND WITH THE
INTENTION TO CONTINUE THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST, 2035.
>> ALTHOUGH THE DISTRICT IS NOT REQUIRED TO RETURN RENEW UNTIL
THE END OF THIS TERM FOLLOWING STAKEHOLDER ENGAGEMENT,
PROPERTY OWNER ENGAGEMENT AND APPROVAL BY ITS BOARD OF
DIRECTORS, THE SFP ELECTED TO PURSUE AN EARLY RENEWAL
IN ORDER TO UPDATE THEIR MANAGEMENT PLAN AND ALIGN THEIR
BUDGET SERVICES AND DISTRICT BOUNDARIES WITH THE EVOLVING
NEEDS OF DOWNTOWN. >> IF APPROVED THE RENEWED
DISTRICT WOULD OPERATE UNDER THE PROPOSED MANAGEMENT PLAN AN
EXPANDED SERVICE AREA FOR A NEW TEN YEAR TERM COMMENCING
JANUARY 1ST, 2027 AND ENDING DECEMBER 31ST 2036.
AS ROBBY WILL DISCUSS IN GREATER DETAIL IN A MOMENT,
THE PROPOSAL WOULD EXPAND DISTRICT BOUNDARIES TO INCLUDE
THE FUTURE EMBARCADERO PARK AND PORTIONS OF THE EMBARCADERO
OWNED BY THE PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO.
SO PRIOR TO TODAY'S HEARING THE DISTRICT COMPLETED THE
PROCEDURAL REQUIREMENTS ESTABLISHED ESTABLISHED UNDER
THE CALIFORNIA PROPERTY AND BUSINESS IMPROVEMENT
DISTRICT LAW OF 1994. IN APRIL SFP EXCEEDED THE
REQUIRED 30% THRESHOLD TO INITIATE THE BALLOT PHASE.
THEY SUBMITTED 107 PETITIONS WHICH REPRESENTED JUST OVER $5
MILLION IN ASSESSMENTS OR 40.3% OF THE PROPOSED ASSESSMENT.
FOLLOWING THAT MILESTONE ON MAY 19TH THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
ADOPTED THE RESOLUTION OF INTENTION AUTHORIZING THE
SPECIAL ASSESSMENT BALLOTING PROCESS.
BALLOTS WERE MAILED TO ALL AFFECTED PROPERTY OWNERS ON
JUNE 6TH, OPENING THE REQUIRED 45 DAY BALLOTING PERIOD WHICH
CULMINATES IN TODAY'S SESSION TODAY.
>> THROUGHOUT THIS PROCESS DCEP WORKED CLOSELY WITH NUMEROUS
CITY PARTNERS AS I MENTIONED PARTICULARLY YORK AND PARK
AND THE PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> ON JUNE 30TH THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS AUTHORIZED THE MAYOR TO CAST ASSESSMENT
BALLOTS IN THE AFFIRMATIVE ON BEHALF OF THE CITY AND COUNTY
OF SAN FRANCISCO AND I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT HAVING WAS
HERE EARLIER AND IS ABLE TO ANSWER ANY QUESTIONS SHOULD
THERE BE ANY FOLLOW UPS LATER ON AS THEY COME.
>> ANOTHER IMPORTANT COMPONENT AS HAS BEEN HIGHLIGHTED BY
SUPERVISORS ORDER IS THE INCLUSION OF THE PORT OF SAN
FRANCISCO WITHIN THE DISTRICT BOUNDARIES.
ON JUNE 10TH THE PORT COMMISSION UNANIMOUSLY APPROVED
THE PORT'S PARTICIPATION IN THE PROPOSED DISTRICT.
IF APPROVED TODAY THE EXPANDED DISTRICT WOULD INCLUDE PORT
OWNED PROPERTIES ALONG THE EMBARCADERO WHICH WOULD
REPRESENT APPROXIMATELY $882,000 IN FIRST YEAR
ASSESSMENTS. BEYOND THE FINANCIAL
CONTRIBUTION, THE INCLUSION REFLECTS COORDINATED PLANNING
BETWEEN THE PORT AND DFP TO SUPPORT LONG TERM STEWARDSHIP,
MAINTENANCE AND ACTIVATION ALONG THE WATERFRONT WHILE
STRENGTHENING THE CONNECTION BETWEEN THE EMBARCADERO
AND DOWNTOWN CORE. I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT
SCOTLAND'S ATL AND AMY COHEN FROM THE PORT ARE ALSO PRESENT
IN CHAMBERS. SHOULD THERE BE ANY QUESTIONS
REGARDING THE PORT'S PARTICIPATION?
WITH THAT OVERVIEW I'D NOW LIKE TO INVITE ROBBIE SILVER, THE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF DFP TO PRESENT ON THE PROPOSED RENEWAL
AND EXPANSION. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU JACKIE. GOOD AFTERNOON OR ALMOST
EVENING PRESIDENT OF MANAGEMENT AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS CITY STAFF AND MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC.
THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE TODAY AND ALLOWING US TO PRESENT ON
THIS TOPIC. I TOOK OVER THE ORGANIZATION
IN 2020 AT THE HEIGHT OF THE PANDEMIC AND THIS WAS BEFORE
VACCINES SO IT IS QUITE THE SURREAL EXPERIENCE TO BE UP
HERE TODAY TALKING ABOUT ECONOMIC RECOVERY FOR OUR CITY
AND OUR BELOVED DOWNTOWN. >> THIS EFFORT IS FUNDAMENTALLY
ABOUT ENSURING DOWNTOWN SAN FRANCISCO REMAINS COMPETITIVE
AND ITS PRIMARY TAX BASE TO FUND CITYWIDE SERVICES.
OUR RESILIENT AND POSITIONED FOR LONG TERM RECOVERY
AND GROWTH. OVER THE PAST SEVERAL YEARS OUR
DOWNTOWN HAS FACED UNPRECEDENTED CHALLENGES FROM
THE IMPACTS OF THE PANDEMIC AND SHIFTS IN OFFICE
UTILIZATION TO INCREASING PRESSURE ON PUBLIC REALM
MAINTENANCE, SAFETY AND ECONOMIC VITALITY AND AT
THE SAME TIME EXPECTATIONS FOR CLEAN STREETS, SAFE
ENVIRONMENTS AND VIBRANT PUBLIC SPACES HAVE ONLY INCREASED.
THIS IS THE REALITY THAT PROPERTY OWNERS, BUSINESSES,
RESIDENTS AND VISITORS ARE ASKING FOR MORE SERVICES, MORE
ACTIVATION AND STRONGER COORDINATION THAN EVER
AND EARLY RENEWAL ALLOWS US TO PROACTIVELY RESPOND TO THOSE
NEEDS RATHER THAN WAITING FOR CHALLENGES TO BE RESOLVED ON
THEIR OWN. RENEWAL IS NOT SIMPLY ABOUT
CONTINUING EXISTING SERVICES. IT IS ABOUT EVOLVING THE
DISTRICT'S TO MEET THE FUTURE OF DOWNTOWN EXPANSION ALLOWS US
TO BRING IN ADDITIONAL NEIGHBORHOODS, COMMERCIAL
CORRIDORS AND STAKEHOLDERS TO A UNIFIED STRATEGY FOCUS ON A
CLEAN AND SAFE SERVICES ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT, PUBLIC
SPACE ACTIVATION AND ADVOCACY. DOWNTOWN FUNCTIONS AS AN
INTERCONNECTED ECOSYSTEM AND OUR BOUNDARIES
AND RESOURCES MUST REFLECT THAT .
NEXT SLIDE PLEASE. >> SO THIS IS OUR CURRENT
BOUNDARIES IN IN 2017 A COALITION OF PROPERTY OWNERS
AND BUSINESSES CAME TOGETHER WITH A SIMPLE GOAL CREATE A
CLEANER, SAFER AND MORE WELCOMING DOWNTOWN.
WE OFFICIALLY LAUNCHED OPERATIONS IN JANUARY 2020 JUST
WEEKS BEFORE THE PANDEMIC DRASTICALLY CHANGED THE
TRAJECTORY OF OUR CITY AND THE WORLD.
OVER THE PAST SIX YEARS WE'VE EVOLVED FROM SIMPLY CREATING A
TRADITIONAL CLEAN AND SAFE DISTRICT TO AN ORGANIZATION
FOCUSED ON PLACE MANAGEMENT, ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT, PUBLIC
REALM ACTIVATION AND DOWNTOWN RECOVERY IN ORDER TO RISE TO
POST-COVID CHALLENGES. >> OUR WORK FOCUSES ON THESE
AREAS AS MENTIONED BEFORE AND TOGETHER THESE FUNCTIONS
HELP ENSURE THAT DOWNTOWN REMAINS A PLACE WHERE
BUSINESSES CAN SUCCEED. RESIDENTS CAN THRIVE
AND VISITORS FEEL WELCOME. AND AS FRONT LINE STEWARDS OVER
THE LAST SIX YEARS YOU CAN SEE THESE ARE TANGIBLE RESULTS FROM
OUR AMBASSADOR TEAMS FROM PICKING UP TRASH FILE WASTE
GRAFFITI POWER WASHING EVERYTHING THAT A CBDC IS
DESIGNED TO DO. >> ONE EXAMPLE OF OF OUR
ABILITY TO INNOVATE HAS BEEN OUR PARTNERSHIP WITH THE
DOWNTOWN DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION TO LAUNCH THE
MARKET STREET AMBASSADOR CORRIDOR PILOT.
SINCE THIS PARTNERSHIP MAJOR EMPLOYER CITY AGENCIES
AND COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS HELP FUNDED THE PROGRAM TO
IMPROVE CONDITIONS AROUND OUR DOWNTOWN TRANSIT HUBS SINCE
JUNE AND JULY OF 2025 AMBASSADORS HAVE GENERATED OVER
71,000 PUBLIC INTERACTIONS AND CONTRIBUTED TO A 53%
REDUCTION IN SAFETY RELATED 911 CALLS IN THIS AREA.
THIS PILOT DEMONSTRATES HOW STRATEGIC PRIVATE PUBLIC
PARTNERSHIPS CAN DELIVER MEASURABLE RESULTS.
AND AS DOWNTOWN EVOLVES WE MUST THINK BEYOND MAINTENANCE
AND OPERATIONS. OUR AWARD WINNING PUBLIC REALM
ACTION PLAN PROVIDES A ROADMAP FOR TRANSFORMING DOWNTOWN
STREETS AND PUBLIC SPACES INTO DESTINATIONS THAT SUPPORT
ECONOMIC ACTIVITY, COMMUNITY GATHERING AND CULTURAL
EXCHANGE. THIS PLAN WAS CREATED FROM
INPUT FROM STAKEHOLDERS NOT A TOP DOWN APPROACH BUT RECEIVING
DIRECTIONS DIRECTLY FROM THE COMMUNITY.
>> THESE ARE SOME OF OUR WORK THAT HAS COME OUT OF OUR PUBLIC
REALM ACTION PLAN THAT WE'VE BEEN ABLE TO ACCOMPLISH.
FIRST LANDING AT LIGHT A STAFF THE FRONT STREET ENTERTAINMENT
ZONE, FIRST ENTERTAINMENT ZONE AND THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA.
OUR DOWNTOWN GATEWAY PROJECT AT THE CORNER OF MARKET
AND CALIFORNIA STREET AT THE CABLE CAR LINE AND OF COURSE
MECHANICS MONUMENT PLAZA. >> THESE PROJECTS REPRESENT
WHAT A MODERN DOWNTOWN MANAGEMENT ORGANIZATION LOOKS
LIKE THROUGH STRATEGIC ACTIVATIONS, STREETSCAPE
IMPROVEMENTS AND PRIVATE PUBLIC PARTNERSHIPS.
WE TRANSFORM THESE UNDERUTILIZED SPACES INTO
COMMUNITY ASSETS WHETHER IT'S LANDING AT LIGHT A STORE FRONT
STREET DOWNTOWN GATEWAY OR MECHANICS.
EACH PROJECT DEMONSTRATES HOW THOUGHTFUL PLACEMAKING CAN
INCREASE FOOT TRAFFIC SUPPORT LOCAL BUSINESSES AND INCREASE
DOWNTOWN'S IDENTITY. WE'VE ALSO BECOME A LEADER THAT
ONCE LED IN PRODUCING PUBLIC EVENTS PROGRAMS SUCH AS LET'S
GLOW S.F. THE STEEL ON BELT IN FRONT STREET AND DRAG ME
DOWNTOWN, ATTRACT VISITORS, SUPPORT LOCAL BUSINESSES
AND REINFORCE DOWNTOWN'S REPUTATION AS A CULTURAL
DESTINATION. >> LET'S CLOSE SPECIFICALLY HAS
BROUGHT MORE THAN 375,000 ATTENDEES SINCE IT STARTED
AND 2021 SO THIS BRINGS US TO THE PURPOSE BACK ONLINE.
>> THIS BRINGS US TO THE PURPOSE OF TODAY'S HEARING.
DOWNTOWN SAN FRANCISCO HAS EXPERIENCED RENEWED MOMENTUM
AND RATHER THAN WAIT UNTIL THE END OF OUR CURRENT TERM,
PROPERTY OWNERS CHOSE TO PURSUE AN EARLY RENEWAL APPROXIMATELY
EIGHT YEARS AHEAD OF SCHEDULE BECAUSE THEY BELIEVE DOWNTOWN
RECOVERY CAN AND SHOULD MOVE FASTER.
>> THIS PROPOSAL DESIGNED TO DESIGNED ACCELERATE RECOVERY,
STRENGTHEN THE SERVICE DELIVERY AND EXTEND SUPPORT TO THE
EMBARCADERO WATERFRONT ONE OF SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST IMPORTANT
PUBLIC SPACES. >> WE'VE DONE EXTENSIVE
COMMUNITY OUTREACH OVER THE LAST YEAR AND A HALF.
>> WE ESTABLISHED A RENEWAL AND EXPANSION STEERING
COMMITTEE. WE'VE CONDUCTED FOCUS GROUPS,
HOSTED COMMUNITY MEETINGS, LAUNCHED A DEDICATED WEBSITE
MAILED SURVEYS TO EVERY PROPERTY OWNER AND COMPLETED
NUMEROUS ONE ON ONE INTERVIEWS WITH STAKEHOLDERS THROUGHOUT
THE DISTRICT. WE ALSO COORDINATED EXTENSIVELY
WITH THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT, THE
PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO AND RECREATION AND PARKS.
LOOKS LIKE ONE MORE FIVE PRIMARY GOALS GUIDE THIS
EFFORT. FIRST IS TO STRENGTHEN DOWNTOWN
COMPETITIVE POSITION. SECOND SECURE THE CITY'S TAX
BASE AND INVESTMENTS. THIRD CREATE A STRONGER
PLATFORM FOR ADVOCACY, INVESTMENT AND ECONOMIC GROWTH.
FOURTH, ENHANCE OUR SERVICE DELIVERY AND PROVIDE
OPERATIONAL EXCELLENCE. AND FIFTH SUPPORT THE
ACTIVATION OF THE EMBARCADERO PARK PROJECT.
>> UPON OUR DUE DILIGENCE WE STUDY DOWNTOWNS ACROSS THE
COUNTRY AND FOUND THAT OUR DOWNTOWN HAS HAS ONE OF THE
LOWEST RESOURCES. THIS PROPOSED RENEWAL HELPS
ENSURE THAT SAN FRANCISCO REMAINS COMPETITIVE WITH OTHER
DOWNTOWNS THAT ARE INVESTING HEAVILY INTO THE PUBLIC REALM.
SAFETY ACTIVATION AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT RENEWAL ALLOWS US
TO SIGNIFICANTLY EXPAND SERVICES MOST NOTABLY AS CLEAN
AND SAFE SERVICES WILL DOUBLE AND TRANSITION TO A 24 HOUR
OPERATION. THIS PROPOSAL ALSO FUNDS A NEW
HOMELESS OUTREACH PROGRAM AND OVERNIGHT SAFETY PATROLS.
>> LASTLY, IT ACCELERATES OUR IMPLEMENTATION OF OUR PUBLIC
REALM ACTION PLAN NO LONGER RELYING ON CITY GRANTS BUT
FOCUSING ON THESE EFFORTS TO BOOST BEAUTIFICATION EFFORTS TO
SUPPORT SMALL BUSINESSES AND OUR OVERALL DOWNTOWN
RECOVERY. >> THIS IS THE PROPOSED MAP
THAT EXPANDS BEYOND THE EXISTING FINANCIAL DISTRICT
IN JACKSON SQUARE TO INCLUDE THE EMBARCADERO AND PORT AREAS
FROM 43 TO 70 BLOCKS THREE SERVICE ZONES WILL PROVIDE
FOCUSED DEPLOYMENT OF RESOURCES RATHER THAN A ONE SIZE FITS ALL
APPROACH. THE EXPANSION REFLECTS HOW
PEOPLE ACTUALLY EXPERIENCE DOWNTOWN TODAY AS A CONNECTED
ECOSYSTEM RATHER THAN A COLLECTION OF SEPARATE
NEIGHBORHOODS. DIFFERENT SERVICE ZONES HAVE
BEEN DESIGNATED TO MATCH VARYING SERVICE NEEDS WHILE
ENSURING EQUITABLE INVESTMENT ACROSS THE DISTRICT.
>> THE NEXT TWO SLIDES ILLUSTRATE SPECIFIC SERVICE
IMPROVEMENTS THAT MAKE THIS RENEWAL POSSIBLE AGAIN.
ESSENTIALLY PROPERTIES WILL RECEIVE DOUBLE THE AMOUNT OF
CLEANING AT DOUBLE THE AMOUNT OF POWER WASHING AND DOUBLE THE
AMOUNT OF SAFETY PROGRAMS. IN ADDITION WE WILL CREATE
DEDICATED FUNDING STREAMS DIRECTLY FOR ECONOMIC
DEVELOPMENT ADVOCACY, STREETSCAPE IMPROVEMENTS,
PUBLIC REALM PROGRAMING, DESTINATION MARKETING
AND BUSINESS ATTRACTION EFFORTS .
>> THE PROPOSED METHODOLOGY WAS DEVELOPED THROUGH A TRANSPARENT
PUBLIC PROCESS AND REVIEWED BY OUR ASSESSMENT ENGINEER.
YEAR ONE IS PROJECTED TO GENERATE APPROXIMATELY $11
MILLION IN ASSESSMENTS SUPPORTING AN OVERALL OPERATING
BUDGET OF APPROXIMATELY 11.3 MILLION.
AND YOU CAN SEE THE BREAKDOWN IN OUR MANAGEMENT PLAN BETWEEN
CLEAN AND SAFE AND PLACEMAKING TO SERVE IDENTITY ECONOMIC
DEVELOPMENT AND ADVOCACY AND ADMINISTRATION
AND MANAGEMENT AND CONTINGENCY FUND.
>> NEXT SLIDE. >> A MAJOR COMPONENT OF THIS
PROPOSAL IS THE LONG TERM STEWARDSHIP OF EMBARCADERO
PARK. THIS FIVE ACRE WATERFRONT
WATERFRONT PARK INVESTMENT REPRESENTS ONE OF THE MOST
SIGNIFICANT PUBLIC ROUND PROJECTS IN DOWNTOWN SAN
FRANCISCO'S HISTORY. >> THE PROPOSED PARK OVERLAY
WILL NOT BE ACTIVATED UNTIL THE PARK ASSET IS SUBSTANTIALLY
COMPLETE AND A FORMAL AGREEMENT IS IN PLACE WITH RECREATION
AND PARKS DEPARTMENT. THIS ENSURES SUSTAINABLE
FUNDING FOR PROGRAMING AND ACTIVATION.
IT'S OUR VISION THAT ALL SAN FRANCISCO NEIGHBORHOODS WILL
HAVE A PLACE HERE. APPROXIMATELY $1.8 MILLION WILL
BE RAISED BASED ON THIS PROJECT BASED ON A PROPERTY'S PROXIMITY
TO THE PARK. >> OVER THE PAST YEAR WE'VE
COMPLETED THE STAKEHOLDER OUTREACH, DEVELOPED OUR NEW
MANAGEMENT PLAN, AN ASSESSMENT ENGINEER'S REPORT AND OUR
PETITION PROCESS AND CONDUCTED THE REQUIRED PROPERTY BALLOT
PROCEEDING. AND TODAY REPRESENTS THE FINAL
STEP IN THAT PROCESS. >> IN CLOSING THE COMMUNITY
BENEFIT DISTRICT MODEL HAS CONSISTENTLY DEMONSTRATED
MEASURABLE RESULTS. CLEANER STREETS ENHANCE
HOSPITALITY AND AMBASSADOR SERVICES, STRONGER MARKETING
AND EVENTS AND IMPROVE COORDINATION BETWEEN THE
PRIVATE SECTOR AND THE CITY. BUT PERHAPS MOST IMPORTANTLY
THIS RENEWAL IS ABOUT CONFIDENCE CONFIDENCE FOR
BUSINESSES CONSIDERING WHETHER THEY'LL STAY OR GROW IN SAN
FRANCISCO. CONFIDENCE FOR EMPLOYEES
RETURNING BACK DOWNTOWN. CONFIDENCE FOR VISITORS
RESIDENTS AND INVESTORS THAT DOWNTOWN IS CONTINUING TO MOVE
FORWARD AND WE BELIEVE THIS RENEWAL AND EXPANSION POSITIONS
US NOT ONLY TO MAINTAIN THAT MOMENTUM BUT HELP SHAPE THE
NEXT CHAPTER. I ALSO WANT TO TAKE A MOMENT TO
RECOGNIZE ONE OF OUR FOUNDING MEMBERS, CLINT RILEY, WHO FOR
NOT HIM THIS ORGANIZATION SHOULD WOULD NOT HAVE COME
TOGETHER BACK IN 2017 AND 2018 WHO SADLY PASSED AWAY OVER THE
WEEKEND. AND WE WISH HIS FAMILY ALL THE
BEST DURING THIS TIME. THANK YOU FOR YOUR
CONSIDERATION AND WE'RE HAPPY TO ANSWER ANY QUESTIONS.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AMANDA MANN AND PLEASE HELP ME UNDERSTAND
THAT LOOKS LIKE THE DISTRICT COVERED THE PORT SIDE AND THAT
THE RATE COLLECTED FROM THE PORT SITES UP TO A LITTLE BIT
OVER $800,000 A YEAR. AND SO IT MEANS THAT THE SAN
FRANCISCO PORT IS PAYING INTO THAT, CORRECT?
>> THAT'S CORRECT. IN THIS CASE THE PORT WILL
SERVE AS THE MASTER PROPERTY OWNER BUT DEPENDING ON THEIR
SUBLEASE IS WHAT THEIR TENANTS THEY'LL PROBABLY BE NEGOTIATED
AND THAT THEY CAN PASS ON SOME OF THOSE ASSESSMENTS ONTO THEIR
TENANTS OR SUBLEASES. >> THAT MEANS THE FERRY
BUILDING COULD BE IN THE FERRY BUILDING AND THEN THIS AREA
WE'RE LOOKING THROUGH PIER FIVE AND SEVEN AS WELL.
>> BUT THE DISTRICT THAT YOU CURRENTLY PROPOSE DOES NOT
INCLUDE SILBERMAN PARK OR EMBARCADERO PLAZA.
>> YEAH, OUR CURRENT DISTRICT BOUNDARIES DOES NOT INCLUDE THE
PORT NOR EMBARCADERO AND SUE BERRYMAN PARK.
SO PART OF THIS EXPANSION EFFORT IS MAKING SURE THOSE
PROPERTIES ARE BROUGHT IN AND THERE IS A SUSTAINABLE FUNDING
MODEL FOR PROGRAMING AND ACTIVATION.
>> AND IT ALSO DOES NOT INCLUDE THE IMPACT FEDERAL BUILDINGS
WHICH IS OWNED BY BOSTON PROPERTY CURRENTLY NOT BUT BXP
IS REPRESENTED HERE TODAY AND WILL BE JOINING THE
DISTRICT. >> BUT IT LOOKS LIKE ACCORDING
TO YOUR PROPOSAL THE BENEFITS INCLUSIVE OF THE PARK OVERLAY
MEANING THAT YOU ARE DEDICATED ROUGHLY ABOUT $1.8 MILLION TO
THE PARK MAINTENANCE NOT MAINTENANCE BUT PROGRAMING
AND ACTIVATION. SO AT THE END OF THE DAY REC
AND PARK WILL BE ULTIMATELY RESPONSIBLE FOR MAINTENANCE
AND CLEANLINESS. THIS WILL BE A SUPPLEMENTAL
AND ENHANCE TO WHATEVER THE CITY'S BASELINE SERVICES WILL
BE. >> AND AND THE $1.8 MILLION
ROUGHLY IS NOT GOING TO HAPPEN UNTIL THE RENOVATION IS
COMPLETED. >> CORRECT.
SO THAT THAT WILL NOT BE TRIGGERED NOW AND IT WILL NOT
BE TRIGGERED UNTIL FISCAL YEAR. MOST LIKELY 28 TO 29.
AND WHICH TIME PROPERTY OWNERS WILL BE NOTIFIED OF THE
TRIGGERING WHICH WILL BE UNDER THE AUTHORITY OF OUR BOARD OF
DIRECTORS. AND AGAIN, WE WANT TO MAKE SURE
LIKE THE PARK ITSELF IS SIGNIFICANTLY COMPLETED
AND READY TO RECEIVE THOSE FUNDS AS WELL AS WE HAVE A
SATISFACTORY OPERATIONS AGREEMENT WITH THE REC AND PARK
DEPARTMENT. >> AND THEN WITH THAT WOULD
THAT AGREEMENT WILL HAVE TO COME TO THE BOARD SUPERVISOR
FOR FINAL APPROVAL. I WILL HAVE TO GET BACK TO YOU
ON THAT. I'M NOT SURE ON THAT PROCESS.
>> HEY, SUPERVISOR CHAN. NO, ULTIMATELY IT HAS TO.
>> THE AGREEMENT IS BETWEEN REC AND PARK AND DOWNTOWN
PARTNERSHIP IN TERMS OF THE SPECIFICITY OF THE
PARTICULARITIES OF THE MAINTENANCE AGREEMENT GIVEN THE
FACT THAT THERE'S SOME ASPECTS OF THE PARK THAT AREN'T FULLY
SOLIDIFIED REC AND PARK WAS COMFORTABLE WITH THE FACT THAT
IN THE MANAGEMENT PLAN WHICH IS IN FRONT OF YOU ALL TODAY TO
APPROVE THAT NECESSITATES THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN REC AND PARK
AND DFP ON THESE ITEMS TO BE DETERMINED.
>> BUT HOW I UNDERSTAND THOUGH BECAUSE THE $1.8 MILLION IS
ACTUALLY COMING FROM THE COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT.
AND SO THEN WOULDN'T IT BE AN ASSET TO EXPEND GRANT TO THE
REC AND PARK AND WHICH IS THEN OR ARE YOU SAYING THAT THE CBD
IS ACTUALLY GOING TO BE DOING THE PROGRAMING WORTH $1.8
MILLION WORTH AND AT PARK PROPERTY?
>> THE LATTER PART SO YES THE CBD WOULD BE DOING THE
PROGRAMING ITSELF. AND I SHOULD ALSO NOTE TOO AS A
PART OF BOTH THE PETITION PHASE AND THE BALLOT PHASE ON THE
BALLOT ITSELF THERE'S LANGUAGE INDICATING THE FACT OF THE FACT
THAT PROPERTY OWNERS MAY BE ASSESSED.
AND AS SOON AS FISCAL YEAR 2020 FOR THIS ADDITIONAL ASSESSMENT.
SO THIS WAS CLEAR IN TERMS OF THE BALLOT LANGUAGE ITSELF
AND THE PETITION LANGUAGE ITSELF FOR PROPERTY OWNERS AS
THEY WERE FILLING THAT INFORMATION OUT.
>> I'M JUST A LITTLE BIT CONFUSED BECAUSE AT THE END OF
THE DAY THE DISTRICT THE BENEFIT DISTRICT DOES NOT
INCLUSIVE OF SILBERMAN AND THEN BAGATELLE PLAZA WHICH IS
TOTALLY FINE BECAUSE I WOULD ASSUME REC AND PARK WOULD NOT
WANT TO PAY THE TAX LIKE PORT DOES ESPECIALLY DOES NOT
GENERATE ANY REVENUE LIKE THE PORT WOULD BE WITH FERRY
BUILDING. BUT THEN THE BENEFIT DISTRICT
CAN DECIDE WHAT KIND OF ACTIVITIES AND PROGRAMING GO ON
THE PUBLIC LAND THAT IS WORTH $1.8 MILLION.
I'M JUST A LITTLE BIT CONFUSED. I'M JUST TRYING TO UNDERSTAND
HOW DO WE THEN DETERMINE THAT WHAT KIND OF PROGRAMING WHAT
KIND OF ACTIVITIES WOULD THAT BE GOING ON TO A PUBLIC PARK IF
IF IF REC AND PARK I'M JUST TRYING TO UNDERSTAND THE
JURISDICTION AND JUST DECISION. >> SURE.
SURE. LET ME CLARIFY 11..
SO THE CURRENTLY EMBARCADERO PLAZA AND SUBURBAN PARK ARE NOT
PART OF OUR BOUNDARIES, RIGHT? SO WITH THE EXTENSIVE
CONVERSATIONS WE'VE HAD WITH THE REC AND PARK DEPARTMENT,
THEY'RE AGREEING TO JOIN THE CBD AS A PART OF THIS BALLOT
PROCESS. AND THE ONE ROUGHLY 1.8 MILLION
WILL BE GENERATED THROUGH PROPERTY ASSESSMENTS AS WELL
AND IT'S ACTUALLY BASED ON A FORMULA THAT WE STUDIED WITH
OTHER URBAN PARKS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.
THE CLOSER YOU ARE TO IT URBAN PARK THE LOGICALLY THE MORE
BENEFIT YOU'RE GOING TO GET AND PROBABLY INCREASED VALUE
FOOT TRAFFIC AND THINGS LIKE THAT.
SO THAT'S WHERE WE'VE DEVELOPED THAT FORMULA BASED ON
PROXIMITY. SO NOW THAT HOPEFULLY OUR
BALLOT PROCESS WILL BE APPROVED.
OUR NEXT STEP IS TO WORK WITH REC AND PARK AND WORK WITH
COMMUNITY TO DECIDE HOW SHOULD THIS PARK BE PROGRAMED IN THE
FUTURE. SO THERE THERE'S STILL A LOT TO
FIGURE OUT THERE. WE WANTED TO MAKE SURE AS WE
ARE DOING THIS PROCESS NOW WE COULDN'T GO BACK IN A COUPLE OF
YEARS AND THEN TRY TO DO ANOTHER SPECIAL ASSESSMENT.
SO WE'RE MAKING SURE THAT THAT FUNDING WILL BE THERE IN THE
FUTURE. AND THEN WE ESSENTIALLY HAVE
ABOUT TWO YEARS TO WORK WITH THE DEPARTMENTS AS WELL AS
COMMUNITIES TO AGAIN UNDERSTAND WHAT TYPE OF PROGRAMING.
AND AGAIN OUR VISION IS IS WE WANT THIS PARK TO FEEL LIKE IT
BELONGS TO EVERYBODY IN SAN FRANCISCO AND MAKING SURE THAT
OUR WONDERFUL NEIGHBORHOODS HAVE A PLACE IN DOWNTOWN.
>> MY SENSE IS YOU WILL HAVE TO COME BACK TO THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS FOR FINAL APPROVAL FOR FOR THAT AGREEMENT SIMILAR
TO WHAT WE HAVE DONE AT CRINKLE PARK WHICH IS WITH THE YMCA.
BUT I LOOK FORWARD TO IT. I THINK IT'S A WORTHWHILE
INVESTMENT AND I APPRECIATE THE FACT THAT YOU'RE MAKING PORT
PAY IN TO THE CBD BUT NOT REC AND PARK AND THEN YOU'RE
SPENDING PROGRAMING AND SUPPORT INTO THE PARK TO THE PUBLIC
SPACE WHICH I APPRECIATE. >> THANK YOU.
YOU'RE WELCOME. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT. I DON'T SEE ANYONE ELSE IN THE
QUEUE. SO AT THIS TIME A PROPERTY
OWNER WHO WISHES TO CHANGE THEIR VOTES OR WHO HAS NOT YET
VOTED MAY SPEAK WITH THE DEPARTMENT OF ELECTION STAFF AT
A TABLE JUST OUTSIDE THE LEGISLATIVE CHAMBERS.
THEY CAN PROVIDE YOU WITH THE AFFIDAVIT AND BALLOT.
AND AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT CLOSES THE BALLOTS WILL BE COUNTED.
MADAM CLERK, WE WILL NOW OPEN PUBLIC COMMENT FOR THIS MATTER
AND WE'RE GOING TO GIVE EVERY SPEAKER TWO MINUTES.
>> YES. IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO PROVIDE
COMMENTS ON THE DOWNTOWN CBD ITEMS 5053 AND 54 PLEASE LINE
UP TO SPEAK NOW ON THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER.
ONCE THE IN-PERSON LINE HAS BEEN EXHAUSTED WE WILL GO TO
OUR REMOTE SPEAKERS. IF YOU ANTICIPATE PROVIDING
REMOTE PUBLIC COMMENT THE TELEPHONE NUMBER AND MEDIA
NIGÉRIA PUBLISHED ON THE AGENDA AND STREAMING ON YOUR SCREEN.
THE FIRST PUBLIC COMMENTS ARE HERE IN PERSON PLEASE COME
FORWARD. >> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS CATALINA. I AM WITH THE TRANSGENDER
DISTRICT AND WE HAVE THE PRIVILEGE OF BEING THE
BENEFICIARY COMMUNITY PARTNER WITH DOWNTOWN SAN FRANCISCO
WITHIN THEIR PRIDE EVENTS. >> WE ARE HERE TO SUPPORT THIS
INITIATIVE BUT ALSO TO HIGHLIGHT THE IMPACT THAT THESE
THREE YEARS OF PARTNERSHIP THAT WE'VE HAD WITH THEM HAS ON NOT
ONLY OUR COMMUNITY BUT ALSO THE DOWNTOWN.
SAN FRANCISCO AREA AND MID-MARKET CORRIDOR WHICH
IS WHERE WE PREDOMINANTLY WORK .
>> WE'RE SUPER FORTUNATE OF THIS OPPORTUNITY BECAUSE
IN BEING IN THESE EVENTS WE'VE WE'VE PROGRESSIVELY SEEN MORE
AND MORE ENGAGEMENT AND THROUGH THAT FOLKS THAT ARE BRINGING
THEIR FAMILIES AND BRINGING IN JOY AND EXPANDING UPON THAT
DURING THIS TIME AND WE BELIEVE THAT THIS IS AN INITIATIVE THAT
SAN FRANCISCO SHOULD INVEST INTO BECAUSE THIS IS WHAT SAN
FRANCISCO IS KNOWN FOR MORE SO BRINGING IN COMMUNITY
AND AMPLIFYING JOY BETWEEN GENERATIONS AND PEOPLE WITHIN
THE BAY AREA. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER GOOD EVENING.
I'M CHRIS FRIIS OF RED CO AND HARRINGTON SO I HAVE THE
LUXURY OF BEING BOTH A PROPERTY OWNER IN THE DISTRICT.
I CURRENTLY OWN FOUR BUILDINGS ABOUT 700,000FT2 AND ALSO BEING
A SMALL BUSINESS OWNER SO I CAN SPEAK TO MY EXPERIENCES WITH
CTS-V AND I AM VERY EXCITED TO SUPPORT AND I'VE ALSO PLAYED A
ROLE IN THE RENEWAL STEERING COMMITTEE HERE WITH MY PARTNER
DAN KINGSLEY. SO I'M I'M OFFERING UP MY
SUPPORT AND ANY SORT OF FURTHER QUESTIONS FOR THE BOARD BUT I
BELIEVE WE'RE IN GREAT HANDS AND WE'RE EXCITED TO SEE THIS
MOVE FORWARD SO THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER GOOD EVENING PRESIDENT MADAM AND MEMBERS OF
THE BOARD SUPERVISOR SOUDER THANKS FOR THE SHOUT OUT.
MY NAME IS AARON FENTON AND I REPRESENT PXP.
WE OWN AND MANAGE THE EMBARCADERO CENTER WHICH IS THE
LARGEST OFFICE RETAIL AND PUBLIC GATHERING SPACE
IN DOWNTOWN SAN FRANCISCO. I'M HERE TODAY TO EXPRESS BXP
SUPPORT FOR THE RENEWAL AND EXPANSION OF THE S.F.
DOWNTOWN S.F. PARTNERSHIP. EMBARCADERO CENTER WAS NOT PART
OF THE ORIGINAL BID BECAUSE MOST OF THE SERVICES THAT THE
BID PROVIDED WAS SOMETHING THAT WE ALREADY DID OURSELVES.
HOWEVER, AFTER SEEING THE BENEFITS THE BID PROVIDES TO
THE FINANCIAL DISTRICT FROM ITS STREET CLEANING CREWS TO ITS
PUBLIC REALM ACTIVATIONS, WE ULTIMATELY AGREED TO JOIN THE
DISTRICT BUT NOT ONLY TO JOIN THE DISTRICT BUT TO SUPPORT ITS
EXPANSION BECAUSE WE BELIEVE THESE SERVICES ARE BEING
PROPOSED ARE CRITICAL TO THE RECOVERY OF DOWNTOWN AS
PROPERTY OWNERS AND LONG TERM INVESTORS WE KNOW FIRSTHAND
THAT DOWNTOWN SUCCESS DEPENDS ON MORE THAN JUST BUILDINGS.
IT DEPENDS ON HAVING CLEAN STREETS A SAFE ENVIRONMENT,
STRONG NEIGHBORHOOD IDENTITY AND HIGH QUALITY PUBLIC SPACES
AND CONSISTENT PROGRAMING THAT BRINGS PEOPLE TOGETHER.
AND THESE ARE EXACTLY THE TYPE OF SUPPLEMENTAL SERVICES THAT
THE DOWNTOWN AS A PARTNERSHIP PROVIDES.
WE'RE PARTICULARLY SUPPORTIVE OF THE PARTNERSHIP'S ROLE
IN HELPING ACTIVATE AND MAINTAIN THE FUTURE
EMBARCADERO PARK B P IS CURRENTLY LEADING THE
DEVELOPMENT OF THIS TRANSFORMATIONAL WATERFRONT
IN PARTNERSHIP WITH THE CITY AND WE KNOW THAT SUCCESSFUL
URBAN PARKS AROUND THE COUNTRY THAT GREAT PUBLIC SPACES
REQUIRE ONGOING STEWARDSHIP ACTIVATION AND CLEANLINESS,
SAFETY AND PROGRAMING TO REACH THEIR FULL POTENTIAL.
SAN FRANCISCO IS MAKING A SIGNIFICANT INVESTMENT
IN DOWNTOWN'S FUTURE INCLUDING THE PARK THE DOWNTOWN ASSET
PARTNERSHIP IS THE ORGANIZATION THAT WILL HELP ENSURE THOSE
INVESTMENTS SUCCEED LONG TERM WAY AFTER THE RIBBON CUTTING.
SO FOR THAT REASON BXP STRONGLY SUPPORTS THE RENEWAL
AND EXPANSION. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER HELLO MY NAME IS
EMILY XU AND I'M SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF THE ACLU OF NORTHERN
CALIFORNIA, A PROPERTY OWNER IN THE DISTRICT.
>> WE HAVE THREE OVERARCHING QUESTIONS ABOUT THE NEARLY 70%
OF THE PROPOSED BUDGET ALLOCATED TOWARDS CLEAN, SAFE
AND PLACEMAKING AND GOALS. >> FIRSTLY, THE PLAN PROPOSES
TO INCREASE SAFETY PATROLS AND SO WE ASK WHO WILL CONDUCT
THESE PATROLS? HOW AND WILL SAN FRANCISCO
POLICE DEPARTMENT BE INVOLVED? WHERE WILL THESE PATROLS ADD TO
THE EXISTING POLICING IN THE DISTRICT?
>> SECONDLY, THE PROPOSED DISTRICT BUDGET INCLUDES A
QUOTE INTEGRATED NETWORK OF SECURITY CAMERAS.
>> SO WE ASK WHO WILL HAVE ACCESS TO THIS FOOTAGE?
>> HOW WILL IT BE USED AND MANAGED?
AN IMPORTANTLY HOW WILL THE PRIVACY RIGHTS OF THOSE
CAPTURED ON CAMERA BE PROTECTED ?
>> AND FINALLY THE BUDGET PROPOSES FUNDING FOR HOMELESS
OUTREACH AND SO WE ASK WHAT WILL THIS CONSIST OF?
WELL, THE DISTRICT'S PLAN OFFERED GENUINE ACCESS TO
RESOURCES AND SERVICES OR SIMPLY COMPEL UNHOUSED PEOPLE
TO TAKE UP RESIDENCE ON THE STREETS OUTSIDE THE DISTRICT.
SO WE LOOK FORWARD TO CLARIFICATION ON THESE POINTS.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE. >> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS SHADI KAILA. >> I'M COUNSEL AT EMPIRE
AND WE'RE WITHIN THE DISTRICT. I'M HERE ON BEHALF OF EMPIRE TO
EXPRESS OUR STRONG SUPPORT FOR THE EXPANSION OF THE COMMUNITY
COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT. THERE ARE FEW INITIATIVES THAT
WE AS A COMPANY CONTRIBUTE TO FINANCIALLY THAT SO
IMPRESSIVELY INVISIBLY DELIVER ON THEIR PROMISES.
THE STAFF OF THE COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT ARE A FRIENDLY
FACE AT EACH CORNER BEAUTIFYING, ASSISTING,
INFORMING AND KEEPING SAFE THE COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHEN WE CALL
DC ASSAF P'S THERE IN A TIMELY MANNER WHETHER IT'S CLEAN TRASH
POWER WASH SURROUNDING SIDEWALKS, GRAFFITI REMOVAL OR
OTHERWISE. THEY'RE THERE AND THEY DELIVER
AND WHAT THIS DOES FOR THE CONTINUING NARRATIVE OF SAN
FRANCISCO AS A RESURGING CLEAN, SAFE CITY IS IMMEASURABLE.
THEY'RE GREAT PARTNERS TO US AND THE CITY AT LARGE.
WE'RE ALSO PARTICIPANTS IN AND SPONSORS OF LIGHTS GLOW ASSAF
WE BELIEVE IT'S ONE OF THE MORE UNIQUE PROGRAMS WE HAVE IN THIS
CITY BRINGING JOY AND BEAUTY TO THIS CITY DURING THE HOLIDAY
SEASON. AND IT'S A SMALL EXAMPLE OF
WHAT THIS COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT CAN DO AND GIVEN THE
RESOURCES THAT IT NEEDS. >> DOWNTOWN S.F. PARTNERSHIP
SHOULD BE MARKETED AS ONE OF THE GREATER BENEFITS OF HAVING
A BUSINESS WITHIN THE DISTRICT. IT'S THAT COMPELLING OF A
BENEFIT THAT I BELIEVE IT WOULD ACTUALLY INCENTIVIZE BUSINESSES
TO LOCATE WITHIN OR REMAIN WITHIN THE DISTRICT.
I URGE YOU TO VOTE TO EXPAND THE DOWNTOWN COMMUNITY BENEFIT
DISTRICT. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI THERE. I'M RANDY HELDER.
I REPRESENT GENSLER WHICH IS THE LARGEST ARCHITECTURE
AND DESIGN FIRM IN THE WORLD FOUNDED HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO
IN 1965. WE WERE ONE OF THE FIRST
EMPLOYERS IN THE WAKE OF THE PANDEMIC TO BRING OUR EMPLOYEES
BACK TO THE OFFICE FIVE DAYS A WEEK WHEN WE MOVED INTO OUR NEW
LOCATION AT 220 MONTGOMERY STREET.
NOW SO WHEN WE WERE DOING THAT THE EFFORTS OF THE DOWNTOWN AS
A PARTNERSHIP BEEN KEEPING OUR DOWNTOWN SAFE AND CLEAN WERE
ABSOLUTELY VITAL TO OUR EMPLOYEES FEELING SAFE, FEELING
PROUD TO BE IN THE OFFICE FIVE DAYS A WEEK NOW THAT WE FIND
OURSELVES IN THE FORTUNATE POSITION OF BEING IN AN
ECONOMIC UPSWING. THE EXPANSION AND RENEWAL IS
ABSOLUTELY CRITICAL TO KIND OF CONTINUING THAT UPSWING
BRINGING TOGETHER THE NEW NEWLY EXPANDED DISTRICT, CREATING
CONSISTENCY IN EXPERIENCES FOR OUR VISITORS, OUR CLIENTS WHO
ARE COMING TO SAN FRANCISCO TO MAKE BIG INVESTMENTS IN OUR
CITY AND OUR STATE. HAVING THAT CONSISTENT
EXPERIENCE BETWEEN THE WATERFRONT AND THE DOWNTOWN
WITH THE PLACEMAKING EFFORTS IN ADDITION TO THE CLEAN
AND SAFE PROGRAM IS ABSOLUTELY VITAL AND SO WE AS A LARGE
EMPLOYER IN THE DISTRICT ABSOLUTELY SUPPORT
AND ENCOURAGE YOU ALL TO VOTE TO SUPPORT THIS RENEWAL
AND EXPANSION. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> NEXT SPEAKER.
>> >> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS AND PRESIDENT MENDELSOHN.
MY NAME IS DREW CONNELLY. I'M THE GENERAL MANAGER OF
GALLERY PARK HOTEL AND THE FINANCIAL DISTRICT SINCE 2024.
>> I'M HERE TO SUPPORT THE RENEWAL AND EXPANSION OF THE
DOWNTOWN S.F. PARTNERSHIP. >> JUST LAST MONTH IN JUNE THE
HOTEL REACHED A MAJOR MILESTONE WHERE WE EXCEEDED THE JUNE OF
2019 IN OUR OCCUPANCY. THAT'S THE FIRST METRIC THAT
WE'VE EXCEEDED THAT SINCE THE PANDEMIC.
>> AND EVEN THOUGH IT'S JUST ONE MEASURE OF A HOTEL'S HEALTH
,EVERY OCCUPIED ROOM REPRESENTS SOMEONE WHO CHOSE
SAN FRANCISCO. THEY COULD HAVE HELD THEIR
MEETINGS ELSEWHERE. THEY COULD HAVE TAKEN A
DIFFERENT VACATION. BUT THEY CAME HERE WHO WALKED
OUR STREETS, EAT IN OUR RESTAURANTS, VISITED OUR
BUSINESSES AND FORMED AN OPINION THAT THEY'LL TAKE HOME
WITH THEM. WHEN I ARRIVED HERE IN 2020 FOR
THE HOTEL I'D MISSED ITS BUDGET EVERY MONTH FOR THE PAST YEAR.
THE OWNERS HAD SOME SOME SERIOUS CONCERNS ABOUT THE LONG
TERM FUTURE OF THE HOTEL. IN 2025 WE INCREASED BY 20%
AND THEN IN 2026 WERE FORECASTED TO INCREASE BY 20%
AGAIN. I'M VERY PROUD OF THOSE RESULTS
BUT I DON'T THINK THEY BELONG ONLY TO US.
IT'S AN INDICATOR THAT PEOPLE ARE CHOOSING DOWNTOWN SAN
FRANCISCO AGAIN AND WE CAN SEE THAT CONFIDENCE RETURNING
IN FORMERLY EMPTY STOREFRONT IS COMING BACK TO LIFE AND SMALL
BUSINESSES ACROSS THE DOWNTOWN INCLUDING SEVERAL AROUND
GALLERIA PARK IN CONVERSATIONS WITH HOTEL OWNERS
AND COMMERCIAL REAL ESTATE LEADERS AS WELL.
THEY'RE ACTIVELY LOOKING FOR OPPORTUNITIES TO INVEST IN SAN
FRANCISCO AGAIN AND THAT'S A REMARKABLE AND HARD EARNED
SHIFT FROM JUST A FEW YEARS AGO.
>> THIS RENEWAL WILL BUILD ON THAT MOMENTUM.
>> OVER THE PAST TWO YEARS RENEWED COLLABORATION BETWEEN
THE CITY, LOCAL BUSINESSES AND ORGANIZATIONS LIKE DOWNTOWN
S.F. PARTNERSHIP HAS BECOME TO TO HAS BEGUN TO CHANGE HOW
PEOPLE EXPERIENCE DOWNTOWN. CLEANLINESS, SAFETY,
BEAUTIFICATION AND ACT OF PUBLIC SPACES MAY SOUND LIKE A
SEPARATE EFFORTS BUT TO A VISITOR THEY ARE ALL PART OF
ONE EXPERIENCE. AND THAT'S WHY THE DOWNTOWN
S.F. PARTNERSHIP MATTERS SO MUCH.
AND PROJECTS LIKE THE EMBARCADERO PARK ARE IMPORTANT
FOR THAT EFFORT TO CONTINUE THIS EXTRAORDINARY MOMENTUM.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD EVENING.
I'M JOHN DUNLAP, THE RESIDENTIAL MEMBER OF THE BOARD
OF DIRECTORS OF THE PARTNERSHIP .
I'VE BEEN ON THE BOARD ABOUT FOUR YEARS.
I'VE LIVED IN THE DISTRICT FOR ABOUT EIGHT AND I CAN'T IMAGINE
NOT HAVING THIS PARTNERSHIP IN EXISTENCE TO HELP KEEP THE
STREETS SAFE AND CLEAN. THE KEY THING FOR THE RESIDENTS
OF THE DISTRICT IS TO MAKE SURE THAT IT'S SAFE, IT'S CLEAN,
THAT THERE'S INFRASTRUCTURE AROUND TO SUPPORT THAT.
I'VE SERVED ON A LOT OF BOARDS AND COMMISSIONS IN MY CAREER
AND THIS IS ONE OF THE MOST INCLUSIVE FORWARD THINKING
AND AGGRESSIVE RELATIVE TO MISSION ORGANIZATIONS I'VE EVER
BEEN INVOLVED WITH. THE STAFF IS INCREDIBLE KIND,
AGGRESSIVE AS I MENTIONED AND DOING ALL THAT THEY CAN TO
SERVICE THE DISTRICT. I APPRECIATED JOINING THE BOARD
ABOUT FOUR YEARS AGO AS THE ONLY RESIDENTIAL MEMBER OF THE
BOARD. I FELT I'VE HAD A VOICE, I'VE
BEEN HEARD AND THAT I'VE BEEN ABLE TO GET ACCESS TO RESOURCES
FOR RESIDENTS TO BE ABLE TO HAVE AN ENVIRONMENT THAT
SUPPORTS A TERRIFIC LIVING ENVIRONMENT.
ADDITIONALLY I WANTED TO MENTION HOW IMPORTANT IT IS FOR
PUBLIC SPACE INVESTMENT AND SUPPORTING ECONOMIC
RECOVERY AND I THINK THE PLAN AND THE INCLUSIVE NATURE OF
THIS ORGANIZATION IS GOING TO MAKE THAT HAPPEN AND GROW
CONTINUING INVESTMENT INTO THIS DISTRICT IS IMPORTANT.
AS WE ALL KNOW, THE DOWNTOWN NEEDS TO BE VIBRANT AND SAFE
AND I THINK THIS THIS EFFORT, THIS PARTNERSHIP MAKES THAT
HAPPEN. SO I'D URGE ALL OF YOU TO
SUPPORT THE RENEWAL AND EXPANSION OF THIS
PARTNERSHIP. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI, I'M A RESIDENT OF D SIX. I LIVE ON MARKET STREET
IN MID-MARKET. HAVE SINCE THE SUMMER OF 2021
WITH MY WIFE WHO'S A TRANSGENDER WOMAN AND MYSELF
NON-BINARY PERSON ALSO AND YOU KNOW I JUST IT JUST SOUNDS LIKE
AND FROM EVERYTHING I HAVE READ JUST THIS IS FOR BUSINESSES
THIS ISN'T IT FOR LIKE HOMELESS PEOPLE AND GETTING BACK TO
THEIR ECONOMIC RECOVERY OR POOR PEOPLE AND MAKING SURE DOWNTOWN
AND SAN FRANCISCO IN GENERAL IS AFFORDABLE FOR THEM.
>> I APPRECIATE THE COMMENTER WHO TALKED ABOUT WHAT THOSE
HOMELESS OUTREACH MEAN WHAT DO SAFE STREETS AND HOW THAT AS A
PD MEAN BECAUSE FOR ME MY WIFE AND I EXPERIENCE HAVE BEEN
EXPERIENCING A WORSENING QUALITY IN DOWNTOWN SAN
FRANCISCO WHERE NOW WE HAVE SF DOES A SPEEDY PRESENCE HAS
INCREASED INCREDIBLY OVER THE LAST SEVERAL YEARS AND NOW
EVERY NIGHT WE HAVE MULTIPLE S.F. PD SUVS WITH THEIR LIGHTS
ON PARKED DIRECTLY LIKE IN FRONT OF OUR DOORS.
WE NOW ARE READING ABOUT THE DRONE SURVEILLANCE THAT IS
HAPPENING MORE TIMES THAN WE'RE AWARE OF BECAUSE THEY'RE SO
HIGH IN THE SKY. WE ARE HUMAN EYES CANNOT SEE
THEM BUT THEY CAN SEE US AND AS TRANS PEOPLE LIVING IN SAN
FRANCISCO WHICH IS SUPPOSED TO BE LIKE ONE OF THE SAFE HAVENS
IN THIS COUNTRY THAT IS NOT A COMFORTING THOUGHT AT ALL.
BEING SURVEILLED BY CPD IS NOT COMFORTING.
I'LL SEEING HOMELESS PEOPLE BEING HARASSED TO MOVE ALONG
AND THEIR CIVIL RIGHTS CIVIL RIGHTS BROKEN AND THE
DEPARTMENT PUBLIC WORKS JUST HARASSING THEM SFPD TERRORIZING
THEM, THE SIDEWALKS CONSTANTLY BEING CLEANED TO KEEP DRUGS OFF
OF THEM AND KEEP PEOPLE OFF THEM.
>> AND IT'S IT'S TERRIBLE FOR ME.
>> SO WHATEVER. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. SEE NO OTHER INDIVIDUALS HERE
IN PERSON. WE WILL BE MOVING ON TO THE
REMOTE CALL IN LINE IF YOU HAVE NOT ALREADY DONE SO PLEASE
PRESS STAR THREE TO LINE UP TO SPEAK REMOTELY AS I PREVIOUSLY
STATED. PERSONAL ATTACKS, HARASSMENT OR
DISCRIMINATORY REMARKS WILL RESORT RESULT IN THE SPEAKER
FORFEITING THE REMAINING TIME AND WE WILL BE MOVING ON TO THE
NEXT SPEAKER. >> LET'S HEAR FROM THE FIRST
CALLER. >> ALL RIGHT.
IT SOUNDS LIKE THAT NOW WE STARTED TALKING ABOUT YOUR
TARGET FACT. >> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT,
DID I MENTION THE CALIFORNIA STATE LEGISLATURE?
THANK YOU GUYS. >> PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED
. >> ALL RIGHT.
SO NOW THIS HEARING HAS BEEN HELD AND IS NOW FILED.
>> THE BALLOTS ARE GOING TO BE TABULATED.
>> WE WILL RETURN TO ITEM 54 AFTER THE DEPARTMENT OF
ELECTIONS REPORTS THE RESULTS. AND THAT I THINK MADAM CLERK
TAKES US BACK TO ITEM 441 41 PLEASE CALL ITEM 41.
>> YES. ITEM 41 IS AN ORDINANCE
AMENDING THE POLICE CODE TO REPEAL THE PROHIBITION ON
CERTAIN TYPES OF LIBRARIES LENDING OR RENTING ANY BOOK
MAGAZINE PAMPHLET OR OTHER PRINTED MATTER TO ANY PERSON
UNDER THE AGE OF 21 UNLESS A PERSON HAS OBTAINED A
MEMBERSHIP CARD WITH THE CONSENT OF A PARENT OR LEGAL
GUARDIAN. >> SUPERVISOR WONG WE'RE NOT
TIMING SUPERVISOR WONG I DON'T THINK.
>> COLLEAGUES, THIS ORDINANCE ALSO COMES BEFORE THE FULL
BOARD WITH THE RECOMMENDATION OF PUBLIC SAFETY NEIGHBORHOOD
SERVICES COMMITTEE. THIS MEASURE IS PART OF MY
OFFICE'S BROADER EFFORT TO CLEAN UP OUTDATED PROVISIONS
IN SAN FRANCISCO'S CODES INCLUDING THROUGH OUR DUMB LAWS
CONTEST THE LAW CONCERNS CIRCULATING LIBRARIES PRIVATE
BUSINESSES THAT RENTED BOOKS AND OTHER PRINTED MATERIALS.
>> THIS INDUSTRY DISAPPEARED LONG AGO BEFORE BLOCKBUSTER
CAME ALONG AND NOW BLOCKBUSTER ITSELF HAS GONE BEEN GONE LONG
ENOUGH TO INSPIRE NOSTALGIA. YET SAN FRANCISCO IS STILL
REGULATING UNDER THE CURRENT POLICE CODE A CIRCLING LIBRARY
CAN NOT LEND A BOOK, MAGAZINE PAMPHLET OR OTHER PRINTED
MATERIAL TO ANYONE UNDER 21 UNLESS THEY HAVE A MEMBERSHIP
CARD APPROVED BY A PARENT OR GUARDIAN IN WRITING SIGNED
IN PERSON AND WITNESSED BY THE LIBRARIAN.
SO UNDER THIS LAW A 20 YEAR OLD COULD VOTE SERVING MILITARY
WORK FULL TIME AND GET MARRIED BUT WOULD STILL NEED PARENTAL
PERMISSION TO RENT A BOOK. REPEALING THIS LAW DOES NOT
AFFECT OUR PUBLIC LIBRARIES OR REMOVE ANY ANY MEANINGFUL
PROTECTION. IT SIMPLY REMOVES A REQUIREMENT
TIED TO A BUSINESS MODEL THAT HAS BEEN OBSOLETE FOR
GENERATIONS. GOOD GOVERNMENT MEANS NOT ONLY
PASSING NEW LAWS BUT OCCASIONALLY ADMITTING THAT
SOME OLD ONES ARE IN FACT NOT USEFUL ANYMORE.
I THINK SUPERVISOR SNYDER AND CHERYL FOR CO-SPONSORING
THIS ORDINANCE AND I RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR YOUR
SUPPORT MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL IN THIS ITEM
AND ITEM 41 SUPERVISOR ARE CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON I. SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHAN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I.
AMENDMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR
I THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING PLEASE CALL ITEM 40 TWO ITEM NUMBER 42
IS AN ORDINANCE AMENDING THE HEALTH CODE TO REPEAL THE
PROHIBITION ON TRANSPORTING BREAD IN OPEN BASKETS OR
CONTAINERS ON CITY STREETS. THE PROHIBITION ON SELLING
UNSTERILIZED RAGS AND OTHER TYPES OF CLOTH TO BE USED FOR
CLEANING AND THE PROHIBITION ON OPERATING A LAUNDRY FOR
STERILIZING SUCH RAGS WITHOUT A PERMIT.
>> SUPERVISOR WONG COLLEAGUES THIS ORDINANCE ALSO COMES
BEFORE THE FULL BOARD OF THE RECOMMENDATION OF THE PUBLIC
SAFETY AND NEIGHBORHOOD SERVICES COMMITTEE.
LIKE IN THE PREVIOUS ITEM IT GREW OUT OF OUR DUMB LAWS
CONTEST AND AS PART OF MY OFFICE'S BROAD EFFORT TO CLEAN
UP OUTDATED PROVISIONS IN SAN FRANCISCO'S CODES, THIS
ORDINANCE REPEALS TWO SETS OF OLD HEALTH CODES THE FIRST
PROHIBITS TRANSPORTING BREAD CAKE OR PASTRIES THROUGH CITY
STREETS IN OPEN BASKETS EXPOSED CONTAINERS OR EXPOSED VEHICLES
. >> THIS PROVISION APPEARS TO
COME FROM AN ERA WHEN SAN FRANCISCO WAS CONFRONTING VERY
REAL CONCERNS ABOUT DISEASE CONTAMINATION AND EVEN PLAGUE.
THOSE CONCERNS WERE NOT SILLY AT THAT TIME BUT TODAY WE HAVE
MODERN DAY FOOD SAFETY LAWS AND RESIDENTS SHOULD NOT HAVE
TO WONDER WHETHER CARRYING AN EXPOSED BAGEL DOWN THE STREET
COULD BECOME A PUBLIC HEALTH VIOLATION OR MAKE YOU AN
OUTLAW. THE SECOND SET OF PROVISIONS
REGULATES INDUSTRIAL WIPING WAX WITH DETAILED RULES FOR
STERILIZATION, INSPECTION LABELING AND SPECIAL LAUNDRY
PERMITS. AGAIN WORKPLACE ANNOTATION IS
IMPORTANT BUT THOSE PROTECTIONS ARE NOW COVERED BY MODERN STATE
AND FEDERAL STANDARDS. WE DO NOT NEED OUTDATED LOCAL
PROVISIONS THAT LEAVE PEOPLE WONDERING WHETHER WASHING YOUR
CAR WITH DIRTY RAGS MIGHT TRIGGER A MUNICIPAL WIPING RAG
VIOLATION. REPEALING THESE PROVISIONS DOES
NOT WEAKEN PUBLIC HEALTH PROTECTIONS OR CREATE AN
ENFORCEMENT GAP BUT SIMPLY REMOVES AN OVERLY SPECIFIC
RULES THAT HAVE LONG SINCE BEEN REPLACED BY MODERN STANDARDS.
GOOD GOVERNMENT MEANS PASSING LAWS WHEN THEY'RE NEEDED
AND RECOGNIZING WHEN THEY'RE NO LONGER NEEDED.
I THINK SUPERVISOR CHERYL FOR CO-SPONSORING THIS ORDINANCE
AND I RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR HER SUPPORT.
>> THANK YOU. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 43 TO
40 FIVE TOGETHER. >> YES.
ITEMS 43 TO 40 5 OR 3 RESOLUTIONS DETERMINING THE
ISSUANCE OF OR TRANSFER OF A LIQUOR LICENSE WILL SERVE THE
PUBLIC INCONVENIENCE OR NECESSITY OF THE CITY
AND IMPOSING CONDITIONS ON THE ISSUANCE OF THE LICENSES.
ITEM 43 IS A TYPE 42 ON SALE BEER AND WINE PUBLIC PREMISES
LIQUOR LICENSE TO THE LOVE POTION LIBRARY LLC LOCATED AT
284 SNOWY STREET. ITEM 44 IS A PERSON TO PERSON
PREMISE DEPARTMENT'S TRANSFER OF A TYPE 21 OFF SALE GENERAL
BEER, WINE AND DISTILLED SPIRITS LIQUOR LICENSE TO DEL
RIO PRODUCE MARKET INC DOING BUSINESS THE DEL RIO PRODUCE
MARKET LOCATED AT 2214 CLEMENT STREET AND ITEM 45 IS A PERSON
TO PERSON PREMISE TO PROVINCE TRANSFER OF A TYPE 20 OFF SALE
BEER AND WINE LIQUOR LICENSE TO FOOD FOLK LLC DOING BUSINESS AS
FOOD FOLK LOCATED AT 210 ELEMENTARY AND WE CAN TAKE
THOSE ITEMS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 46.
>> ITEM NUMBER 46 IS A MOTION APPROVING THE MAYORAL
APPOINTMENT OF JAMES PAPPAS TO THE REDEVELOPMENT SUCCESSOR
AGENT OF AGENCY OVERSIGHT BOARD TERM ENDING JANUARY 24TH, 2013.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL THE MOTION WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
MOTION IS APPROVED. MADAME CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
47. >> ITEM 47 IS A MOTION
APPROVING THE MAYOR'S NOMINATION FOR THE
REAPPOINTMENT OF LIEUTENANT LEONARD POGGIO TO THE
ENTERTAINMENT COMMISSION TERM ENDING JULY 1ST, 2013.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ADAM
NUMBER 48 ITEM 40 EIGHT IS A MOTION APPROVING THE MAYOR'S
NOMINATION FOR THE REAPPOINTMENT OF PAUL WOOLFORD
TO THE PUBLIC WORKS COMMISSION FOR A TERM ENDING JULY 2ND,
2013. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
PLEASE CALL 49 ITEM 49 AS A MOTION APPROVING THE MAYOR'S
NOMINATION FOR APPOINTMENT OF VANESSA HARTIGAN TO THE PORT
COMMISSION. TERM ENDING MAY 1ST 2030.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. >> PLEASE CALL ITEM 50.
ITEM 50 IS A MOTION APPOINTING ROBERT EATON GAIL GEARY
CATHERINE AND MILLER CHRISTOPHER INGRAM RESIDENCY
REQUIREMENT WAIVED AND BRANDON BRACAMONTES RESIDENCY
REQUIREMENT WAIVED FOR A ONE FOR ONE YEAR TERMS BEGINNING
UPON THE COUNCIL'S FIRST MEETING TO THE FIRE CODE
TECHNICAL ADVISORY COMMITTEE. >> SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
>> AND LET'S GO TO OUR COMMITTEE REPORTS PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 57. >> I WILL START WITH ITEMS 57
THROUGH 62 OR CONSIDERED BY THE GOVERNMENT AUDIT AND OVERSIGHT
COMMITTEE ON JULY 16TH AND WERE FORWARDED TO THE BOARD AS
COMMITTEE REPORTS. ITEM 5057 SPECIFICALLY IS AN
ORDINANCE AMENDING THE LABOR AND EMPLOYMENT CODE TO REVISE
THE CRITERIA FOR AN EMPLOYEE IN THE CITY TO QUALIFY FOR
PARENTAL LEAVE BENEFITS UNDER THE PAID PARENTAL LEAVE
ORDINANCE BY REDUCING FROM 180 DAYS TO 90 DAYS THE MINIMUM
NUMBER OF DAYS THAT AN EMPLOYEE MUST WORK BEFORE THEY'RE
ELIGIBLE TO RECEIVE PARENTAL LEAVE BENEFITS FROM THEIR
EMPLOYER. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
PLEASE CALL ITEM 58 THROUGH 62 TOGETHER ITEMS 58 THROUGH 62 OR
5 ORDINANCES AUTHORIZING SETTLEMENT OF LAWSUITS WITH THE
CITY. ITEM 58 IS WITH PAULINE SILVA
RAY FOR 65,000 BOISE INVOLVING AN EMPLOYMENT DISPUTE.
ITEM 59 IS WITH ROBERT BLAISDELL AND DAVID PORTALES
FOR $1 MILLION INVOLVING ALLEGED PERSONAL INJURY ON A
CITY STREET. ITEM 60 IS WITH FOR THIS WITH
ALFRED MARTINEZ ENGINEERING FOR 80,000 INVOLVING ALLEGATIONS OF
BREACH OF CONTRACT ITEM 61 IS WITH AND LAW FOR A 40,000
INVOLVING AN ALLEGED PERSONAL INJURY ON THE CITY SIDEWALK
AND ITEM 62 IS A SETTLEMENT WITH SAMUEL ROSAS FOR 200,000
INVOLVING ALLEGED CIVIL RIGHTS VIOLATIONS.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST READING PLEASE CALL ITEM 63
ITEMS 63 AND 64 WERE CONSIDERED BY THE LAND USE
AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE ON JULY 20TH AND WERE FORWARDED TO
THE BOARD AS COMMITTEE REPORTS .
ITEM 63 SPECIFICALLY IS AN ORDINANCE AMENDING THE PUBLIC
WORKS CODE TO AUTHORIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS TO
RECOVER THE CITY'S COSTS FOR BIDDING ILLEGAL DUMPING THROUGH
ADMINISTRATIVE ENFORCEMENT PROCEEDINGS AGAINST PERSONS
RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ILLEGAL DUMPING AND AFFIRMING AFFIRMING
THE CINCO DETERMINATION. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
PLEASE CALL ITEM 64. >> ITEM 64 IS AN ORDINANCE
AMENDING THE PLANNING CODE TO DESIGNATE THE HOUSE OF LATIN
ROCK AS A LANDMARK CONSISTENT WITH THE STANDARDS OF ARTICLE
TEN OF THE PLANNING CODE AFFIRMING THE SCORE
DETERMINATION AND MAKING APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING PLEASE CALL ITEM 65.
>> I GUESS I'LL START WITH ITEM 65 AND 66 WERE CONSIDERED BY
THE RULES COMMITTEE ON JULY 20TH.
ITEM 65 WAS REFERRED TO THE BOARD AS A COMMITTEE REPORT
AND ITEM 66 WAS NOT SENT. ITEM 65 WAS RECOMMENDED AS
AMENDED WITH A NEW TITLE TO APPROVE THE MAYOR'S NOMINATION
FOR THE REAPPOINTMENT OF LYDIA SO TERM ENDING JUNE 30TH 2030
TO THE PLANNING COMMISSION SUPERVISOR WONG.
>> JUST WANTED TO SAY I'M PLEASED TO SUPPORT LYDIA
SEWARD'S REAPPOINTMENT TO THE PLANNING COMMISSION.
MANY OF US HAVE HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO WORK WITH LYDIA
OVER THE YEARS AND KNOW FIRSTHAND THE PROFESSIONALISM,
INTEGRITY AND STEADY LEADERSHIP SHE BRINGS TO PUBLIC SERVICE.
SHE HAS EARNED THE TRUST OF COLLEAGUES ACROSS CITY HALL
THROUGH HER THOUGHTFUL JUDGMENT AND COLLABORATIVE APPROACH
AND A WAVERING COMMITMENT TO SERVING THE PEOPLE.
CERTAINLY I WANT TO THANK LYDIA FOR HER YEARS OF DEDICATED
SERVICE TO OUR CITY AND CONGRATULATE HER ON HER
WELL-DESERVED REAPPOINTMENT NEXT.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
MOTION IS APPROVED. >> MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO
ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS. >> YES.
FIRST UP ON ROLL CALL TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS TODAY IS
SUPERVISOR CHERYL. >> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MANDEL
MIN. >> TODAY I'M INTRODUCING
LEGISLATION AND THAT AFFECTS THE WAY THAT WE PURCHASE
FIREARMS AND AMMUNITION UNDER CHAPTER 21 H.
THE CITY'S ADMINISTRATIVE CODE AND THIS IS AN UPDATE TO
LEGISLATION PASSED BY MY PREDECESSOR ASSEMBLY MEMBER
STEPHANIE THAT HAS SIMILAR BEEN ENACTED IN OTHER JURISDICTIONS.
THE POINT OF OF INTRODUCING THIS UPDATE WAS REALLY TO BUILD
ON THAT WORK AND TO MAKE SURE THAT OUR CITY UPHOLDS THE
STRINGENT STANDARDS TO WORK WITH ONLY THE MOST REPUTABLE
AND ETHICAL DEALERS IN THE COUNTRY BUT ALSO TO MAKE SURE
THAT OUR CITY DEPARTMENTS OR CITY PURCHASER CAN FOLLOW THESE
RULES EFFECTIVELY AND EFFICIENTLY AND NOT
CONSISTENTLY HAVE TO ASK FOR WORKAROUNDS.
SO I'M EXCEPT I'M EXCITED TO INTRODUCE THIS.
I'M GRATEFUL TO CITY ADMINISTRATOR CARMEN CHU, THE
CITY ADMINISTRATION'S ENTIRE OFFICE BUT ESPECIALLY THE
OFFICE OF CONTRACT ADMINISTRATION FOR WORKING
DILIGENTLY ON THIS AND I ESPECIALLY WANT TO THANK BRADY
AGAINST GUN VIOLENCE FOR THEIR PARTNERSHIP, FOR THEIR SUPPORT
FOR THE PROPOSED CHANGES IN THIS ORDINANCE
AND ESPECIALLY TO ASSEMBLY MEMBER STEPHANIE FOR LEADING
THE WAY ON THIS AND FOR HELPING US TO KIND OF CONTINUE TO
UPDATE HER WORK. THANK YOU VERY MUCH COLLEAGUES
. I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT
GOING FORWARD AND FURTHERMORE I'D LIKE TO BE RE REFERRED
FOLLOWING BOARD PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT'S COMMENTS DURING
ROLL CALL. >> THEIR ASSESSMENT THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR SHERYL SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU SUPERVISOR
WANG THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN HAS LEFT MR. PRESIDENT.
>> SURE. COULD I HAVE A MOTION TO EXCUSE
SUPERVISOR CHAN FROM THE REMAINDER OF THE MEETING MOVED
BY CHEN SECONDED BY FIELDER. WE CAN TAKE THAT WITHOUT
OBJECTION. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION.
THE SUPERVISOR IS EXCUSED AND THEN CONTINUE.
>> SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU, CARMEN.
>> I'M CLARK COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM INTRODUCING LEGISLATION THAT
ADVANCES OUR HOUSING AND POLICY GOALS FOR THE PRIORITY EQUITY
GEOGRAPHIES NEIGHBORHOODS FUND THE MISSION CHINATOWN B WILL
FILLMORE EXCELSIOR AND OCEAN ROADS ARE HOME TO COMMUNITIES
PARTICULARLY VULNERABLE TO DISPLACEMENT.
THESE ARE AREAS WHICH THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH AND OUR HOUSING ELEMENT HAVE
DEFINED AS HAVING RESIDENTS EXPERIENCING HEALTH AND HOUSING
RISKS, ECONOMIC DISADVANTAGE AND OTHER DEMOGRAPHIC
AND SOCIAL INDICATORS. WHY STATE AND LOCAL POLICY
CONTINUE TO INCENTIVIZE DEVELOPMENT WITHIN THE PRIORITY
EQUITY GEOGRAPHIES THROUGH REZONING OFFERS STATE
STREAMLINING INCENTIVES AND DENSITY BONUS PROGRAMS.
THE HOUSING ELEMENT CALLS FOR ENTITIES PLACEMENT COMMUNITY
STABILIZATION AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING STRATEGIES.
>> MY LEGISLATION HELPS ACHIEVE THIS GOAL FOR DEVELOPMENT
PROJECTS THAT TEAR DOWN EXISTING HOMES.
IT ESTABLISHES A REPLACEMENT HOUSING STANDARD BASED ON THE
PROPORTION OF LOW INCOME RENTERS TO THE OVERALL
POPULATION WITHIN THE PRIORITY EQUITY GEOGRAPHIES NOT CITYWIDE
. THE LEGISLATION ALSO ESTABLISH
AN ADDITIONAL TIER OF AFFORDABILITY EXTREMELY LOW
INCOME THAT IS MORE INCLUSIVE OF THE RANGE OF INCOMES OF
RENTERS WITH THE PRIORITY EQUITY GEOGRAPHIES.
>> WITH THIS LEGISLATION WE ARE EXPANDING OUR TOOLBOX TO KEEP
THE CITY AFFORDABLE FOR OUR MOST VULNERABLE SAN
FRANCISCANS. I LOOK FORWARD TO YOUR
CONSIDERATION AND I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR WALTON
AND FIELDER FOR HER EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP AND MY
LEGISLATIVE AIDE CHARLIE THOMAS FOR ALL HIS WORK ON THIS
AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN. SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
MADAM CLERK. >> I WOULD ASK TO BE REFERRED
AFTER THE BOARD PRESIDENT ALL RIGHT THEN WHERE WILL
SUPERVISOR FILTER? >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK
COLLEAGUES SYNTHETIC TEXT IMAGE AUDIO AND VISUAL EXTRUDERS ALSO
KNOWN AS GENERATIVE ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE HAVE CHANGED THE
MEDIA LANDSCAPE AND THEREFORE THE LANDSCAPE OF WHAT IS REAL
AND WHAT IS FAKE IN THE REALM OF INFORMATION NOW OUR EVERYDAY
FEEDS ARE FULL OF SYNTHETIC MEDIA CREATED BY LARGE LANGUAGE
MODELS THAT AS THEY BECOME MORE AND MORE SOPHISTICATED ARE
MAKING IT HARDER FOR THE AVERAGE REASONABLE PERSON TO
DECIPHER BETWEEN CONTENT THAT IS UNALTERED AND CONTENT THAT
IS ALTERED AS WELL IN THE MONTHS LEADING UP TO AN
ELECTION, VOTERS ARE FED CONSTANT STREAMS OF ADS FROM
VARIOUS CAMPAIGN COMMITTEES VIA SOCIAL MEDIA, ROBO CALLS, MASS
TEXTS, MAILERS AND MORE. THAT IS WHY I'M PLANNING TO
WORK WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY TO DETERMINE WHAT LEGISLATIVE
ACTION THE CITY CAN TAKE TO REGULATE THE USE OF SYNTHETIC
AUDIO PHOTO AND VIDEO EXTRUDERS ALSO KNOWN AS GENERATIVE AI
IN THE REALM OF FREE AND FAIR ELECTIONS USING THE LEAST
RESTRICTIVE MEANS ON FREE SPEECH AS POSSIBLE THE RUSS I
SUBMIT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M SUBMITTING A DRAFT AND REQUEST FOR REVISED
LEGISLATIVE PROPOSALS TO CONTINUE THE VISION OF THE
AFFORDABLE GROCERIES ACT FOCUSED ON THE MOST TIME
EFFICIENT COMPONENTS THAT WE CAN MOVE FORWARD ON IN THE
COMING WEEKS AND MONTHS. WHILE SAN FRANCISCANS WILL NOT
GET A CHANCE TO HAVE THEIR VOICES HEARD AT THE BALLOT BOX
ON THE ORIGINAL VERSION OF THIS PROPOSAL, WE AS A BOARD STILL
HAVE A RESPONSIBILITY TO CONTINUE TO ADDRESS THE PROBLEM
OF FOOD SECURITY DIRECTLY AS WE HAVE BEEN FOR YEARS.
>> OUR RESIDENTS DESERVE ACTION ON FOOD ACCESS AFFORDABILITY
AND THE ACTIVATION OF ZOMBIE STORIES THAT PLAGUE OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS. THE NEW AFFORDABLE GROCERIES
ACT WILL INCLUDE NEW IDEAS AND EXPAND UPON ALREADY
EXISTING PROGRAMS THAT WE KNOW MAKE A DIFFERENCE SUCH AS ONE
RESTORING FUNDING TO THE HEALTHY RETAIL SRF PROGRAM TO
CONVERT CORNER STORES INTO AFFORDABLE PRODUCE STORES
BECAUSE YOU CAN TELL A LOT ABOUT A NEIGHBORHOOD'S HEALTH
BY HOW FAR SOMEONE HAS TO WALK FOR A FRESH TOMATO.
AND IN TOO MANY PARTS OF THE CITY THAT DISTANCE KEEPS
GROWING. NUMBER TWO CREATING GROCERY
STARTUP INCENTIVES BY EXPANDING THE FIRST YEAR FREE PROGRAM TO
EXEMPT GROCERY STORES FROM BUILDING AND PLANNING PERMIT
FEES AS WELL AS EXPANSION OF THE STOREFRONT OPPORTUNITY
GRANT TO PROVIDE FUNDING FOR CAPITAL BUILD OUTS OF NEW
GROCERY STORES AND FOOD DESERTS BECAUSE IF A GROCER WANTS TO
OPEN IN A FOOD DESERT CITY HALL'S OWN PAPERWORK SHOULDN'T
BE WHAT STOPS THEM. FINALLY, ZONING CHANGES SUCH AS
LEGISLATING NEW DENSITY BONUSES FOR HOUSING DEVELOPMENTS THAT
INCORPORATE NEW GROCERY STORES ON THE GROUND FLOOR LIKE NEW
YORK CITY'S FRESH PROGRAM AND REFORMS TO MAKE
SUBDIVISIONS OF EXISTING VACANT PARCELS EASIER FOR NEW GROCERY
STORES. THIS IS A DRAFTING REQUEST
AND THE CONVERSATION WILL CONTINUE AND I HOPE IT ENDS
WITH EVERY FAMILY IN THE CITY HAVING A PLACE TO BUY FRESH
AFFORDABLE PRODUCE WITHIN WALKING DISTANCE OF THEIR HOME.
TODAY IN THAT SPIRIT I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
IN SUPPORT OF AB 1857 THE GROCERY STORE ACCESS ACT
AUTHORED BY ASSEMBLY MEMBER CECILIA AGUILAR CURRY BECAUSE
EVERY CALIFORNIA COMMUNITY DESERVES RELIABLE ACCESS TO
HEALTHY AFFORDABLE FOOD, FOOD INSECURITY ISN'T CONFINED TO
ANY ONE PART OF THE STATE. ACROSS THE BAY AREA COMMUNITIES
FROM VALLEJO TO OAKLAND TO SAN FRANCISCO HAVE WATCHED GROCERY
STORES CLOSED AND SIT VACANT FOR YEARS ZOMBIE STORES AND A
PROBLEM THAT COMPOUNDS THIS SITUATION ARE RESTRICTIVE
COVENANTS THAT LOCK OUT THE PERSON FROM EVER HOSTING A
GROCERY STORE AGAIN. WHEN A GROCERY STORE CLOSES,
COMMUNITIES SHOULD HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO ATTRACT A NEW
OPERATOR AND NOT BE BLOCKED BY THESE RESTRICTIVE COVENANTS
THAT KEEP FORMER GROCERY SITES VACANT INDEFINITELY.
AB 1857 ADDRESSES THIS NARROW BUT IMPORTANT BARRIER BY MAKING
THESE COVENANTS UNENFORCEABLE UNDER SPECIFIC CIRCUMSTANCE
THOSE WHILE PRESERVING LOCAL ZONING, PERMITTING HEALTH
AND SAFETY REQUIREMENTS ORGANIZATIONS ON THE FRONT
LINES OF HUNGER HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO INCLUDING CLYDE FACTS
AND THE SAN FRANCISCO MARIN FOODBANK HAVE ENDORSED THIS
LEGISLATION. >> THIS BILL DOESN'T REQUIRE
ANY CITY TO APPROVE A GROCERY STORE NOR DOES IT OVERRIDE
LOCAL LAND USE AUTHORITY. >> IT SIMPLY REMOVES AN
ANTI-COMPETITIVE OBSTACLE TO RESTORING GROCERY ACCESS.
>> BY ADOPTING THIS RESOLUTION, SAN FRANCISCO JOINS COMMUNITIES
ACROSS THE BAY AREA AND CALIFORNIA CALLING FOR
POLICIES THAT REDUCE FOOD INSECURITY, ENCOURAGE FAIR
COMPETITION AND PUT SHUTTERED COMMERCIAL SPACES BACK TO USE.
THANK YOU SUPPORTERS OF CHEN FOR YOUR CO-SPONSORSHIP
AND COLLEAGUES. I RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR YOUR
SUPPORT. >> THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR FOR MR. PRESIDENT.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE AN
IN MEMORIAM TO RESOLUTIONS AND AN ORDINANCE I WILL DO THE
IN MEMORIAM FIRST AND I KNOW THERE ARE OTHERS WHO WANT TO
SPEAK AFTER THAT SO WE'LL DO THAT.
THE THAT IN MEMORIAM IS FOR CLINT REILLY WHO DIED THIS PAST
WEEKEND AT AGE 79. BORN IN OAKLAND ON JANUARY 13TH
,1947, CLINT WAS THE OLDEST OF TEN CHILDREN THE SON OF A
MILKMAN AND A CONCESSION STAND OPERATOR.
HE GREW UP IN SAN LEANDRO AND ATTENDED ST PATRICK'S
SEMINARY IN MENLO PARK FOR COLLEGE, INTENDING TO BECOME A
CATHOLIC PRIEST AS PART OF HIS STUDIES, CLINT ENGAGED
IN SOCIAL JUSTICE RESEARCH AND ACTIVISM AND ALTHOUGH HE
ULTIMATELY CHOSE NOT TO PURSUE THE PRIESTHOOD AND LEFT THE
SEMINARY SEVERAL YEARS BEFORE ORDINATION, THOSE EXPERIENCES
KINDLED HIS INTEREST IN POLITICS AND ITS POWER TO
AFFECT CHANGE ON A BROAD SCALE .
IN THE 1970S HE FOUNDED CLINTON REILLY CAMPAIGNS AND PIONEERED
A NEW APPROACH TO POLITICAL CONSULTING THAT BROUGHT POLLING
VOTER DATA ADVERTISING AND PRECISELY TARGETED CAMPAIGN
MAIL UNDER ONE ROOF. HE WAS KNOWN FOR FOCUSING RACES
AROUND JUST A FEW KEY ISSUES AND COMMUNICATING THOSE ISSUES
TO VOTERS THROUGH EXPERTLY CRAFTED IF HARSH ADVERTISING
AND MESSAGING CLIFF'S TALENTS CLINT'S TALENTS AS A POLITICAL
CONSULTANT BROUGHT HIM NATIONAL RECOGNITION AND ESTABLISHED HIM
AS ONE OF THE MOST SOUGHT AFTER STRATEGISTS OVER THE COURSE OF
HIS POLITICAL CAREER HE WORKED ON CAMPAIGNS FOR SPEAKER
EMERITA NANCY PELOSI, FORMER SENATOR DIANNE FEINSTEIN
AND BARBARA BOXER, FORMER MAYOR FRANK JORDAN AND THAT'S
JUST NAMING A VERY FEW OF HIS CLIENTS.
A 1987 NEW YORK TIMES ARTICLE DESCRIBED CLINTON RILEY
CAMPAIGNS AS PERHAPS THE MOST SUCCESSFUL POLITICAL CONSULTING
FIRM OF ITS TIME. TAKE A RANDOM SAMPLING OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND SAN FRANCISCO'S CAMPAIGN CONSULTANTS TODAY
AND ODDS ARE THEY SPENT AT LEAST SOME OF THEIR CAREER
WORKING FROM WORKING FOR AND LEARNING FROM CLINT REILLY.
IN ADDITION TO RUNNING CANDIDATE CAMPAIGNS, CLINTON
HELPED MAYOR FRANK JORDAN KEEP THE SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS
AND SAN FRANCISCO AND HELPED PASS A $52 MILLION BOND TO FUND
THE CREATION OF THE ASIAN ART MUSEUM IN 1995.
HE ENDED HIS CAREER IN POLITICAL CONSULTING
AND BEGAN ONE IN REAL ESTATE. THAT YEAR HE BOUGHT THE
MERCHANTS EXCHANGE BUILDING IN THE FINANCIAL DISTRICT HOME
TO THE JULIA MORGAN BALLROOM. HE WOULD GO ON TO ACQUIRE A
NUMBER OF DOWNTOWN OFFICE BUILDINGS, EVENT SPACES
AND HOSPITALS BUSINESSES. IN 1999 HE ANNOUNCED A RUN FOR
MAYOR CITING CONCERNS ABOUT THE MANAGEMENT OF MUNI UNDER
MAYOR WILLIE BROWN. HE LOST THAT BID.
BUT HE AND MAYOR BROWN LATER SMOOTHED OVER THEIR
RELATIONSHIP AND BROWN REMEMBERS CLINT AS ABLE
AND DEDICATED AND COMMITTED. HE WAS PASSIONATE ABOUT LOCAL
MEDIA AND JOURNALISM. IN 2006 HE BROUGHT AN ANTITRUST
SUIT AGAINST MEDIA NEWS GROUP, THE DENVER BASED OWNER OF THE
MERCURY NEWS AND HEARST CORPORATION AND OWNER OF THE
S.F. CHRONICLE ALLEGING THE TWO WERE COLLUDING TO CREATE A
LOCAL MEDIA MONOPOLY. HE LATER ENTERED THE PUBLISHING
WORLD THE PUBLISHING BUSINESS HIMSELF ACQUIRING THE HILL
GAZETTE IN 2016 AND THE SAN FRANCISCO EXAMINER AND S.F.
WEEKLY IN 2020. >> THROUGHOUT HIS LIFE CLINT
THE CHILD OF WORKING CLASS PARENTS WHO HAD LIMITED
FINANCIAL RESOURCES NEVER FORGOT THE GENEROSITY OF THOSE
WHO HELPED HIM OBTAIN A CLASSICAL EDUCATION WHICH HE
CREDITED AS PROVIDING THE FOUNDATION FOR HIS LARGER THAN
LIFE CAREER. IN 2007 HE FOUNDED BAY
SCHOLARS, THEN KNOWN AS THE CLINT REILLY SCHOLARSHIP
PROGRAM TO HELP COVER TUITION COSTS FOR STUDENTS ATTENDING
CATHOLIC HIGH SCHOOLS AROUND THE BAY AREA.
SINCE ITS FOUNDING, THE PROGRAM HAS AWARDED MORE THAN $3
MILLION IN SCHOLARSHIPS TO 546 STUDENTS.
CLINT WAS FEARLESS, INNOVATIVE, CLEARLY A GENERATIONAL
POLITICAL TALENT AND HIS IMPACT ON SAN FRANCISCO CANNOT BE
OVERSTATED. HE IS SURVIVED BY HIS WIFE
JANET RILEY AND HIS DAUGHTERS JILL AND EVA.
AND OUR THOUGHTS GO OUT TO THEM.
REST IN PEACE, JANET. REST IN PEACE, CLINT RILEY.
MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING. I SEE.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY IN THE QUEUE .
I THANK YOU PRESIDENT MOUNTBATTEN FOR THAT.
EXCELLENT IN MEMORIAM FOR CLINT REILLY.
I APPRECIATE THE OPPORTUNITY TO ADD MY OWN WORDS TO YOURS
AND TO EXPRESS MY CONDOLENCES TO JANET AND JILL AND AVA AS
WELL AS TO THE MANY FRIENDS, COLLEAGUES AND EMPLOYEES WHOSE
LIVES WERE TOUCHED BY CLINT'S GENEROSITY, CONVICTION AND LOVE
FOR OUR CITY. I FIRST MET CLINT REILLY
IN 1990 WHEN I WAS A YOUNG POLITICAL OPERATIVE BRAND NEW
TO SAN FRANCISCO FROM BOSTON AND HE WAS A LEGENDARY
POLITICAL CONSULTANT WHO HAD FAMOUSLY JUST FIRED DIANNE
FEINSTEIN AS A GUBERNATORIAL CLIENT.
IT REALLY WASN'T UNTIL YEARS LATER THAT I GOT TO KNOW
CLINTON. JANET, HOWEVER, AND TRULY
APPRECIATE HOW MUCH THEY CONTRIBUTED TO OUR CITY AND TO
ITS DIVERSE COMMUNITIES. FOR ME AS A CATHOLIC, ONE OF
THE THINGS I MOST ADMIRED ABOUT CLINT WAS HIS GROUNDBREAKING
LEADERSHIP AS THE FIRST CHAIRMAN OF THE BOARD OF
CATHOLIC CHARITIES AT A TIME WHEN LAY LEADERSHIP IN THE
CHURCH WASN'T COMMON. HE REPRESENT IT A BRAND OF
LIBERAL CATHOLICISM THAT APPEALED TO ME AND THAT ABLY
DEMONSTRATED HOW FAITH AND PUBLIC SERVICE CAN
REINFORCE ONE ANOTHER WITHIN OUR CHURCH AS WELL AS WITHIN
OUR CITY. HE WAS A STRONG VOICE FOR
SOCIAL JUSTICE EVEN WHEN IT WASN'T EASY.
IN FACT FOR ME AS A GAY MAN ESPECIALLY I REALLY APPRECIATED
THE PRINCIPAL STANCE CLINT TOOK IN 2015 WHEN HE SPOKE OUT
BOLDLY AGAINST ARCHBISHOPS SALVADOR CORDILEONE OVER
APPROACHES THAT WERE HOSTILE TO THE LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY.
CLINT HELPED TO ORCHESTRATE A FULL PAGE AD IN THE SAN
FRANCISCO CHRONICLE WHOSE SIGNATORIES INCLUDED TOM BRADY
SENIOR AS WELL AS CLINT HIMSELF CALLING ON POPE FRANCIS TO
REPLACE CORDILEONE AND FOR FOSTERING QUOTE DIVISION
AND INTOLERANCE. THAT WAS ALSO NOT THE FIRST
TIME CLINT REILLY STOOD HEROICALLY AS A STRAIGHT ALLY
TO THE LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY. HANK PLANT, THE LONG TIME
BROADCAST NEWS REPORTER AND ANCHOR HERE IN THE BAY
AREA, RECALLED ON SOCIAL MEDIA THAT ONE OF CLINT'S FIRST
POLITICAL ACTS WAS TO GO DOWN TO DADE COUNTY, FLORIDA IN 1977
TO CAMPAIGN AGAINST ANITA BRYANT'S ANTI-GAY BALLOT
MEASURE. EARLIER TODAY I WAS TEXTING
WITH JOHN WHITEHURST WHO'S TWO AND A HALF YEARS WORKING FOR
CLINT TAUGHT HIM ENOUGH TO SPEND THE NEXT 35 YEARS WORKING
AS ONE OF SAN FRANCISCO'S TOP POLITICAL CONSULTANTS IN HIS
OWN RIGHT. JOHN RECALLED THAT CLINT WORKED
SIDE BY SIDE WITH A GENERATION OF GAY POLITICAL CONSULTANTS
SOME OF WHOM WERE MENTORS TO ME EARLY IN MY CAREER INCLUDING
ROBERT BARNES, JIM RIVALDO AND PAVICH.
CLINT RILEY WAS A STAUNCH ALLY TO THE LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY
AND A MAN OF COURAGE AND PRINCIPLE WHO NEVER
HESITATED TO SPEAK HIS CONSCIENCE.
HE LEAVES A VALUED AND ENDURING LEGACY TO THE CITY HE LOVED.
HE WILL BE MISSED. AND MAY HIS MEMORY BE A
BLESSING. >> SUPERVISOR CHERYL THANK YOU
BOARD PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN FOR SPONSORING THIS.
THIS IN MEMORIAM. >> YOU KNOW WHAT WHAT HAS
ALWAYS STOOD OUT ABOUT CLINT STORIES AND HOW MANY DIFFERENT
WAYS HE FOUND TO INVEST IN THIS CITY POLITICS, REAL ESTATE
JOURNALISM, PHILANTHROPY, BUILDING A FAMILY HERE AND EAST
CHAPTER. HE WAS BUILDING SOMETHING THAT
MADE SAN FRANCISCO STRONGER. TODAY LOCAL JOURNALISM IS UNDER
ENORMOUS PRESSURE BUT HIS DECISION TO PURCHASE THE
EXAMINER AND COMMIT TO ITS FUTURE INVEST IN ITS FUTURE WAS
A MEANINGFUL ACT OF CIVIC FAITH THAT I KNOW I AND SO MANY OF US
SITTING HERE HAVE DEEP APPRECIATION FOR.
THROUGH BASE SCHOLARS HE MADE SURE THAT A FAMILY'S FINANCIAL
CIRCUMSTANCES WOULD NOT BE THE DECIDING FACTOR IN WHETHER A
YOUNG PERSON IN THE BAY AREA COULD ACCESS AN EXCELLENT
EDUCATION AND AND THIS IMPACT AGAIN WAS NOT CONFINED TO ANY
ONE ARENA. HIS MARK WAS LEFT ON A WIDE
RANGE OF FIELDS AND A BREADTH OF CONTRIBUTION WHICH IS TRULY
RARE. HIS LEGACY CARRIES ON THROUGH
THE LIVES HE UPLIFTED THE INSTITUTIONS HE CREATED.
OF COURSE THE GIANTS WHO HE HELPED KEEP IN THE CITY AND THE
MANY OTHER WAYS HE DEVOTED HIMSELF TO SERVING THE CITY HE
LOVED. I WANT TO EXTEND MY CONDOLENCES
TO HIS WIFE JANET, HIS DAUGHTERS JILL AND EVAN TO ALL
WHO WORKED ALONGSIDE HIM TO MAKE THE CITY BETTER.
>> THANK YOU GUYS. >> THANK YOU COLLEAGUES.
I'LL MOVE ON TO MY RESOLUTIONS. THE FIRST IS A RESOLUTION
CELEBRATING THE 155TH ANNIVERSARY OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO CAMPUS FOR JEWISH LIVING AND COMMENDING ITS LONG
RECORD OF COMPASSIONATE CARE FOR OLDER ADULTS IN OUR CITY.
FOUNDED IN 1871 TO CARE FOR THE AGED AND INFIRM MEMBERS OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S JEWISH COMMUNITY AND FORMALLY KNOWN AS THE
JEWISH HOME TODAY THE CAMPUS ON SILVER AVENUE IS ANCHORED BY
THE JEWISH HOME AND REHABILITATION CENTER
AND THE FRANK RESIDENCES AND PROVIDES SKILLED NURSING
REHABILITATION, ASSISTED LIVING MEMORY CARE AND ONE OF NORTHERN
CALIFORNIA'S ONLY SPECIALIZED INPATIENT GERIATRIC PSYCHIATRY
UNITS. THE CAMPUS IS ONE OF THE
LARGEST NONPROFIT EMPLOYERS AND THE EXCELSIOR TRAINING THE
REGION'S NEXT GENERATION OF GERIATRIC CARE PROVIDERS
AND SERVING MORE THAN 2500 INDIVIDUALS AND FAMILIES EACH
YEAR. WORK IT CARRIES OUT FOR ANYONE
WHO NEEDS IT REGARDLESS OF ABILITY TO PAY.
I MYSELF WILL FOREVER BE GRATEFUL FOR THE CARE OF THE
JEWISH HOME PROVIDED TO MY GRANDMOTHER AND THEN TO MY
MOTHER AS THEY EACH APPROACH THE END OF THEIR LIVES.
COLLEAGUES I WANT TO THANK CO SPONSORS SUPERVISORS CHEN
MELGAR, DORSEY AND WANG AND ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT FOR THIS
RESOLUTION HONORING THE SAN FRANCISCO CAMPUS FOR JEWISH
LIVING CENTURY AND A HALF OF SERVICE TO OLDER ADULTS ACROSS
SAN FRANCISCO. I'M ALSO INTRODUCING A B TESTED
PAYMENT WAIVER RESOLUTION TO ALLOW FILM ASSAF TO PARTNER
MORE CLOSELY WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO TRAVEL ASSOCIATION
AND OUR LOCAL HOTEL INDUSTRY. OUR FILM INDUSTRY DEPENDS ON
PARTNERS ACROSS THE CITY WHO HELP US MARKET SAN FRANCISCO AS
A PREMIERE DESTINATION FOR FILM ,TELEVISION AND MEDIA
PRODUCTION. SAN FRANCISCO TRAVEL
ASSOCIATION IS ONE OF THOSE PARTNERS AND OUR HOTELS ARE
TOO. THEY WANT TO INVEST
IN PROMOTING SAN FRANCISCO AS A FILMING DESTINATION AND FILM.
ASSAF WANTS TO WORK WITH THEM. HOWEVER, SINCE SAN FRANCISCO
TRAVEL OBTAINS FILM PERMITS TO THE FILM COMMISSION IT IS
CLASSIFIED AS A RESTRICTED SOURCE.
SO FILM ITSELF IS LIMITED IN ITS ABILITY TO SOLICIT OR
ACCEPT IN-KIND SUPPORT. EVEN THOUGH PROMOTING SAN
FRANCISCO AS A FILM DESTINATION IS A SHARED OBJECTIVE, THE SAME
IS TRUE OF HOTELS. A LOCAL HOTEL RECENTLY
APPROACHED FILM ASSAF WANTING TO HOST A FILM INDUSTRY MIXER
BUT BECAUSE THAT HOTEL OBTAINED A PERMIT THROUGH THE FILM S.F.
OFFICE FILM ITSELF IS UNABLE TO SOLICIT OR ACCEPT THAT KIND OF
SUPPORT WITHOUT A WAIVER. THIS WAIVER WOULD AUTHORIZE THE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR, COMMISSIONERS AND STAFF TO
SOLICIT DONATIONS AND IN-KIND SUPPORT FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO
TRAVEL ASSOCIATION AND HOTELS FOR A LIMITED SIX MONTH PERIOD
TO SUPPORT FILM SERVICE, MARKETING AND INDUSTRY
ENGAGEMENT EFFORTS. MARKETING SAN FRANCISCO AS A
PREMIERE PRODUCTION DESTINATION IS CRITICAL TO ATTRACTING FILM
TELEVISION AND MEDIA PROJECTS THAT CREATE JOBS, GENERATE
LOCAL SPENDING AND SHOWCASE THE CITY TO AUDIENCES AROUND THE
WORLD. HOSTING INDUSTRY EVENTS,
BUILDING RELATIONSHIPS WITH PRODUCTIONS AND GETTING THE
WORD OUT THE SAN FRANCISCO IS OPEN FOR BUSINESS CAN HELP
BRING FILM, TELEVISION AND MEDIA PROJECTS HERE
AND WITH THEM THE JOBS AND SPENDING THAT FOLLOW.
SPONSORSHIPS AND IN-KIND CONTRIBUTIONS LIKE THESE ALLOW
THE FILM COMMISSION TO EXPAND ITS MARKETING AND COMMUNITY
ENGAGEMENT WORK WITHOUT RELYING SOLELY ON CITY FUNDS.
I WANT TO THANK MANAGER FATAH FROM FILM ISF AND LOREN CURRY
FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE FOR THEIR WORK ON THIS
LEGISLATION. I ALSO WANT TO THANK GRACE WANG
AND MAVE KELLY IN MY OFFICE. AND LASTLY COLLEAGUES I AM
INTRODUCING AN ORDINANCE TO UPDATE CHAPTER SEVEN OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO ENVIRONMENT CODE. CHAPTER SEVEN CODIFIES THE
CITY'S MUNICIPAL GREEN BUILDING REQUIREMENTS.
THESE UPDATES WILL PROVIDE CLEAR GUIDANCE TO CITY
DEPARTMENTS REGARDING THE DESIGN, DEVELOPMENT
AND RENOVATION OF CITY BUILDINGS AND ADVANCE THE
BUILDING SECTOR CLIMATE GOALS IN THE YEARS AHEAD.
THEY ALSO STREAMLINE EXISTING REQUIREMENTS AND ALIGN THEM
WITH INDUSTRY STANDARDS, REGULATIONS AND THE CITY'S 2026
CLIMATE ACTION PLAN. I WANT TO THANK CINDY COMERFORD
,NICK KESSLER, BARRY HOOPER, ALICE HER AND CHARLES SHEEHAN
AT THE DEPARTMENT THE ENVIRONMENT FOR THEIR WORK ON
THIS UPDATE. I'D ALSO LIKE TO THANK ROB
KAPLAN FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE AND GRACE WANG FROM MY
OFFICE AND THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
I'D LIKE TO BE ADDED TO THE IN MEMORIAM FOR FOR CLINT
REILLY. I ALSO LIKE YOU SUPERVISOR
DORSEY WORKED FOR CLINT IN 1994 WHILE CLINT WAS RUNNING
KATHLEEN BROWN'S CAMPAIGN FOR GOVERNOR WHICH SHE WAS
ULTIMATELY DEFEATED BY PETE WILSON UNFORTUNATELY BUT WILL
ALWAYS REMEMBER HIS MENTORSHIP. MANY MANY VERY STRATEGIC
AND INTERESTING CONVERSATIONS EVEN ONES WHEN WE DISAGREED
AND SEND ALL THE LOVE TO JANET AND HIS FAMILY AND THE REST I
SUBMIT THANK YOU. >> AND ACTUALLY MAYBE WE CAN
HAVE THAT COME FROM THE FULL BOARD AS WELL.
SO LET'S HAVE THAT BE FROM THE FULL BOARD.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MILK OUR SUPERVISOR
SAUTER THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT. SENOR THEIR NAMES ON THE
ROSTER. >> LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT
AT THIS TIME THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES GENERAL
PUBLIC COMMENT IN PERSON SPEAKERS WILL BE PRIORITIZED SO
PLEASE LINE UP ON THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER DURING
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT YOU MAY SPEAK TO APPROVAL THE JUNE 16TH
BOARD MEETING MINUTES ITEM 69 THROUGH 75 THE ITEMS UNDER THE
FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE GENDA AND OTHER
GENERAL MATTERS THAT ARE NOT ON TODAY'S AGENDA BUT MUST BE
WITHIN THE BOARD'S SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION FOR SPEAKER
POLICE OH OH. >> OH.
NOT QUITE. HI EVERYBODY AGAIN.
MY NAME IS AMELIA AND I HAVE RETURNED TO SPEAK ON THE
REMOVAL OF THE PIER COUNSELORS FROM THE STREET CRISIS RESPONSE
TEAM. IN MY INDIVIDUAL CAPACITY I
HAVE PROVIDED EACH OF YOU A PROBLEM SOLVING FRAMEWORK TO
BREAK THROUGH THE SILOS BETWEEN OUR FIRST RESPONSE HEALTH CARE,
SOCIAL SERVICE AND HOMELESSNESS SYSTEMS TO FIX THIS.
AND THANK YOU TO THE FIVE SUPERVISORS OFFICES THAT HAVE
ALREADY ENGAGED WITH ME AND MY COLLEAGUES.
ONE OF THE CLINICIANS FROM AND YOU H.W. SAID EARLIER
SOMETHING ALONG THE LINES OF THE BEGINNING OF THE CARE
JOURNEY IS WHERE YOU NEED TO INSPIRE HOPE.
AND I CAN'T MAKE A BETTER I CANNOT MAKE A BETTER CASE FOR
KEEPING PEERS ON STREET CRISIS NATIONAL RESEARCH ON CERTIFIED
PEER SUPPORT CONSISTENTLY SHOWS REDUCED REPEAT EMERGENCY CALLS
AND BETTER ENGAGEMENT AND CARE. A NINE ON ONE ENGAGEMENT THAT
ENDS IN REFUSAL IS TAXPAYER MONEY SPENT TWICE MAYBE THREE,
FIVE, TEN TIMES OVER AGAIN EVERY AVOIDED AMBULANCE,
TRANSPORT AND EMERGENCY ROOM VISIT IS GENERAL FUND MONEY
REMOVING PEERS DOESN'T CUT COSTS IT MOVES COST TO THE MOST
EXPENSIVE PARTS OF THE SYSTEM. I AM INTERESTED IN WORKING
UPSTREAM IN THE PROVIDED FRAMEWORK I HAVE INCLUDED A
MECHANISM FOR MEDI-CAL REIMBURSEMENT FOR PEER
SERVICES. MY FIRST ASK BEFORE THE RECESS
SIGN A LETTER TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE REQUESTING HE CONVENE
APPROPRIATE STAKEHOLDERS AND PAUSE THE RESTRUCTURING
PENDING INTERDEPARTMENTAL REVIEW.
IF THIS DOES NOT SUFFICE I ASK THE RULES COMMITTEE TO CALENDAR
A HEARING TO EVALUATE THE PROGRAM AND PROPOSED FRAMEWORK.
I FURTHER ASK THE BUDGET AND APPROPRIATIONS OVERSIGHT
AND TO REQUIRE OUTCOME DATA BEFORE THIS PROGRAM CHANGES
AGAIN IN THE FUTURE. IN THIS HARD FOUGHT MOMENT OF
GROWTH FOR A 24 HOUR CRISIS CONTINUUM OF CARE, WE CANNOT
AFFORD TO LOSE THE CRITICAL FUNCTION OF PEERS INSPIRING
PEOPLE TO ACCEPT THE SERVICES WE NOW HAVE.
I ASK THIS LEGISLATIVE BODY PAUSE EXAMINE AND MEASURE.
WE HAVE TO ACT PROPORTIONATELY ACROSS THE SYSTEM OF CARE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO.
THIS IS A POEM I WROTE RECENTLY AS A SAN FRANCISCAN TURNED OUT
TO HAVE AN ANEURYSM. >> IT'S JUST A POEM.
ANOTHER MAN, A FATHER AND IMMIGRANTS FROM MEXICO WITH
COPPER SKIN WAS HUNTED DOWN AND MURDERED BY ICE.
>> AGAIN, I SEE ONE OF HIS ADULT KIDS SPEAKING INTO
CAMERAS IN ANGUISH CRYING THAT HIS FATHER DIDN'T DESERVE THIS.
THEY BREAK MY HEART BREAKING THROUGH BRICK SQUEEZING TEARS
FROM CONCRETE TOMBS. I FEEL WHEN I SEE MEMORIALIZED
FATHER MOURNING FAMILY ABSOLUTE EVIL SANCTIONS EVIL WORSE THAN
ROAMING TARGETED AIR SURVEILLANCE POWERED HUNTING
IN THE STREETS. I THINK OF HERE MY HOME EMPTY
STREETS INVISIBLE EVIL VANISHED IMMIGRATION COURTS DEFUNDED
RAPID RESPONSE NETWORK S.F. PD TARGETING HUMANS AND TRANS VIA
AIR SURVEILLANCE POWERED REAL-TIME RESPONSE CENTER CHRIS
LARSON FUNDED DRONES AND CAMERAS HOUSED IN DONALD
TRUMP'S TOWER SWARMS OF SFPD INDISTINGUISHABLE FROM ICE
TACKLE AND ATTACK PEOPLE WHO DIDN'T DESERVE THIS.
>> MY TEARS ARE FROZEN. IT'S TOO COLD HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO HOT TEXAS EXPANDING ICE MELTS ME COLD CALIFORNIA
EXPANDING TRANSPHOBIA FREEZE ME FIGHT FLIGHT FON CLAMMY PANIC
QUIETS PANIC SCREAM WHERE WE'RE UNCIVIL AND LOUD MOUTHED IF WE
DO A FROZEN BRICK AN EXPLODING BROOK IS SILENCE BRICK
ASSAILING BRICK AN UPRIGHT BRICK, A BLOOD RED BRICK A
HISTORICAL BRICK AN EXTENSION OF MY BEING ATOMS EARTH BONDED
IN DIFFERENT FORMATIONS WITH DIFFERENT PROPERTIES MINGLING
ELECTRONS EXCHANGE BETWEEN ME AND BRICK MY MUSCLE STRAIN THE
LONGER I GRIP THIS COMPACT COLLECTION OF ORGANIZED ATOMS
POTENTIAL ENERGY IGNITES. >> ALSO YOU HAVE A COLLEAGUE
SPEWING RACIST, ISLAMOPHOBIC ANTI TRANSPHOBIC TROPES
AND NOW RED SCARE RHETORIC. YET I DON'T REALLY SEE ANYONE
COUNTERING HIS FEARMONGERING. I SAY 1 OR 2 SUPERVISORS
SOMETIMES SO YOUR SILENCE ALLOWS A CULTURE OF BIGOTRY
AND REPRESSION TO FLOURISH. >> AND IF YOU DON'T AGREE WITH
ANY OF THAT YOU SHOULD BE AN ADULT.
USE YOUR WORDS AND SAY SOMETHING.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER MY NAME IS RICHARD
S.G. PETERSON. >> TRIBUTE TO CLINT RILEY.
IF YOU'VE EVER REALLY SPENT TIME WITH HIM AND I OVER THE
YEARS SPENT SOME TIME WITH HIM HE'S THE GREATEST PHONE BOOTH
KNIFE FIGHTER IN SAN FRANCISCO HISTORY.
>> >> THE GOOD NEWS FOR ME IS THAT I THINK I STILL HAVE MY
LICENSE TO PRACTICE LAW AND THE BAD NEWS FOR MANY OF YOU OR
SOME OF YOU IS THAT I'VE GOT MY LICENSE TO PRACTICE LAW.
THE REASON I HAVE THIS LITTLE DEMONSTRATION HERE IS HOW EASY
IT IS TO INTERRUPT EVEN WHEN YOU THINK YOU HAVE EVERYTHING
SET UP IN A LAW OFFICE. >> THIS IS AN OPTICAL FIBER.
IT CAN BE CUT WITH A SIMPLE TOENAIL CLIP PUT YOU DOWN,
TAKES A WEEK BEFORE YOU GET EVEN SERVICE TO COME OUT THERE
AND LOOK AT WHAT'S HAPPENING TO YOUR PROBLEM.
>> THERE ARE A LOT OF ISSUES IN SAN FRANCISCO AND I THINK
THEY CAN BE TAKEN DOWN BY I THINK A SIMPLE SNIP OF THESE
LITTLE FIBER OPTIC CABLES SO SOME ATTENTION NEEDS TO BE PAID
TO THAT. BUT I WANT TO LET YOU GUYS GO
BEFORE I RAMBLE ON AND HAVE A NICE WEEKEND.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
ARE THERE ANY OTHER INDIVIDUALS WHO WOULD LIKE TO PROVIDE
PUBLIC COMMENT IN PERSON? >> SEEING NONE WE'LL GO TO THE
REMOTE CALL IN LINE IF YOU HAVE NOT ALREADY.
SHOUT OUT TO MAMIE HAAS. >> LOVE YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT. IF YOU HAVE NOT ALREADY DONE SO
PLEASE PRESS STAR THREE TO LINE UP REMOTELY.
AS I PREVIOUSLY STATED, PERSONAL ATTACKS, HARASSMENT OR
DISCRIMINATORY REMARKS WILL RESULT IN THE SPEAKER
FORFEITING THE REMAINING TIME AND WE WILL MOVE ON TO THE NEXT
SPEAKER. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR FIRST
REMOTE CALLER. >> NO NAME IS GORE ALL OF A
SUDDEN AND NOT LIVE UP AT MODOC COUNTY IN THE STATE OF
JEFFERSON. I WANT TO TALK ABOUT WOW IN OUR
LIFE HERE IN CALIFORNIA AND BEING FRAMED FRAN
SPECIFICALLY I HATE. I HATE HIM SO MUCH.
THEY BEAT OUR GIRLS IN SPORT. THEY BEAT BULL FEMALE GUIDE
JAIL INMATE BREATHING AND THEY WEIGH THEIR BEATS AND RAN INTO
MEN WELL WELL BASICALLY IT'S A THREE I'LL LEAVE IT AT EAT IF
THEY BOTH WANT PAID AND YOU NAME WHO YOU WERE THEN THERE
REASON YOU GAVE IT MEN WERE MEN AND IF ANY OF THESE IT'S GOOD
THING TRAINEES IN A RESTROOM WITH MY WIFE THEY WILL HAVE A
BAD TIME. CALIFORNIA SILVER APPEALED
THROUGH SPACE ALL RIGHTS FOR TRAINEES AND LOCK THEM UP
IN THE INSTITUTIONS. GOD BLESS AMERICA AND GOD BLESS
OUR ATTORNEY PORTEOUS IS DONALD TRAPPED?
DO WE HAVE ANY OTHER CALLERS ON THE REMOTE CALL IN LINE.
SEE NONE. >> I REMAIN UNPERSUADED THAT
THIS WAS A GOOD IDEA WITHOUT PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED.
ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE FOR ADOPTION WITH THAT
COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEM 16 THROUGH 75 TOGETHER.
>> YES. ITEM 609 THROUGH 75 WERE
INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE A UNANIMOUS
VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST
APPEARANCE ANY SUPERVISOR MAY REQUIRE RESOLUTION ON FIRST
READING TO GO TO COMMITTEE ON SUPERVISOR CHERYL SEVER NUMBER
70 PLEASE. >> OKAY THAT'S IT.
>> MADAM CLERK CAN YOU CALL THE ROLL ON THE REMAINING BALANCE
OF THE ITEMS ON THE REMAINING BALANCE MINUS ITEM 70
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR FOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR BENJAMIN HIGH
MENDHAM IN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR
SARDAR EITHER NICE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED AND THE MOTION IS APPROVED PLEASE CALL ITEM 70.
ITEM 70 IS A RESOLUTION SUPPORTING CALIFORNIA STATE
ASSEMBLY BILL NUMBER 2564 WHICH WOULD PROHIBIT RETAILERS FROM
ENGAGING IN SURVEILLANCE PRICING.
>> SUPERVISOR CHERYL THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT FIRST
AND FOREMOST I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR BRINGING
THIS UP. I THINK THE POINT OF MAYBE 2564
TO MAKE SURE THAT COMPANIES ARE NOT JACKING UP PRICES ON
CONSUMERS BASED ON ANY NUMBER OF THINGS IS FANTASTIC.
I HAVE SOME QUESTIONS SPECIFICALLY REGARDING SOME
AMENDMENTS THAT ARE GOING AROUND IN SACRAMENTO TO ADDRESS
CONCERNS ABOUT KIND OF LET'S LET'S CALL IT INADVERTENTLY
PROHIBITING COMPANIES FROM ISSUING DISCOUNTS BASED ON
RECENT PURCHASES. >> SO JUST TO GET SOME TIME TO
ADDRESS THOSE CONCERNS AND MAKE SURE OF THAT, I'D LIKE TO JUST
SEND THIS ITEM TO COMMITTEE. ALL RIGHT.
IT'S GOING TO COMMITTEE AFTER I GAVEL ON THAT.
OKAY. AND I THINK THE LAST TIME I DID
THIS I GOT IN TROUBLE BECAUSE I ALLOWED FOR DIALOG AT THIS
MOMENT WHICH I DON'T THINK WE GET TO DO.
SO I THINK IT'S GONE TO COMMITTEE.
ALL RIGHT. AND DO WE HAVE HOW LONG DO YOU
THINK IT'S GOING TO TAKE US TO GET THE RESULTS?
>> WE DO HAVE THE SERGEANT AT ARMS CHECKING TO SEE WHAT THE
DEPARTMENT OF ELECTIONS OH, WE HAVE A WE JUST WALKED IN.
>> ARE YOU DONE? YOU'RE READY.
>> OKAY THEN WE WILL GO BACK TO 54.
THANK YOU. PEARSON US OKAY WE'RE NOW GOING
BACK TO ITEM 54. >> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
READ THE RESULTS OF THE ELECTION?
YES, SIR. YOU THE RETURNED WEIGHTED
BALLOTS VOTING FOR THE DOWNTOWN COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT WAS
85.15% IN THE RETURN WEIGHTED BALLOTS VOTING AGAINST THE
DOWNTOWN CBD WAS 14.85% FURTHER INDICATING THERE WAS NO
MAJORITY PROTEST. >> SO THERE IS NO MAJORITY
PROTESTS AND THEREFORE MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON ITEM 54 YES ON ITEM 54 SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR FOR WALTON HIGH WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDARIN HAI MENDHAM AND I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SARDAR EITHER TENNIS WITHOUT OBJECTION
THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED AND THAT TAKES US I BELIEVE TO
OUR IMPERATIVE AGENDA. >> DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE
AGENDA ITEMS? MADAM CLERK WE HAVE NO
IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS TODAY THEN COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE
IN MEMORIAM? YES.
TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE
FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS ON BEHALF OF PRESIDENT
MANAGEMENT AND THE ENTIRE BOARD FOR THE LATE MR. CLINT RILEY.
I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA.
MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US
TODAY? >> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS
FOR TODAY. WE ARE ADJOURNED